<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit Upgrades for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MOSCOW_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Muscovites</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Les Russes</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Moskowiter:Die Moskowiter:den Moskowitern</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Male:Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1:1:1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>I Persiani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Los Persas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#204;&#238;&#241;&#234;&#238;&#226;&#232;&#242;&#251;</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MOSCOW_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Muscovy</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Russe</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Moskau</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Persia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Persia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#204;&#238;&#241;&#234;&#226;&#224;</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MOSCOW_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Muscovy</English>
		<French>
			<Text>russe:russe:russes:russes</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Moskowitisch:moskowitischen:moskowitische</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>persiano:persiana:persiani:persiane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>persa:persa:persas:persas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#204;&#238;&#241;&#234;&#238;&#226;&#241;&#234;&#232;&#233;</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS00</Tag>
		<English>Muscovite Peoples</English>
		<French>Peuplade Moscovite</French>
		<German>Moskowitische Völker</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS01</Tag>
		<English>Principality of Moscow</English>
		<French>Principaut&#233; de Moscou</French>
		<German>Fürstentum Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS02</Tag>
		<English>Grand Duchy of Moscow</English>
		<French>Grand-Duch&#233; de Moscou</French>
		<German>Großfürstentum Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS03</Tag>
		<English>Tsardom of Russia</English>
		<French>Tsarie de Russie</French>
		<German>Zarenreich Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS04</Tag>
		<English>Tsardom of Russia</English>
		<French>Tsarie de Russie</French>
		<German>Zarenreich Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS05</Tag>
		<English>Russian Republic</English>
		<French>R&#233;publique Russe</French>
		<German>Russische Republik</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS06</Tag>
		<English>Placeholder Error</English>
		<French>Placeholder Error</French>
		<German>Placeholder Error</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS07</Tag>
		<English>Placeholder Error</English>
		<French>Placeholder Error</French>
		<German>Placeholder Error</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS08</Tag>
		<English>Islamic Tsardom of Russia</English>
		<French>Tsarie Islamique de Russie</French>
		<German>Islamisches Zarenreich Russland</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS09</Tag>
		<English>Russian Islamic Republic</English>
		<French>R&#233;publique Islamique Russe</French>
		<German>Russische Islamische Republik</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS10</Tag>
		<English>Exarchate of Moscovia</English>
		<French>Exarchat de Moscovie</French>
		<German>Exarchat Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS11</Tag>
		<English>Duchy of Muscovy</English>
		<French>Duch&#233; de Moscovie</French>
		<German>Herzogtum Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS12</Tag>
		<English>Emirate of Moscow</English>
		<French>Emirat de Moscou</French>
		<German>Emirat Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS13</Tag>
		<English>Spanish Muscovy</English>
		<French>Moscovie Espagnol</French>
		<German>Spanisch-Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS14</Tag>
		<English>Norse Muscovy</English>
		<French>Moscovie Nordique</French>
		<German>Nordisch-Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS15</Tag>
		<English>Venetian Muscovy</English>
		<French>Moscovie V&#233;nitienne</French>
		<German>Venezianisch-Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS16</Tag>
		<English>Vladimir-Suzdal</English>
		<French>Principaut&#233; de Vladimir-Suzdal</French>
		<German>Fürstentum Wladimir-Susdal</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS17</Tag>
		<English>German Muscovy</English>
		<French>Moscovie Allemande</French>
		<German>Deutsch-Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS18</Tag>
		<English>Counties of Muscovy</English>
		<French>Comt&#233;es de Moscovie</French>
		<German>Counties Moskaus</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS19</Tag>
		<English>Habsburg Muscovy</English>
		<French>Moscovie Habsbourg</French>
		<German>Habsburger Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS20</Tag>
		<English>Principality of Moskova</English>
		<French>Principaut&#233; de Moskova</French>
		<German>Fürstentum Moskova</German>
		><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_MOS21</Tag>
		<English>Province of Muscovy</English>
		<French>Province de Moscovie</French>
		<German>Provinz Moskau</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_IVAN_IV</Tag>
		<English>Ivan IV</English>
		<French>Ivan IV</French>
		<German>Iwan IV.</German>
		<Italian>Ivan IV</Italian>
		<Spanish>Iván IV</Spanish>
		<Russian>Ivan IV</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_IVAN_IV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Ivan "the Terrible" IV[\H1]
[BOLD]First Tsar of Russia[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] August 25, 1530 - March 18 1584


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	Ivan IV was the Grand Duke of Muscovy from 1533 to 1547 and was the first ruler of Russia to assume the title of tsar. His long reign saw the conquest of Kazan Khanate and Siberia and subsequent transformation of Russia into a multiethnic and multiconfessional state. This tsar retains his place in the Russian tradition simply as Ivan Grozny, which is traditionally translated into English as Ivan the Terrible.
[TAB]Ivan (or Ioann, as his name is rendered in Church Slavonic) was a long-awaited son of Vasili III. Upon his father's death, he formally came to the throne at the age of three, but his minority was dominated by regents. Initially his mother Elena Glinskaya acted as regent, but she died when Ivan was only eight. She was replaced as regent by boyars from the Shuisky family until Ivan assumed power in 1544. According to his own letters, Ivan customarily felt neglected and offended by the mighty boyars from the Shuisky and Belsky families. These traumatic experiences may have contributed to his hatred of the boyars and to his mental instability. He was known to throw cats and dogs out of the Kremlin windows, among other cruel acts.
[TAB]Ivan was crowned king with Monomakh's Cap at the Cathedral of the Dormition at age sixteen on January 16, 1547. Despite calamities triggered by the Great Fire of 1547, the early part of his reign was one of peaceful reforms and modernization. Ivan revised the law code (known as the sudebnik), created a standing army (the streltsy), established the first Russian parliament of the feudal estates (the Zemsky Sobor), the council of the nobles (known as the Chosen Council), and confirmed the position of the Church with the Council of the Hundred Chapters, which unified the rituals and ecclesiastical regulations of the entire country. He introduced the local self-management in rural regions, mainly in the Northeast of Russia, populated by the state peasantry. During his reign the first printing press was introduced to Russia (although the first Russian printers Ivan Fedorov and Pyotr Mstislavets had to flee from Moscow to the Grand Duchy of Lithuania).
[TAB]Ivan formed new trading connections, opening up the White Sea and the port of Arkhangelsk to the Muscovy Company of English merchants. In 1552 he defeated the Kazan Khanate, whose armies had repeatedly devastated the Northeast of Russia, and annexed its territory. In 1556, he annexed the Astrakhan Khanate and destroyed the largest slave market on the river Volga. These conquests complicated the migration of the aggressive nomadic hordes from Asia to Europe through Volga and transformed Russia into a multinational and multiconfessional state. He had St. Basil's Cathedral constructed in Moscow to commemorate the seizure of Kazan. Legend has it that he was so impressed with the structure that he had the architects blinded, so that they could never design anything as beautiful again.
[TAB]Other less positive aspects of this period include the introduction of the first laws restricting the mobility of the peasants, which would eventually lead to serfdom. The dramatic change in Ivan's personality is traditionally linked to his near-fatal illness in 1553 and the death of his first wife, Anastasia Romanovna in 1560. Ivan suspected boyars of poisoning his wife and of plotting to replace him on the throne with his cousin, Vladimir of Staritsa. In addition, during that illness Ivan had asked the boyars to swear an oath of allegiance to his eldest son, an infant at the time. Many boyars refused, deeming the tsar's health too hopeless to survive. This angered Ivan and added to his distrust of the boyars. There followed brutal reprisals and murders of innocent people, including Metropolitan Philip and Prince Alexander Gorbatyi-Shuisky.
[TAB]Also problematic was the 1565 formation of the Oprichnina. The Oprichnina was the section of Russia (mainly the Northeast) directly ruled by Ivan and policed by his personal servicemen, the Oprichniki. This whole system of Oprichnina has been viewed by some historians as a tool against the omnipotent hereditary nobility of Russia (boyars) who opposed the absolutist drive of the tsar, while others have interpreted it as a sign of the paranoia and mental deterioration of the tsar.
[TAB]The later half of Ivan's reign was far less successful. Although Khan Devlet I Giray of Crimea repeatedly devastated Moscow region and even set Moscow on fire in 1571, the tsar supported Yermak's conquest of Tatar Siberia, adopting a policy of empire-building, which led him to launch a victorious war of seaward expansion to the west, only to find himself fighting the Swedes, Lithuanians, Poles, and the Livonian Teutonic Knights.
[TAB]For twenty-four years the Livonian War dragged on, damaging the Russian economy and military and failing to gain any territory for Russia. In the 1560s the combination of drought and famine, Polish-Lithuanian raids, Tatar invasions, and the sea-trading blockade carried out by the Swedes, Poles and the Hanseatic League devastated Russia. The price of grain increased by a factor of ten. Epidemics of the plague killed 10,000 in Novgorod. In 1570 the plague killed 600-1000 in Moscow daily. Ivan's closest advisor, Prince Andrei Kurbsky, defected to the Lithuanians, headed the Lithuanian troops and devastated the Russian region of Velikiye Luki. This treachery deeply hurt Ivan. As the Oprichnina continued, Ivan became mentally unstable and physically disabled. In one week, he could easily pass from the most depraved orgies to prayers and fasting in a remote northern monastery.
[TAB]Because he gradually grew unbalanced and violent, the Oprichniks under Malyuta Skuratov soon got out of hand and became murderous thugs. They massacred nobles and peasants, and conscripted men to fight the war in Livonia. Depopulation and famine ensued. What had been by far the richest area of Russia became the poorest. In a dispute with the wealthy city of Novgorod, Ivan ordered the Oprichniks to murder inhabitants of this city, which was never to regain its former prosperity. Between thirty and forty thousand might have been killed during the infamous Massacre of Novgorod in 1570; many others were deported elsewhere. Yet the official death toll named 1,500 of Novgorod big people (nobility) and only mentioned about the same number of smaller people. Many modern researchers estimate number of victims between two and three thousand. (After the famine and epidemics of 1560s the population of Novgorod did not exceed 10,000-20,000.)
[TAB]In 1581, Ivan beat his pregnant daughter-in-law for wearing immodest clothing, causing a miscarriage. His son, also named Ivan, upon learning of this, engaged in a heated argument with his father, which resulted in Ivan striking his son in the head with his pointed staff, causing his son's (accidental) death. This event is depicted in the famous painting by Ilya Repin, Ivan the Terrible and his son Ivan on Friday, November 16, 1581 better known as Ivan the Terrible killing his son.
[TAB]Although it is thought by many that Ivan died while setting up a chess board, it is more likely that he died while playing chess with Bogdan Belsky on March 18, 1584. When Ivan's tomb was opened during renovations in the 1960s, his remains were examined and discovered to contain very high amounts of mercury, indicating a high probability that he was poisoned. Modern suspicion falls on his advisors Belsky and Boris Godunov (who became tsar in 1598). Three days earlier, Ivan had allegedly attempted to rape Irina, Godunov's sister and Feodor's wife. Her cries attracted Godunov and Belsky to the noise, whereupon Ivan let Irina go, but Belsky and Godunov considered themselves marked for death. The tradition says that they either poisoned or strangled Ivan in fear for their own lives. The mercury found in Ivan's remains may also be related to treatment for syphilis, which it is speculated that Ivan had. Upon Ivan's death, the ravaged kingdom was left to his unfit and childless son Feodor.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Iwan "der Schrecklicher" IV.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Erster Zar Russlands[NEWLINE]Lebte: [\BOLD] 1530 - 1584

[TAB][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD]
[TAB]Der Sohn Wassilis III., geboren am 25. August 1530 in Moskau, verlor im Alter von drei Jahren seinen Vater und wurde nach blutigen Machtkämpfen zwischen Gruppen der Bojaren 1547 nach byzantinischem Zeremoniell zum Zaren gekrönt. Er stärkte die Zentralgewalt durch Reformen von Verwaltung, Rechtswesen und Armee und förderte den niederen Dienstadel auf Kosten der mächtigen Bojaren.
[TAB]Mit der Eroberung der Khanate Kasan 1552 und Astrachan 1556 dehnte er seinen Einfluß bis Sibirien aus. Im Westen scheiterte er jedoch bei dem Versuch, in Livland einen Zugang zur Ostsee zur erkämpfen. Der dadurch ausgelöste langandauernde Krieg mit Polen-Litauen und Schweden 1558-83 ruinierte die Wirtschaft.
[TAB]Mißtrauisch bis zum Verfolgungswahn, unterdrückte der Zar jede Unbotmäßigkeit mit brutalen Strafgerichten. Als Terrorinstrument hatte er sich 1565 die Truppe der Opritschnina geschaffen. In einem Wutanfall erschlug er sogar seinen eigenen Sohn.
[TAB]Andererseits war er hochgebildet und literarisch begabt. Bei seinem Tod am 18. März 1584 in Moskau war der Staat so zerrüttet, dass er wenig später zusammenbrach.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
