<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by XMLSPY 2004 Professional Ed. Release 2, Installed Multi + SMP for 3 users (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text Objects -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPEARMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Since a Medieval spear required only a small amount of steel along the sharpened edges, it was an economical weapon. Quick to manufacture, and needing less smithing skill than a sword, it became the common weapon of the peasantry in many parts of the world. With the rise of heavy cavalry, spear shafts began to be planted against the ground to deter charging cavalry. Spears morphed into different pole-arms as mounted knights became more important on the battlefields of Europe and a means to counter them was needed.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Depuis le moyen-age, les lances exig&#233;es seulement une petite quantit&#233; d'acier le long des bords aiguis&#233;s, il s'agissait d'une arme &#233;conomique. Rapide &#224; fabriquer, et n&#233;cessitant moins d'habilet&#233; forge d'un sabre, il est devenu l'arme commune de la paysannerie dans de nombreuses r&#233;gions du monde. Avec la mont&#233;e de la cavalerie lourde, les lances ont commenc&#233; &#224; &#234;tre plant&#233;s sur le sol pour emp&#234;cher la cavalerie. Ces lances sont devenus de plus en plus important sur les champs de bataille d'Europe.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GUISARME_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A guisarme was a pole weapon used in Europe to dismount knights and horsemen, primarily between 1000-1400. Like most polearms it was developed by peasants by combining hand tools with long poles: in this case by putting a pruning hook onto a spear shaft. Later designs implemented a small reverse spike on the back of the blade, increasing the weapon's stopping power. Eventually hooks were incorporated into a variety of different polearms and guisarme became a catch-all for any weapon that included a hook on the blade.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un Guisarme &#233;tait une arme utilis&#233;es en Europe pour mettre pied &#224; terre les chevaliers et les cavaliers, surtout entre 1000-1400. Comme la plupart des armes d'hast il a &#233;t&#233; d&#233;velopp&#233; par des paysans en combinant des outils &#224; main avec de longues perches: dans ce cas en mettant une serpette sur un axe de lance. Derniers mod&#232;les mis en oeuvre, un petit clou sur le dos de la lame qui permit l'augmentation du pouvoir d'arr&#234;t de l'arme. </French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PIKEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Early in the middle ages, the pike was only useful on defense; its length made it difficult for untrained soldiers to use in formation. The Swiss brought a renaissance to pike warfare in the 15th century, with strong training regimens and drummers to aid coordination. Now pike blocks could both rise to the attack and go into an impenetrable defensive formation when attacked by cavalry. The deep pike attack column remained an essential part of infantry combat for several hundred years.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Au d&#233;but du Moyen Age, le piquier a &#233;t&#233; utile que sur la d&#233;fense, et sa longueur, il &#233;tait difficile pour les soldats non entraîn&#233;s &#224; utiliser en formation. Les suisses ont lanc&#233; une renaissance du piquier avec la guerre au 15&#232;me si&#232;cle, avec des sch&#233;mas de formation solide et des batteurs de coordination de l'aide. Les piquiers pouvait &#224; la fois &#234;tre utiliser &#224; l'attaque et aller dans une formation d&#233;fensive imp&#233;n&#233;trable quand on est attaqu&#233; par la cavalerie. En definitive les piquiers sont rest&#233;es un &#233;l&#233;ment essentiel du combat d'infanterie pour plusieurs centaines d'ann&#233;es.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SWORDSMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Swords in antiquity and classical times tended to be relatively short, at first because they were made of bronze and later because they were rarely called upon to penetrate armor. The blade of the classic Roman stabbing sword, the gladius, was only some two feet long, though in the twilight years of the empire the gladius gave way to the spatha, the long slashing sword of the barbarians and forerunner of the great broadswords of medieval Europe. During the Early Middle Ages, European swords tended to be long and straight, with no crossguard to protect the wielder's hand.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LONG_SWORDSMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Longsword is a type of European sword used during the late medieval period. Made to counter the increasingly strong armor of the time, the longsword was commonly held in combat with both hands, though some may be used single-handed. A man-at-arms or dismounted knight fighting with a longsword would also have worn substantial other armor, such as a mail hauberk and helm. The terms "hand-and-a-half sword", "greatsword", and "bastard sword" are used colloquially to refer to longswords in general.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SCOUT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Light cavalry have been employed as scouts and skirmisher from ancient times. The only real requirement for these units is that they be able to cover great distances and escape from situations in which they would be killed. Specially trained or bred horses are not required, and the unit needs to be only minimally armored. Before the development of the stirrup and other equestrian technology, it took years to learn to fight from horseback effectively, not a worthwhile investment for scouting units.</English>
		<French></French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOUNTED_SEARGENT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A seargent, or serjeant, was a man of lesser rank and wealth to a knight, but with comparable equipment and training. Serjeants could fight either as heavy or light cavalry, and here fulfill that secondary role. Serjeants ranked above the common man-at-arms on the social scale. Although the social structure of the Norman society of England was generally static, the easiest manner for a man to attain social rank and improve his standing was through military service, as the Norman states, unlike the Germanic ones, believed in knighting men of common birth who demonstrated nobility and courage on the field.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HORSE_ARCHER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A horse archer is a cavalryman armed with a bow. Because using a bow requires a horseman to let go of the reins with both hands, horse archers need superb equestrian skills and horse archery is typically associated with steppe nomads. The weapon of choice for horse archers was the recurve bow, which is compact enough to shoot from a horse yet retained sufficient range and penetrating power. Mounted archers needed little or no armor and could ride light, fast mounts.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PISTOLIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Pistols were the first gunpowder weapons developed for cavalry, and the pistoliers was one of the new cavalry types to develop which signaled the end of the lance-charging heavy cavalry. Pistoliers were expected to be able to engage their opponents both with firearms and sword; they formed up in deep blocks and used their firearms in a caracole attack to disrupt enemy infantry formations before charging home and engaging in hand-to-hand combat. German mercenary cavalry called Reiters or "Black Riders" were some of the most prominent pistoliers.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUSSAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Frederick the Great was instrumental in spreading the irregular light cavalry of Hungary (huszars) to the battlefields of Europe. By dropping metal body armor, these light hussars became ideal for reconnaissance and raiding. In battle, they were used in such light cavalry roles as harassing enemy skirmishers, overrunning artillery positions, and pursuing fleeing troops. Following the Prussian example, hussar regiments were introduced across Europe, often maintaining the colorful uniforms a reputation for recklessness in battle of Frederick's original hussars.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LANCER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Carolingians of early medieval France relied heavily on mounted warriors in their conquests. Inventions such as the stirrup and high-backed saddle are sometimes identified as the key element driving the shift from infantry to cavalry. Although these technologies were certainly useful in fighting from horseback, strategic considerations are just as likely to have driven the shift; the extended Carolingian empire required a mobile army. These early cavalry were protected with a byrnie (probably long scale armor) and fought primarily with lance and sword.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEAVY_LANCER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Increasing armor weight required new breeds of heavier horses to carry mounted warriors. The most highly prized type of war-horse was the destrier, bred specifically for battles or jousts. In the wet climates of Europe, these new breeds required horseshoes to protect their hoofs. All of these developments required a fairly wealthy and advanced civilization, but the price was well worth it: few lighter units could hope to stand against the determined charge of a fully armored lancer.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARBALEST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The arbalest was a late variation of the medieval European crossbow. A larger weapon, the arbalest had a steel prod ("bow"). Since an arbalest was much larger than earlier crossbows, and because of the greater tensile strength of steel, it had a greater force and range. A skilled arbalestier could shoot two bolts per minute. Arbalests were sometimes considered inhumane or unfair weapons, since an inexperienced arbalestier could use one to kill a knight who had a lifetime of training.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARQUEBUSIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The arquebus is an early muzzle-loaded firearm. They were used against enemies that were often protected by steel-plate armor, which a bullet could pierce only at close range. The arquebus was unable to match the accuracy of a bow in the hands of a highly-skilled archer. However, it had a faster rate of fire than the most powerful crossbow, and a much shorter learning curve than a longbow. Once the methods were developed, powder and shot were relatively easy to mass-produce, while arrow making was a genuine craft requiring highly skilled labor.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German/>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BOMBARD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A bombard is a medieval cannon or mortar, used chiefly in sieges for throwing heavy stone balls. This weapon was usually used during sieges to hurl various forms of missile into enemy fortifications. Projectiles such as stone or metal balls, burning materials and weighted cloth soaked in quicklime or Greek fire are documented.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOUNTED_INFANTRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Mounted Infantry soldiers use horses to get to the battlefield, but once there they dismount and fight on foot. They rarely take part in charges or other horseback maneuvers, and they tend to suffer badly when engaged in such against trained cavalry units. On the other hand, when fortified on a hill, Mounted Infantry can do serious damage to an attacking Horse Archer or Light Cavalry unit.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les soldats d'infanterie mont&#233;e se servent de chevaux pour atteindre le champ de bataille mais une fois sur place, ils se battent &#224; pied. Ils ne prennent que rarement part aux charges ou aux manoeuvres &#224; cheval et ont tendance &#224; subir des pertes importantes face &#224; des unit&#233;s de cavalerie entra&#238;n&#233;es. Cependant, si elle est plac&#233;e dans des fortifications sur une colline, l'infanterie mont&#233;e peut infliger de s&#233;rieux dommages &#224; une unit&#233; d'archers mont&#233;s ou de cavalerie l&#233;g&#232;re.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Soldaten der Berittenen Infanterie nutzen Pferde, um aufs Schlachtfeld zu gelangen. Sobald sie es erreicht haben, satteln sie jedoch ab und k&#228;mpfen zu Fu&#223;. Sie nehmen nur selten an Vorst&#246;&#223;en oder anderen Man&#246;vern zu Pferd teil, und wenn sie gegen ausgebildete Einheiten der Kavallerie eingesetzt werden, stecken sie meist viel Schaden ein. Wenn sie gefestigt auf einem H&#252;gel stationiert ist, kann die Berittene Infanterie anr&#252;ckenden Berittenen Bogensch&#252;tzen oder Einheiten der Leichten Kavallerie jedoch schweren Schaden zuf&#252;gen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]I soldati della fanteria a cavallo usano i cavalli per arrivare al campo di battaglia ma poi smontano e combattono a piedi. Di rado prendono parte a cariche o altre manovre a cavallo, e tendono a subire malamente gli attacchi delle unit&#224; di cavalleria. D'altro canto quando sono fortificate in collina, i fanti a cavallo possono infliggere seri danni ad arcieri a cavallo o cavalleria leggera.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Los soldados de la infanter&#237;a montada usan sus caballos para llegar al campo de batalla, pero una vez all&#237; desmontan y luchan a pie. Solo en raras ocasiones toman parte en cargas u otras maniobras t&#237;picas de caballer&#237;a y, cuando se enfrentan con escuadrones de caballer&#237;a profesional, normalmente llevan las de perder. Por otro lado, cuando est&#225; atrincherada en una colina, la infanter&#237;a montada puede ser muy peligrosa para los arqueros a caballo o la caballer&#237;a ligera.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PROSECUTOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]While Missionaries often focus on extolling the glories of their respective gods to spread their religion, the Prosecutors focuses instead on pointing out the fallacies of all religions but his own. Ardent in the belief that all other religions are wrong, the Prosecutor lives to destroy the beliefs of others. If the Prosecution convicted a person of heresy, the personal property of a condemned person was confiscated and places of worship were destroyed; based on medieval and feudal laws. Usually the confiscated property was divided three ways: by the Prosecution members, the church officials, and the state treasury. The Church and state kept strict accounts of the prisoner's incarceration, trial and execution costs. If the value of his confiscated property was not enough to cover these costs, then his heirs had to pay the difference. Records show many women and children were left penniless from such confiscation. You may expend a Prosecutor inside a city to remove all religions from that city except your own.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les missionnaires se contentent souvent de glorifier leurs dieux respectifs pour propager leur religion, alors que l'inquisiteur s'efforce de d&#233;montrer les aberrations de toutes les autres religions. Convaincu que toutes les autres religions sont dans l'erreur, l'inquisiteur vit pour d&#233;truire les croyances des autres. Vous pouvez envoyer un inquisiteur dans une ville pour l'expurger de toutes les religions sauf la v&#244;tre.</French>
		<German>[TAB]W&#228;hrend Missionare sich oft darauf konzentrieren, die Tugenden ihrer jeweiligen G&#246;tter zu &#252;bertreiben, um ihre Religion zu verbreiten, konzentriert sich der Inquisitor stattdessen darauf, die Fehler aller anderen Religionen au&#223;er seiner eigenen aufzuzeigen. Der Inquisitor brennt vor &#220;berzeugung, dass alle anderen Religionen falsch sind, und lebt daf&#252;r, den Glauben aller anderen zu zerst&#246;ren. Sie k&#246;nnen einen Inquisitor in eine Stadt entsenden, um aus dieser Stadt alle Religionen au&#223;er Ihrer zu entfernen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Mentre i missionari si concentrano sulle lodi delle rispettive divinit&#224; per diffondere la propria religione, gli inquisitori mettono in risalto gli errori delle altre religioni. Credono ardentemente che le altre religioni si sbaglino e vivono per distruggere la fede degli altri. Puoi usare un Inquisitore in una citt&#224; per rimuoverne tutte le religioni tranne la tua.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Mientras que los misioneros suelen concentrarse en cantar las glorias de sus respectivos dioses para difundir su fe, los inquisidores se dedican a poner de manifiesto las falacias de todas las dem&#225;s religiones. Ferviente convencido de que todas las dem&#225;s religiones se equivocan, El inquisidor vive para socavar las creencias de los dem&#225;s. Puedes gastar un inquisidor dentro de una ciudad para eliminar todas las religiones salvo la tuya.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARABIA_GHAZI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Ghazi warriors were fierce Arabic light/medium cavalry armed with sword and lance, who raided deep into enemy territory to make war on unbelievers. Depending largely on plunder for their livelihood they were organized in bands similiar to mercenary companies which attracted religious zealots and adventurers of every kind. Within the context of Islamic jihad warfare, they struck fast and hard inside enemy borders to destroy war materials and morale, then withdrawing with all the loot they could carry. As flexible and highly mobile border defenders and raiders they often preceeded the deployment of much larger armies during the early Arab invasions of Persia, Egypt and North Africa.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOSCOW_BOYAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A boyar was a member of the highest rank of the feudal Bulgarian, Kievan Rus and Moscovian aristocracies, second only to the ruling dukes. Boyars weilded considerable power through their military support of the Moscovian princes and state, their traditions of family service and their ownership of land. Very similiar to Western knights, they were armed with swords and bows and equiped with chain or plate armour, and commanded their own personal armies of peasant levies and mercenaries. They continued to occupy the highest state offices, after repelling the Mongol invasions of the 13thC, throughout the 14th and 15th centuries until their power was eroded by the Czars, chiefly Ivan IV, during the 16C.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DRAGOON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The word "dragoon" is derived from the French Army designation dragon which was originally the name of a type of firearm (whose name means dragon) carried by French dragoons. In French, Portuguese and Spanish there is no distinction between the words dragoon and dragon.
[TAB]Dragoons were originally infantrymen deployed by horse, but later became cavalry. They were therefore trained in horse riding as well as infantry fighting skills. Dragoon regiments were established in most European armies during the late 17th and early 18th centuries. Originally dragoons were considered as separate from regular cavalry, but during the 18th century they evolved into conventional mounted troops trained to fight from horseback.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TAGMATA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The tagma is a term for a military unit of battalion size. The best-known use of the term however refers to the elite regiments comprising the central imperial army of the middle and late Byzantine Empire.
[TAB]In Byzantine usage, the term came to refer exclusively to the professional, standing troops, garrisoned in and around the capital of Constantinople. Most of them traced their origins to the Imperial guard units of the later Roman Empire. By the 7th century, these had declined to little more than parade troops, meaning that the emperors were hard put to face the frequent revolts of the new and powerful thematic formations, especially the Opsician theme, the Asian theme closest to the capital. Within the first sixty years since its creation, it was involved in five revolts, culminating in the rebellion and usurpation of the throne by its commander, the Count Artabasdos, in 741 - 743.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPANISH_TERCIO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Tercio ("one third"), also known as Tercio Español, was a Renaissance era military formation similar to and derivative of the Swiss pike square and was a term used to describe a mixed infantry formation of about 3,000 pikemen, swordsmen and arquebusiers in a mutually supportive formation; it was also sometimes referred to by other nations as a Spanish Square after its introduction by the Spanish army, and was widely adopted across international lines and dominated formalized field warfare for more than a century.
[TAB]The Tercio Español was the product of the Italian Wars in which the Spanish general, Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba, would reorganize the Spanish army throughout a series of conflicts at the end of the 15th and early 16th centuries, into a tactically unique combination of modern and medieval combined arms centered around armored infantry. This emphasis on the infantry was the result of Spain's great dependence on mules in daily life, which in turn resulted in an inability to raise large cavalry forces. It marked the transformation of medieval military institutions into the early modern combined-arms[3] army. (See: Pike and Shot for an excellent description of the eventual formation.) Gonzalo Fernández, developed the Tercio to further increase the effectiveness of Spanish infantry against every manner of opposing infantry while remaining impervious to the dangers of a cavalry charge.
[TAB]At first the army consisted of units of around 6000 men, called coronelias, which by 1534 had been reduced into the Tercios of 3000 for increased mobility on the offensive.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VENICE_GALLEAS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The galleass or "galliass" developed from large merchant galleys converted for military use they were higher and larger than regular ("light") galleys. They had up to 32 oars, each worked by up to 5 men. They usually had three masts and a forecastle and aftcastle. Much effort was made in Venice to make these galleasses as fast as possible to compete with regular galleys. The gun-deck usually ran over the rowers' heads, but there are also pictures showing the opposite arrangement.
[TAB]Galleasses usually carried more sails than true galleys, and were far deadlier; a galley caught broadside lay all but helpless, but coming broadside to a galleass, as with a ship of the line, exposed an attacker to her gunfire. The galleass exemplified an intermediate type between the galley and the true man-of-war. Relatively few galleasses were built - one disadvantage was that, being more reliant on sails, their position at the front of the galley line at the start of a battle could not be guaranteed - but they were used at the Battle of Lepanto (7 October 1571), their firepower helping to win victory for the Christian fleet, and some sufficiently seaworthy galleasses accompanied the Spanish Armada in 1588 (e.g. La Girona). In the 15th century a type of light galleass, called the frigate, was built in southern European countries to answer the increasing challenge posed by the north African based Barbary pirates in their fast galleys.
[TAB]In the Mediterranean, with its shallower waters, less dangerous weather and fickle winds, both galleasses and galleys continued in use, particularly in Venice and Turkey, long after they became obsolete elsewhere. Later, "round ships" and galleasses were replaced by galleons and ships of the line which originated in Atlantic Europe. The first Venetian ship of the line was built in 1660.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KIEV_DRUZHINA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The name is derived from the Slavic word drug with the meaning of "companion, friend". It is a cognate of the Germanic drottin meaning "war band".
[TAB]Druzhina was in the history of early East Slavs a detachment of select troops in personal service of a Knyaz (A Slavic title). It's main functions were bodyguarding, raising tribute from conquered territories and serving as the core of the army during war campaigns. Equipped as heavy cavalry wearing padded and mail armour and armed with lance and sword, the "Druzinniks" served freely and could leave one knyaz and join another. Druzyna varied in size, but usually numbered several hundred. They served as the nucleus of the army which was otherwise largely recruited as peasant levies. Druznya were paid by the knyaz and were able to share a portion of any military loot while on campaign.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CORDOBAN_BERBER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Following the Muslim conquest of North Africa in the 7thC., the Berber peoples of the Maghreb and Morocco largely adopted Islam and became the mainstay of Arab armies in the West. Skilled with bow and javelin and mounted on camels, they soon mastered the horse and became adept as scouting and raiding light cavalry. The Arab conquest of Iberia initiated by the Berber general, Tarik ibn-Zihad consisted of about 300 elite Arabian cavalry and a mixed Berber army of about 1800-2000 bowmen, spearmen and light cavalry. Later Andalusian armies were largely comprised of a core of Arabian noble horsemen and a majority of Berber voluteers and mercenaries who fought both on foot and on horseback.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GENOA_BALESTRIERI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Genoese crossbowmen were a famous military formation both in the defence of Genoa and as mercenaries for other Italian and European powers during the Middle Ages. Fighting on both land and in naval battles, they were outfitted with a dagger, light metal helmet, gorget and a large shield called a "pavese" which protected them while loading the crossbow. The presence of balestieri companies on the battlefield was highly feared due to the efficiency of their weapons and their organization, and even often enough to lead an opponent to alter his battle plans. The balestrieri remained feared and respected military formations into the late 16thC. even after the introduction of black powder weapons into Europe.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_COGGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The cog (or cogge) was a type of ship which first appeared in Northern Europe and was widely used from the 12thC. onwards. Cogs were generally made of oak, an abundant timber in the Baltic region, and were fitted with a single mast and square-rigged sail. Even though this rigging prevented them sailing into the wind, cogs between associated with sea going trade in the northern waters of Medieval Europe. They were generally flat-bottomed and employed a stern-mounted rudder with fore and stern castles as defense against pirates, enabling them to often used as warships. By the late 15thC. they were replaced by the carrack which was more sea-worthy and suitable for sailing in the open ocean over longer distances.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ENGLISH_LONGBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Longbows were tall, powerful bows employed to penetrate all but the best of Medieval armour. Their use by English armies reached a peak during the Hundred Years War when the use of massed longbowmen was highly effective against the French at the battles of Crecy (1346), Poitiers (1356) and at Agincourt in 1415. The longbow combined long range and high accuracy but not both at the same time. Most longbow shooting involved launching volleys of arrows at enemy armies at long range from protected positions. The longbow was the machine gun of the Middle Ages, accurate, deadly and more rapid-firing than the crossbow or even early firearms though with the development of the latter the longbow gradually fell into disuse.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WELSH_LONGBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Following the Norman conquest of Wales in the 13thC., during which Welsh bowmen caused heavy casualties to the invader, Kings of England increasingly began to used longbowmen, including Welsh bowmen in their armies. Originally the Welsh employed a much shorter, rougher bow made of elm technically distinct from the classic English yew longbows. But as soon as the Welsh campaign was successfully over, Welsh conscripts began to be incorporated in large numbers into English armies. The valuable lessons the English learned in Wales of the tactic of massed formations of skilled archers using powerful bows was later used with great effect by English and Welsh mercenary longbowmen on the battlefields of Scotland and France.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUNGARIAN_LANCER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A type of irregular light horsemen was already well established by the 15th century in medieval Hungary. Etymologists are divided over the derivation of the word 'hussar'. Many scholars believe the word that was passed into Hungarian by way of the Croatians originates from the Latin word 'cursus' meaning 'raid'. According to Webster's the word hussar stems from the Hungarian huszár, which in turn originates from the Serbian husar or gusar, meaning pirate, from the Medieval Latin cursarius (cf. the English word corsair). A variant of this theory is offered by Byzantinist scholars, who argue the term originated in Roman military practice, and the cursarius--a group of fast moving horsemen used for scouting or raiding-came to be called tsanarioi in Greek or the Armenian Chosarioi. Through Byzantine Army operations in the Balkans in the 10th and 11th centuries, the word was thus reintroduced to Western European military practice after its original usage had been lost with the collapse of Rome in the west. According to another theory, the word is derived from the Hungarian word of húsz meaning twenty, suggesting that hussar regiments were originally composed of twenty men. Or the term huszár probably signified 'one in twenty' as selected for service by ballot.
[TAB]The hussars reportedly originated in bands of Hungarian and Serbian warriors crossing into southern Hungary after the Turkish invasion of Serbia at the end of the 14th century. The Governor of Hungary, Hunyadi János - John Hunyadi, created mounted units inspired by his enemy the Ottoman Turks. His son, Hunyadi Mátyás Matthias Corvinus, later king of Hungary, is unanimously accepted as the creator of these troops. Initially they fought in small bands, but were reorganized into larger, trained, formations during the reign of King Matthias I Corvinus of Hungary. So the first Hussar regiments were the light cavalry of the Black Army of Hungary. Under his command the hussars took part in the war against the Ottoman Empire in 1485 and proved successful against the Turkish Spahis as well as against Bohemians and Poles. After the king's death in 1490, hussars remained the preferred form of cavalry in Hungary. The Habsburg emperors hired Hungarian hussars as mercenaries to serve against the Ottoman Empire and on various battlefields throughout Europe. The "father" of the US cavalry in 1777 was a Hungarian hussar named Kováts Mihály - Michael de Kovats.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FIELD_ARTILLERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Field artillery is a type of mobile artillery used to suppport armies in the field, offering mobility, tactical proficiency and specializing in long or short range bombardment. Until the 19thC. they were known as foot artillery, for while the guns were pulled by beasts of burden (often horses), their crews marched on foot providing fire support for the infantry, unlike the later horse artillery, with their emphasis on speed. who supported cavalry units with their lighter guns and their crews travelling on horseback. Early artillery were unsuited to the battlefield, as the extremely massive pieces could not be easily moved except in areas under friendly control. Thus their principal role was limited to functions like breaking seiges.
[TAB]The first field artillery were developed with advances in metallurgy which allowed thinner barrels able to withstand explosive forces without bursting, thus making them considerably lighter. But there was always the risk that constant changes on the battlefield would leave slow-moving artillery units behind. making them vulnerable to enemy cavalry who often specialized in seeking them out and destroying them. It was only with invention of the limber, pulled by horses hitched to a wheeled artillery piece, in the 18thC., that the concept of field artillery become truly established.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TURKEY_GREAT_BOMBARD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Although gunpowder weapons were used in China in the early 10thC., the Arabs first acquired gunpwder about 1240AD and it is believed that the first cannon in history was used by the Mamluks against the Mongols in 1260. The Ottoman Empire became the first in Europe to put gunpowder into widespread use in both hand weaponry and seige cannons. The army of Mehmet I which conquered Constantinople in 1453 included foot soldiers armed with matchlock muskets and bombard artillery of various sizes. The barrage of Ottoman cannon fire, from 69 guns firing over 19,000 times, is said to have lasted for at least 40 days.
[TAB]Amongst these were a number of extremely large and powerful seige bombards. Bombards had been deployed by many European armies since the late 1300's but the Ottoman siege guns were especially massive and powerful "superguns", like the "Dardanelles Gun" or Great Turkish Bombard, weighing over 18 tons and firing huge stone or iron projectiles of over 2 feet in diameter. This famous gun along with many others, remained in use by the Ottomans until the early 19thC.,even causing serious damage to British naval operations against the Ottomans in 1807.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HOLK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A holk (or hulk) was a type of sea craft similiar to the cog and was one of the technological forerunners of the carrack and caravel. Like cogs, they were generally flat-bottomed and square-sailed with overlapping "strakes" or planks at each end and full lapstrakes covering the sides. Their keels were shallow and their sternpost straight and long with a stern-mounted central rudder similiar to those in the cog. Improvements in wood-working techniques allowed a transition from smaller cogs to holks of greater capacity until both were overtaken by the development of the carrack and caravel in the late 14thC.
[TAB]The holk was probably a fairly minor type of boat and largely confined to the Low Countries and the Baltic where it was used originally as a river or canal boat with a limited potential for sea cruising. Even so, for a period in the 14thC. holks began to evolve into larger examples which exceeded the cog in both size and capacity, if not in ocean-going sea-worthiness and the holk remained a major load carrier in the medieval economy well into the 16thC..</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GUN_GALLEY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A galley is a type of ship that can be propelled entirely by human oarsmen and used for warfare and trade, but usually had masts and sails for use when the wind was favourable. various types of galleys dominated naval warfare in the Meditteranean Sea from the 8thC.BC to the 16thC. Many medieval states, notably Venice, Genoa, the Byzantines, Arabs and the Ottoman Turks depended largely on heavily-armed galleys until the introduction of the ocean-going "man-of-war". The Battle of Lepanto, in 1571, was one of the largest and last sea battles in which galleys played the principal part.
[TAB]Galleys remained in regular use in the Meditteranean until the introduction of broadside sailing ships in the 17thC.. While war galleys originally carried archers and slingers for offensive operations and defence, the advent of gunpowder weapons saw the development of early cannons mounted on ships. In fact, medieval war galleys pioneered the use of naval guns, with the typical Venetian gun galley or "laterna" mounting high calibe guns in the bow and stern with various lighter swivel guns deployed throughout the ship. However, with the development of the high-sided carrack and galleas capable of powerful broadside cannonfire, the usefulness of these gun galleys eventually came to an end.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LINE_INFANTRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Line infantry refers to those regiments that historically fought in linear formations, unlike light troops who fought in loose order. Generally speaking, line infantry were so named because they made up the line of battle rather than because they necessarily fought in lines. The 17th.C saw the expansion of the roles of the infantry as the improvement of gunpowder weapons made the mixed pike and shot formations like the Spanish Tercios increasingly effective. Fighting in close order squares these disciplined combined arms units were feared on the battlefield throughout Europe.
[TAB]Increasingly in the 18thC. line infantry units became wholly equiped with accurate long-range firearms and were deployed as integrated units. Typically, specialist companies were deployed on the flanks of the main body of musket-armed infantry with a company of light infantry trained as skirmishers to operate independently on the battlefield and a company of grenadiers, who were usually the biggest and strongest men in the regiment, deployed in advance as the lead assault troops. Regiments of these line infantry remained the mainstay of all European armies until the beginning of the 20thC.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AUSTRIAN_KURASSIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Curassiers were mounted cavalry with armour and firearms which first appeared on the battlefields of late 15thC. as the successors to the medieval armoured knights. The first curassiers wore three-quarter armour which covered the upper body and a close helm or "lobster-tail" pot helmet with the torso protected by breast and back plates, worn above long riding boots. Weapons included a pair of pistols in saddle holsters, a short sword or sabre and often a light mace or war hammer. 
[TAB]The first curassiers were formed as a regiment of Austrian kurassiers (or "kyrissers") recruited from Croatia in 1484 to serve the future Holy Roman Emperor, Maximilian. Austrian Kurassiers also fought the Swedes and their allies at Lutzen in 1632, killing their king Gustavus Adolphus during the battle. The armour worn by the Kurassiers gradually decreased throughout the 18thC. until the Napoleonic Wars so that the Kurassiers, like other curassiers, wore little more than helmets and breast plates. Kurassiers played a prominent role in the armies of Austria during the campaigns of Frederick the Great and remained the senior members of the mounted branch of the army, retaining their status as "big men on horses" throughout the 19thC. and beyond.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_NETHERLANDS_GRENADIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A grenadier (from the word "grenade") was originally a specialized soldier who threw explosive grenades and sometimes took part in assault operations on the field of battle. From the 17thC. grenadiers were chosen from the largest and strongest soldiers and often led the storming of breaches in seige warfare, a role later performed by sappers and pioneers. Grenades were small iron spheres, the size of a baseball or cricket ball, filled with gunpowder and fused by a slow match. The wide hats worn by grenadiers were gradually replaced by tall caps shaped like a bishop's mitre which permitted the grenadier greater ease in throwing the grenade overhand.
[TAB]Grenade usage declined in the late 18thC. although the need for elite assault troops remained and grenadiers were retained for this purpose and specially selected for their strength, experience and steadiness under fire. All the major European armies continued to employ elite grenadier companies until the early 19thC.. Their use was particularly marked in the battles of the Dutch Republic from 1648 to the 1790s as Dutch grenadiers wearing their distinctive guilded "bishop's mitres" saw action in numerous battles during the Anglo-Dutch wars. Grenadiers remained prominent on the battlefield until the invasion and occupation of the Netherlands by Revolutionary France in 1795.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>CHANGED_TXT_KEY_UNIT_WAR_GALLEY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Galleys, propelled by banks of oarsmen and equiped with masts and sails, have been employed in warfare throughout history since the ancient Greeks and Phoenicians. While the use of war galleys was largely confined to the Meditteranean, the early Norsemen developed the longship, a clinker-built narrow, sleek galley of shallow draught capable of travelling on inland rivers as well as being extremely seaworthy on the open ocean under sail. Longships became the epitome of Norse naval power and remained dominant in Northern Europe until the introduction of the cog and the carrack in the 14thC..
[TAB]War galleys, as employed in the Meditteranean, were less capable of ocean voyages but ideal for shallow waters and near-shore navigation and soon grew considerably in size and firepower. The largest examples were rowed by nearly 300 men and carried a further 400 crew and fighting soldiers as well as dozens of cannons of all sizes. By the late 16thC. the large war galleys became mostly obsolete by the man-of-war although they remained the mainstay of the North African "corsair" pirate fleets and continue to play a significant role in the Meditteranean until the beginning of the 19thC..</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SELJUK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Seljuk Turks were a Turco-Persian tribe with its origins in the Turcoman clans of Central Asia who migrated into Persia in the 10thC., adopting Sunni Islam and Persian culture and language and are considered to be the cultural ancestors of today's modern Turks of Central Asia and Anatolia. By the mid 11thC. they built up a vast nomadic empire including most of Western Asia and Persia and the Caucasus. During the 1060's, The Seljuk hordes, along with their Turkic and Kurdish allies, invaded Armenia, Georgia and Asia Minor, conquering the Armenian capitol in 1064 and Caesarea in 1067.
[TAB]Their victory at Manzikert in 1071 was a decisive defeat for the Byzantine Empire and soon all of Syria and Anatolia came under Seljuk control. Seljuk petty kingdoms were set up throughout the region, notably the Sultanate of Rum in eastern Anatolia which remained in existence until the 14thC. Their fractured states, however, were more concerned with consolidating their territories and conquering their neighbours than cooperating against the First Crusade. Although they easily defeated the untrained "Peoples Crusade" in 1096 they could not prevent the main Crusader army from seizing important cities like Nicaea, Iconium and Antioch, capturing the Holy Land in 1099 and setting up the first of the Crusader kingdoms.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HIGHLANDER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The term "Highlander" refers to the Gaelic-speaking inhabitants of the northern uplands and western isles of Scotland who are descended from original Picts and Scots before the 10thC., becoming increasingly distinct from the "Lowlanders" of southern Scotland, with their traditional Gaelic language and customs. Organized in clans led by chiefs or "lairds", they were known as fierce warriors armed with swords, axes and small shields, wearing little else but their short skirt or "kilt" woven in their distinctive clan pattern or "tartan". Although they supported Robert the Bruce in the unification of Scotland and its independence following the Declaration of Arbroath in 1320, the highland clans remained resistant to any central government.
[TAB]The Stewart dynasty ruled Scotland for the remainder of the Middle Ages, managing to retain the loyalty of the fierce Highland clans despite their growing resentment of the increasingly Protestant and Anglophile Scottish lowlands. Clan resistance to British rule erupted after the Act of Union between Scotland and England in 1707 in support of the Stewart pretender "Bonnie Prince Charlie" until the Scottish highlanders were finally decisively beaten at the Battle of Culloden in 1745. The Scottish Highlands were effectively cleared and replaced with sheep in the late 18thC. while most highlanders were deported to the colonies, mainly Canada and Australia, where many retain their language and customs to this day.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PORTUGAL_FOOT_KNIGHT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Military Order of Aviz, originally the "Knights of St. Benedict of Aviz" was a Catholic military order formed during the early 14thC which gave their name and arms to the Aviz Dynasty which ruled Portugal between 1385 and 1580. The Kingdom of Portugal, founded in 1128, not only participated in the Crusades but conducted one of its own against the Moors of Iberia and North Africa with the help of existing military orders like the Templars. A native order of this kind was established in Portugal in 1146 and Afonso Henriques gave it the town of Evora captured from the Moors in 1166. After the conquest of Aviz a castle was erected there and the order became known as the Knights of St. Benedict of Aviz. Like the Knights of Calatrava in Castille, these Portugese Knights were indebted to the Cistercian abbots for their rule and their habit, a white mantle with a green fleur-de-lysed cross. Although nominally remaining as a branch of the Calatravan Order, they never ceased to have a Portugese Grand Master and be subject to the Kings of Portugal. 
[TAB]The mission of the Knights of Aviz did not end with the overthrow of Muslim domination as Portugese expeditions across the sea opened new opportunities for them. The first landings of Europeans in Africa, the conquest of Ceuta by King Joao I in 1415 and the Portugese attacks on Tangier in 1437 were seen as crusades, in which the Knights of Aviz and the Knights of Christ (local successors to the disbanded Templars) played a leading part. By the 16thC. however, their crusades in Africa had lost their religious zeal and their efforts were reduced to vulgar money-making enterprises. The Order of the Knights of Aviz became increasingly secular and commercial and after the institution of liberal government in the 19thC. it evolved into the largely charitable foundation and symbolic order of merit it remains to this day.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BURGUNDIAN_PALADIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Paladins (often called Chevaliers) Were Medieval knights who followed the code of chivalry or knightly conduct, which emphasized courage, honour and service. The Paladin was adept at the art of war, trained in fighting in armour on horses with lances, swords and shields. They were expected to show courage, be gallant to women, defend the Church and swear off cowardice and baseness. Their origins lie with the first mounted infantry in the armies of the Emperor Charlemange as some elite warriors who wore armour and fought on horseback were rewarded with grants of land called "benefices" and became powerful captains with feudal fiefs that soon became hereditary and powerful, both in political influence and economic wealth.
[TAB]These knights became the mainstay of governing power under the King, raising their own armies in time of war and often rivalled the Church in wealth and influence. But chivalry and the Church remained closely entwined and the Crusades helped to reinforce the moral code of chivalry as it related to religion. Thus Christian armies were encouraged to devote their efforts to sacred purposes and the Paladins were expected to use their weapons for the protection of the weak and defenceless, to women and children, and above all to the defence of churches and pilgrims, giving rise to the religious military orders like the Templars, the Hospitallers and the Teutonic Knights. Some knightly orders, like the English "Order of the Bath" or the "Order of the Garter" remain day as honorary associations whose membership is granted by the Monarch for meritorious achievement.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CORSAIR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]From the French "corsaire" for privateer, the Barbary Pirates, often known as "Turkish corsairs" were Muslim pirates operating from the North African ports of Tunis, Tripoli, Algiers and part of Morocco in an area which became known as the Barbary Coast. Their attacks even extended into the Atlantic as far north as Ireland and Iceland as they destroyed thousands of Venetian, French, Spanish and English ships from the time of the Crusades until the beginning of the early 1800s. Long stretches of coastline in Italy, Spain and France were almost abandoned for centuries as the pirates captured nearly a million Europeans as slaves between the 16thC. and 19th.C. to be sold in the slave markets of North Africa and the Ottoman Empire.
[TAB]Among the most famous corsairs were the brothers Hayreddin Barbarossa and Oruc Reis, who took control of the port of Algiers in the 15thC.. beginning 400 years of Ottoman presence in North Africa and establishing a centre of Mediterranean piracy, nominally under Ottoman control but self-governing and funded largely by piracy. Many of these Barbary corsairs, sailing in their large war galleys or "Xebecs" were originally Europeans, often former Dutch captives recruited as pirates, and operated with the cooperation of some European powers, like the French against the Spanish or the British and Dutch against the French. Most European nations paid ransom and tribute to the Barbary pirates until the beginning of the 19thC. when concerted French, British and American naval actions finally suppressed their fleets and bases and Algiers was captured by the French in 1830.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BULGARIA_KONNIK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Bulgars were highly skilled in the equestrian arts. Their army mainly consisted of horseman because of their high skill. Every Bulgar horseman had high discipline and had several horses. However, only a single horse could be used for wartime matters, and it was forbidden to do anything else with it. It is believed that the Bulgars were the first who brought the stirrups to Europe. This gave them advantages above the other European armies of this time. The Bulgars could use bows still mounted on horses. Swords and spears were also used in war. The stirrups also increased the stability and speed of the rider.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le Bulgars &#195;&#169;taient fortement habile dans les arts &#195;&#169;questres. Leur arm&#195;&#169;e s'est principalement compos&#195;&#169;e du cavalier en raison de leur comp&#195;&#169;tence &#195;&#169;lev&#195;&#169;e. Chaque cavalier de Bulgar a eu la discipline &#195;&#169;lev&#195;&#169;e et a eu plusieurs chevaux. Cependant, seulement un cheval simple pourrait &#195;&#170;tre employ&#195;&#169; pour des sujets de temps de guerre, et on l'a interdit de faire toute autre chose avec lui. On le croit que le Bulgars &#195;&#169;taient le premier qui a apport&#195;&#169; les &#195;&#169;triers &#195;&#160; l'Europe. Ceci leur a donn&#195;&#169; des avantages au-dessus des autres arm&#195;&#169;es europ&#195;&#169;ennes de ce temps. Le Bulgars a pu employer des arcs toujours mont&#195;&#169;s sur des chevaux. Des &#195;&#169;p&#195;&#169;es et les lances ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; &#195;&#169;galement utilis&#195;&#169;es dans la guerre. Les &#195;&#169;triers ont &#195;&#169;galement augment&#195;&#169; la stabilit&#195;&#169; et la vitesse du cavalier.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Bulgars waren in die Reiterk&#195;&#188;nste in hohem Grade erfahren. Ihre Armee bestand haupts&#195;&#164;chlich aus Reiter wegen ihrer hohen F&#195;&#164;higkeit. Jeder Bulgar Reiter hatte hohe Disziplin und hatte einige Pferde. Jedoch nur ein einzelnes Pferd k&#195;&#182;nnte f&#195;&#188;r Kriegangelegenheiten benutzt werden, und es war verboten, um noch etwas mit ihm zu tun. Es wird geglaubt, da&#195;&#159; das Bulgars das erste waren, wer die Steigb&#195;&#188;gel zu Europa holte. Dieses gab ihnen Vorteile &#195;&#188;ber den anderen europ&#195;&#164;ischen Armeen dieser Zeit. Das Bulgars konnte die B&#195;&#182;gen benutzen, die noch an den Pferden angebracht wurden. Klingen und Stangen wurden auch im Krieg benutzt. Die Steigb&#195;&#188;gel erh&#195;&#182;hten auch die Stabilit&#195;&#164;t und die Geschwindigkeit des Mitfahrers.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il Bulgars era altamente esperto nelle arti equestrian. Il loro esercito pricipalmente ha consistito del horseman a causa dell'loro elevata specializzazione. Ogni horseman di Bulgar ha avuto alta disciplina ed ha avuto parecchi cavalli. Tuttavia, soltanto un singolo cavallo potrebbe essere usato per gli argomenti di wartime ed &#195;&#168; stato proibito a per fargli niente altro con. Si crede che il Bulgars sia stato il primo chi ha portato le staffe ad Europa. Ci&#195;&#178; ha dato loro i vantaggi sopra gli altri eserciti europei di questo tempo. Il Bulgars ha potuto usare gli archi ancora montati sui cavalli. Le spade ed i germogli inoltre sono stati utilizzati nella guerra. Le staffe inoltre hanno aumentato la stabilit&#195;&#160; e la velocit&#195;&#160; del rider.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El Bulgars era altamente experto en los artes ecuestres. Su ej&#195;&#169;rcito consisti&#195;&#179; en principalmente el jinete debido a su alta habilidad. Cada jinete de Bulgar ten&#195;&#173;a alta disciplina y ten&#195;&#173;a varios caballos. Sin embargo, solamente un solo caballo podr&#195;&#173;a ser utilizado para las materias del tiempo de guerra, y fue prohibido para hacer todo lo dem&#195;&#161;s con &#195;&#169;l. Se cree que el Bulgars era el primer qui&#195;&#169;n trajo los estribos a Europa. Esto les dio ventajas sobre los otros ej&#195;&#169;rcitos europeos de este tiempo. El Bulgars pod&#195;&#173;a utilizar los arcos todav&#195;&#173;a montados en caballos. Las espadas y las lanzas tambi&#195;&#169;n fueron utilizadas en guerra. Los estribos tambi&#195;&#169;n aumentaron la estabilidad y la velocidad del jinete.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_POLISH_WINGED_HUSSAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first hussar units in the Kingdom of Poland were formed by the Sejm, the Polish Parliament, in 1503 which hired three banners of Hungarian mercenaries. Soon, recruitment also began among Polish and Lithuanian citizens. The Hussars proved vital to Poland because they were more maneuverable than the previously used lancers. But the reign of King Stefan Batory, the hussars formed the bulk of the Polish and Lithuanian cavalry. Over many years, hussars in Hungary became heavier. When Stefan Batory was elected king of Poland, he reorganized the Polish-Lithuanian hussars of his Royal Guard making them a heavy formation, and equipping lancers as their main weapon. These Polish 'heavy' hussars were known in their homeland as "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] With the Battle of Lubiszew in 1577, the "Golden Age" of the hussar began. Until the Battle of Vienna, Polish-Lithuanian hussars rarely lost in battle. Throughout many battles the Polish-Lithuanian hussars would prove to be an important factor against overwhelming odds.[PARAGRAPH: 1] The primary battle tactic of the Polish-Lithuanian hussars was the charge. They also tended to repeat the charge until the enemy formation broke. The hussars fought with a long lance, a szabla, one or two pistols, and a carbine or arquebus, known in Polish as a "bandolet". Polish hussars were also famous for the wings they wore on their backs. According to some theories, they were designed to foil attacks by Tatar lassos, another theory being that the vibrating of feathers made a strange sound that frightened enemy horses. However, experiments carried out by re-enactors and movie-makers since the 1970s and more recently by Polish historians in 2001 contradict such ideas. Possibly the wings were worn only during parades and not during combat, but this explanation is also disputed.</English>
		<French>[TAB]La premi&#195;&#168;re hussarde unit&#195;&#169;s dans le Royaume de Pologne ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; form&#195;&#169;s par le Sejm, le Parlement polonais, en 1503, qui a engag&#195;&#169; trois banni&#195;&#168;res de mercenaires hongrois. Bient&#195;&#180;t, le recrutement a commenc&#195;&#169; entre les citoyens polonais et lituaniens. Les Hussards av&#195;&#169;r&#195;&#169;e vitale pour la Pologne, parce qu'ils &#195;&#169;taient plus manoeuvrable que les lanciers pr&#195;&#169;c&#195;&#169;demment utilis&#195;&#169;s. But le r&#195;&#168;gne du roi Stefan Batory, les hussards formaient le gros de la cavalerie polonaise et lituanienne. Depuis de nombreuses ann&#195;&#169;es, hussards en Hongrie est devenue plus lourde. Lorsque Stefan Batory est &#195;&#169;lu roi de Pologne, il a r&#195;&#169;organis&#195;&#169; le polonais-lituanien hussards de sa garde royale rendant une lourde formation et l'&#195;&#169;quipement des lanciers comme leur principale arme. Ces polonais "lourds" hussards &#195;&#169;taient connus dans leur pays comme "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Avec la bataille de Lubiszew en 1577, l'&#195;&#162;ge d'or "de la hussarde a commenc&#195;&#169;. Jusqu'&#195;&#160; la bataille de Vienne, polonais-lituanien hussards rarement perdu dans la bataille. Tout au long de nombreuses batailles l'polonais-lituanien hussards se r&#195;&#169;v&#195;&#169;ler &#195;&#170;tre un important facteur &#195;&#169;crasante contre chances. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principale bataille tactique de la polonais-lituanien hussards a la charge. Ils ont &#195;&#169;galement tendance &#195;&#160; r&#195;&#169;p&#195;&#169;ter les frais jusqu'&#195;&#160; la formation ennemie a &#195;&#169;clat&#195;&#169;. Les hussards combattu avec une longue Lance, un szabla, un ou deux pistolets, et un mousqueton ou arquebuse, connue en polonais comme un "bandolet". Hussards polonais &#195;&#169;taient reconnus pour les ailes, ils portaient sur leur dos. Selon certaines th&#195;&#169;ories, mais ils ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; con&#195;&#167;us pour d&#195;&#169;jouer les attaques men&#195;&#169;es par des lassos tatare, une autre th&#195;&#169;orie est que la vibration de plumes fait une &#195;&#169;trange que le son ennemi effray&#195;&#169; les chevaux. Toutefois, les exp&#195;&#169;riences men&#195;&#169;es par la r&#195;&#169;orientation enactors et film d&#195;&#169;cideurs depuis les ann&#195;&#169;es 1970 et, plus r&#195;&#169;cemment, par les historiens polonais en 2001 contredisent de telles id&#195;&#169;es. Eventuellement les ailes ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; port&#195;&#169;es seulement pendant les parades et non pas pendant le combat, mais cette explication est &#195;&#169;galement contest&#195;&#169;.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die ersten Husaren in das K&#195;&#182;nigreich Polen wurden durch den Sejm, das polnische Parlament, in der 1503 die drei gemietet Banner der ungarischen S&#195;&#182;ldnern. Bald begann auch die Einstellung der polnischen und litauischen B&#195;&#188;rger. Die Husaren als entscheidend f&#195;&#188;r Polen, weil sie mehr wendiger als die bisher verwendeten Speertr&#195;&#164;ger. But der Regierungszeit von K&#195;&#182;nig Stefan Batory, die Husaren bilden den gr&#195;&#182;&#195;&#159;ten Teil der polnischen und litauischen Kavallerie. &#195;&#156;ber viele Jahre, Husaren in Ungarn wurde schwerer. Wenn Stefan Batory gew&#195;&#164;hlt wurde K&#195;&#182;nig von Polen, er hat die Polnisch Husaren seiner Royal Guard und machen sie zu einer schweren Ausbildung, Ausr&#195;&#188;stung und Speertr&#195;&#164;ger als ihre wichtigste Waffe. Diese polnischen "schwere" Husaren bekannt waren, in ihrer eigenen Heimat als "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Mit der Schlacht von Lubiszew im 1577, das "Goldene Zeitalter" der Husaren begann. Bis in die Schlacht von Wien, Polnisch Husaren selten verloren in der Schlacht. In vielen Schlachten der polnischen Husaren - Litauisch w&#195;&#188;rde sich als ein wichtiger Faktor gegen die &#195;&#188;berw&#195;&#164;ltigende Quoten. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der prim&#195;&#164;re Kampf Taktik der polnisch-litauischen Husaren war. Dar&#195;&#188;ber hinaus neigten die Geb&#195;&#188;hr zu wiederholen, bis der Feind Bildung pleite. Die Husaren k&#195;&#164;mpften mit einer langen Lanze, ein szabla, ein oder zwei Pistolen, und einem Karabiner oder arquebus, die in der polnischen als "bandolet." Polnischen Husaren waren auch ber&#195;&#188;hmt f&#195;&#188;r die Fl&#195;&#188;gel trugen sie auf dem R&#195;&#188;cken. Nach einigen Theorien, sie wurden so gestaltet, dass Folie Angriffe von Tataren Lassos, eine andere Theorie ist, dass die Vibrationen von Federn, die ein seltsames Ger&#195;&#164;usch, Angst Feind Pferde. Allerdings, Experimente durchgef&#195;&#188;hrt erneut enactors und Film Entscheidungstr&#195;&#164;ger seit den 1970er Jahren und in j&#195;&#188;ngster Zeit von den polnischen Historiker in der 2001 im Widerspruch zu solchen Ideen. M&#195;&#182;glicherweise die Fl&#195;&#188;gel getragen wurden nur w&#195;&#164;hrend der Paraden und nicht w&#195;&#164;hrend des Kampfes, aber diese Erkl&#195;&#164;rung ist auch umstritten.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La prima unit&#195;&#160; ussaro nel Regno di Polonia si sono formati dal Sejm, il parlamento polacco, nel 1503, che noleggiati tre bandiere ungheresi di mercenari. Presto, ha iniziato il reclutamento anche tra i cittadini polacchi e lituani. Il Ussari rivelato fondamentale per la Polonia perch&#195;&#169; erano pi&#195;&#185; manovrabile da quella usata in precedenza lance. Ma il regno di Stefan Batory, la ussari formata la maggior parte della cavalleria polacco e lituano. Nel corso di molti anni, ussari in Ungheria &#195;&#168; diventata pi&#195;&#185; pesante. Stefan Batory, quando &#195;&#168; stato eletto re di Polonia, ha riorganizzato il Polacco-Lituana ussari del suo Royal Guard rendendoli un pesante formazione, e di dotare le lance come loro principale arma. Questi polacco 'pesanti' ussari erano conosciuti in patria come "husaria" [N: 1] Con la Battaglia di Lubiszew nel 1577, il "Golden Age" del ussaro iniziato. Fino alla battaglia di Vienna, polacco - lituano ussari raramente perso in battaglia. In molti battaglie polacco - lituano ussari sarebbe rivelato un fattore importante contro la stragrande quota. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principale battaglia tattica del Polacco-Lituana ussari era l'accusa. Essi hanno anche la tendenza a ripetere la carica fino a quando il nemico formazione rotto. Il ussari combattuto con una lunga lancia, un szabla, uno o due pistole, e di una carabina o arquebus, in polacco noto come "bandolet". Ussari polacchi sono stati anche famosa per le ali che indossavano sulle loro spalle. Secondo alcune teorie, che sono stati progettati per sventare attacchi da Tataro lassos, un'altra teoria &#195;&#168; che la vibrazione di piume fatto uno strano suono che spaventati nemico cavalli. Tuttavia, gli esperimenti effettuati da ristabilire enactors movie e responsabili dal 1970 e, pi&#195;&#185; recentemente, dal polacco storici nel 2001 in contrasto con tali idee. Eventualmente, le ali sono stati indossati solo durante parate, e non durante il combattimento, ma questa spiegazione &#195;&#168; anche contestato.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La primera hussar unidades en el Reino de Polonia se formaron por el Sejm, el Parlamento polaco, en 1503, que contrat&#195;&#179; a tres pancartas h&#195;&#186;ngaro de los mercenarios. En breve, tambi&#195;&#169;n se inici&#195;&#179; la contrataci&#195;&#179;n entre los ciudadanos polacos y lituanos. El Hussars result&#195;&#179; vital para Polonia, ya que fueron m&#195;&#161;s maniobrable que los utilizados anteriormente lancers. But el reinado del rey Stefan Batory, la hussars forman el grueso de la caballer&#195;&#173;a polaco y lituano. Durante muchos a&#195;&#177;os, hussars en Hungr&#195;&#173;a se convirti&#195;&#179; en m&#195;&#161;s pesadas. Cuando Stefan Batory fue elegido rey de Polonia, se reorganiz&#195;&#179; el polaco - lituano hussars de su Guardia Real convierten en una pesada formaci&#195;&#179;n, y el equipamiento lancers como su principal arma. Estos polaco 'pesadas' hussars eran conocidos en su tierra natal como "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Con la Batalla de Lubiszew en 1577, la "Edad de Oro" de la hussar comenz&#195;&#179;. Hasta la Batalla de Viena, polaco, lituano hussars rara vez perdi&#195;&#179; en la batalla. Muchas batallas en todo el polaco - lituano hussars resultar&#195;&#173;a ser un factor importante en contra de enormes dificultades. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principal batalla de la t&#195;&#161;ctica polaca y lituana hussars era el cargo. Tambi&#195;&#169;n tienden a repetir el cargo hasta que el enemigo rompi&#195;&#179; la formaci&#195;&#179;n. El hussars luch&#195;&#179; con una larga lanza, un szabla, una o dos pistolas, y una carabina o arquebus, conocido en Polonia como una "bandolet". Polish hussars tambi&#195;&#169;n famoso por las alas que llevaban en sus espaldas. Seg&#195;&#186;n algunas teor&#195;&#173;as, que estaban dise&#195;&#177;adas para frustrar los ataques de t&#195;&#161;rtaro lassos, otra teor&#195;&#173;a es que la vibraci&#195;&#179;n de plumas hizo un extra&#195;&#177;o sonido que asustados caballos enemigo. Sin embargo, los experimentos llevados a cabo por volver a enactors y de la pel&#195;&#173;cula de la formulaci&#195;&#179;n desde el decenio de 1970 y m&#195;&#161;s recientemente por historiadores de Polonia en 2001 contradice esas ideas. Posiblemente las alas se usaron s&#195;&#179;lo durante los desfiles y no durante el combate, pero esta explicaci&#195;&#179;n es tambi&#195;&#169;n controvertida.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SWEDISH_KAROLIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Karolins were soldiers of the Swedish kings Charles XI and Charles XII. They were part of the yearly Swedish allotment system. The Karolins' tactics were to attack fiercely and remain unafraid. The soldiers also sustained stern discipline, which over the extensive course of a twenty-year-long war would prove vital. The Swedish army tactics of the time did not teach retreat, so the soldiers were known to never withdraw from battle.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le Caroleans &#195;&#169;taient des soldats des Rois su&#195;&#169;dois Charles XI et Charles XII. Ils faisaient partie du syst&#195;&#168;me su&#195;&#169;dois annuel d'attribution. La tactique du Caroleans &#195;&#169;tait d'attaquer violemment et rester sans peur. Les soldats ont &#195;&#169;galement soutenu la discipline s&#195;&#169;v&#195;&#168;re, qui au-dessus du cours &#195;&#169;tendu d'une vingt-ann&#195;&#169;e-longue guerre prouverait essentiel. La tactique su&#195;&#169;doise d'arm&#195;&#169;e du temps n'a pas enseign&#195;&#169; la retraite, ainsi les soldats ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; connus pour ne jamais se retirer de la bataille.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Caroleans waren Soldaten der schwedischen K&#195;&#182;nige Charles XI und Charles XII. Sie waren ein Teil des j&#195;&#164;hrlichen schwedischen Zuteilung Systems. Die Taktiken des Caroleans waren, w&#195;&#188;tend anzugreifen und furchtlos zu bleiben. Die Soldaten unterst&#195;&#188;tzten auch stern Disziplin, die &#195;&#188;ber dem umfangreichen Kurs eines Zwanzig-Jahr-langen Krieges lebenswichtiges pr&#195;&#188;fen w&#195;&#188;rde. Die schwedischen Armeetaktiken der Zeit unterrichteten nicht R&#195;&#188;ckzug, also bekannt die Soldaten, um nie von der Schlacht zur&#195;&#188;ckzutreten.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il Caroleans era soldati dei re svedesi Charles XI e Charles XII. Facevano parte del sistema svedese annuale di assegnazione. Le tattiche del Caroleans erano di attacare ferocemente e rimanere unafraid. I soldati inoltre hanno sostenuto la disciplina severa, che sopra il vasto corso di una guerra venti-anno-lunga dimostrerebbe vitale. Le tattiche svedesi dell'esercito del tempo non hanno insegnato la ritirata, in modo da i soldati sono stati conosciuti per non ritirarsi mai dalla battaglia.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El Caroleans era soldados de los reyes suecos Charles XI y Charles XII. Eran parte del sistema sueco anual de la asignaci&#195;&#179;n. Las t&#195;&#161;ctica del Caroleans eran atacar ferozmente y seguir siendo sin miedo. Los soldados tambi&#195;&#169;n sostuvieron la disciplina severa, que sobre el curso extenso de una guerra veinte-a&#195;&#177;o-larga probar&#195;&#173;a vital. Las t&#195;&#161;ctica suecas del ej&#195;&#169;rcito del tiempo no ense&#195;&#177;aron el retratamiento, as&#195;&#173; que conoc&#195;&#173;an a los soldados nunca para retirarse de batalla.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LITHUANIA_BAJORAS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Prior to the creation of the Lithuanian state by Mindaugas, lesser members of the nobility were called bajorai (singular - bajoras). They evolved from tribal leaders, and were chiefly responsible for waging wars and organizing raids operations into enemy's territory. After the establishment of a unified state they gradually became subordinates to greater Dukes, and later to the King of Lithuania. After Mindaugas death all Lithuanian rulers held the title Grand Duke, or king. In the late 14th century Grand Dukes Jogaila and Skirgaila began forming professional forces. Instead of calling all men to war, a class of professional warriors - bajorai (future nobles) - was formed. In the early 15th century, Vytautas the Great reformed the army of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania further: as there were not enough warriors, Vytautas relieved soldiers from taxes and labour on the land by granting them veldamai, dependent peasants. At first the land was given to the serving men until death (benefice), but during the 14th and 15th centuries most of it became patrimony, granted by privileges of the monarch. Whilst during the 14th century the Grand Duke owned about 2/3 of the Duchy's land, by 1569 he was a direct owner of only 1/3.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th century, the noble social class was already formed in Lithuania; for quite a long time it remained open and anyone could be ennobled for services to the Grand Duke. In time, the influence of lesser nobles decreased and greater nobles acquired increasingly more power, especially during the interregnum fights following Vytautas' death.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VIKING_BESERKER</Tag>
		<English>Berserker</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Berserker</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Berserker</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Berserker</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Berserk:Berserker</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#193;&#229;&#240;&#241;&#229;&#240;&#234;&#229;&#240;</Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>