<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- RESMOD v0.75 by CreativeMind -->
<!-- Game Text Infos -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_GOLD_COAST</Tag>
		<English>Gold Coast</English>
		<French>Côte d'Or</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#199;&#238;&#235;&#238;&#242;&#238;&#229; &#207;&#238;&#225;&#229;&#240;&#229;&#230;&#252;&#229;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_IVORY_COAST</Tag>
		<English>Ivory Coast</English>
		<French>Côte d'Ivoire</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#193;&#229;&#240;&#229;&#227; &#241;&#235;&#238;&#237;&#238;&#226;&#238;&#233; &#234;&#238;&#241;&#242;&#232;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_CUBA</Tag>
		<English>Cuba</English>
		<French>Cuba</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#202;&#243;&#225;&#224;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_BRAZIL</Tag>
		<English>Brazil</English>
		<French>Br&#233;sil</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#193;&#240;&#224;&#231;&#232;&#235;&#232;&#255;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_HUDSON</Tag>
		<English>Hudson Bay</English>
		<French>Baie de hudson</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#195;&#243;&#228;&#231;&#238;&#237;&#241;&#234;&#224;&#255; &#193;&#243;&#245;&#242;&#224;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_FAR_EASTERN_TREATY_PORT</Tag>
		<English>Far Eastern Treaty Port</English>
		<French>Comptoire Chinois</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#196;&#224;&#235;&#229;&#234;&#232;&#233; &#194;&#238;&#241;&#242;&#238;&#247;&#237;&#251;&#233; &#196;&#238;&#227;&#238;&#226;&#238;&#240;&#237;&#251;&#233; &#207;&#238;&#240;&#242;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_INDIA</Tag>
		<English>Indian Trading Post</English>
		<French>Comptoir Indien</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#200;&#237;&#228;&#232;&#233;&#241;&#234;&#224;&#255; &#212;&#224;&#234;&#242;&#238;&#240;&#232;&#255;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_EAST_INDIES</Tag>
		<English>East Indies</English>
		<French>Indon&#233;sie</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#194;&#238;&#241;&#242;&#238;&#247;&#237;&#251;&#229; &#200;&#237;&#228;&#232;&#232;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_MALAYSIA</Tag>
		<English>Malaya</English>
		<French>Malaisie</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#204;&#224;&#235;&#224;&#233;&#255;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_CAPE_TOWN</Tag>
		<English>Cape Town</English>
		<French>Le Cap</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#202;&#229;&#233;&#239;&#242;&#224;&#243;&#237;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_VIRGINIA</Tag>
		<English>Virginia</English>
		<French>Virginie</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#194;&#232;&#240;&#228;&#230;&#232;&#237;&#232;&#255;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_EAST_AFRICA</Tag>
		<English>East Africa</English>
		<French>Afrique de l'Est</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#194;&#238;&#241;&#242;&#238;&#247;&#237;&#224;&#255; &#192;&#244;&#240;&#232;&#234;&#224;</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_ENCYCLOPEDIE</Tag>
		<English>L'Encyclop&#233;die</English>
		<French>L'Encyclopedie</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>&#221;&#237;&#246;&#232;&#234;&#235;&#238;&#239;&#229;&#228;&#232;&#255; ("L'Encyclopedie")</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_AZTEC_CONQUEST</Tag>
		<English>Aztec Conquest</English>
		<French>Conquête Azt&#232;que</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Aztec Conquest</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_INCA_CONQUEST</Tag>
		<English>Inca Conquest</English>
		<French>Conquête Inca</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Inca Conquest</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_HISPANIOLA</Tag>
		<English>Hispaniola</English>
		<French>Saint-Domingue</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Hispaniola</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_QUEBEC</Tag>
		<English>Quebec</English>
		<French>Qu&#233;bec</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Quebec</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_NEW_ENGLAND</Tag>
		<English>New England</English>
		<French>Nouvelle-Angleterre</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>New England</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_JAMAICA</Tag>
		<English>Jamaica</English>
		<French>Jama&#239;que</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Jamaica</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PANAMA</Tag>
		<English>Panama</English>
		<French>Panama</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Panama</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_LOUISIANA</Tag>
		<English>Louisiana</English>
		<French>Louisiane</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Louisiana</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PHILLIPPINES</Tag>
		<English>Philippines</English>
		<French>Philippines</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Phillipines</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>		
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_GUINEA</Tag>
		<English>Guinea</English>
		<French>Guin&#233;e</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Guinea</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_FREE_BONUS_RESOURCE1</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Provides %D1_Mod </English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Fournit %D1_Mod </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[ICON_BULLET]&#206;&#225;&#229;&#241;&#239;&#229;&#247;&#232;&#226;&#224;&#229;&#242; %D1_Mod</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_FREE_BONUS_RESOURCE2</Tag>
		<English>[SPACE] [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </English>
		<French>[SPACE] [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[SPACE] [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK]</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PPROJECT_REQUIRES1</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Requires [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Requiert [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[ICON_BULLET]&#210;&#240;&#229;&#225;&#243;&#229;&#242; [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK]</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PPROJECT_REQUIRES2</Tag>
		<English> [SPACE] (%D1_Mod) </English>
		<French> [SPACE] (%D1_Mod) </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[SPACE] (%D1_Mod)</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_FREE_BONUS_RESOURCE1</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Provides %D1_Mod </English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Fournit %D1_Mod </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[ICON_BULLET]&#206;&#225;&#229;&#241;&#239;&#229;&#247;&#232;&#226;&#224;&#229;&#242; %D1_Mod</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_FREE_BONUS_RESOURCE2</Tag>
		<English>[SPACE] [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </English>
		<French>[SPACE] [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[SPACE] [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK]</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PPROJECT_REQUIRES1</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Requires [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]Requiert [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[ICON_BULLET]&#210;&#240;&#229;&#225;&#243;&#229;&#242; [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK]</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PPROJECT_REQUIRES2</Tag>
		<English> [SPACE] (%D1_Mod) </English>
		<French> [SPACE] (%D1_Mod) </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[SPACE] (%D1_Mod)</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PREREQ_BONUS</Tag>
		<English> [ICON_BULLET]Requires [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </English>
		<French> [ICON_BULLET]Requiert [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>[ICON_BULLET]Requires [LINK=literal]%s1_Bonus[\LINK] </Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_ENCYCLOPEDIE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]"L'Encyclop&#233;die, ou dictionnaire raisonn&#233; des sciences, des arts et des m&#233;tiers" (English: Encyclopedia, or a systematic dictionary of the sciences, arts, and crafts) was a general encyclopedia published in France between 1751 and 1772, with later supplements and revisions in 1772, 1777 and 1780 and numerous foreign editions and later derivatives.[PARAGRAPH:1]Its introduction, the Preliminary Discourse, is considered an important exposition of Enlightenment ideals. The Encyclop&#233;die's self-professed aim was "to change the way people think." It was hoped that the work would eventually encompass all of human knowledge; Denis Diderot explained the goal of the project as "All things must be examined, debated, investigated without exception and without regard for anyone's feelings."[PARAGRAPH:1]The Encyclop&#233;die was originally meant to be simply a French translation of Ephraim Chambers's Cyclopaedia (1728). The translation was commissioned by Paris book publisher Andr&#233; Le Breton in 1743 to John Mills, an English resident in France. In May 1745 Le Breton announced the work as available for sale - however to Le Breton's dismay, Mills had not done the work he was commissioned to do; in fact, he could barely read and write French and did not even own a copy of Cyclopaedia. Le Breton had been swindled, and so he physically beat Mills with a cane - Mills sued on assault charges, but Le Breton was acquitted in court as being justified. Setting out to find a new editor, Le Breton engaged Jean Paul de Gua de Malves. Among those hired by Malves were the young &#201;tienne Bonnot de Condillac, Jean le Rond d'Alembert and Denis Diderot. Within thirteen months, in August 1747, Malves was fired due to his rigid methods. Le Breton then hired Diderot and Jean d'Alembert as the new editors. Diderot would remain editor for the next 25 years, seeing the Encyclop&#233;die through to completion.[PARAGRAPH:1]The work comprised 35 volumes, with 71,818 articles, and 3,129 illustrations. The first 28 volumes were published between 1751 and 1766 and were edited by Diderot - although some of the later picture-only volumes were not actually printed until 1772. The remaining five volumes were completed by other editors in 1777, along with a two volume index in 1780. Many of the most noted figures of the French enlightenment contributed to the work including Voltaire, Rousseau, and Montesquieu. The single greatest contributor was Louis de Jaucourt who wrote 17,266 articles, or about 8 per day between 1759 and 1765.[PARAGRAPH:1]The writers of the encyclopedia saw it as a vehicle to covertly destroy superstitions while overtly providing access to human knowledge. It was a summary of thought and belief of the Enlightenment. In ancien r&#233;gime France it caused a storm of controversy, due mostly to its tone of religious tolerance. The encyclopedia praised Protestant thinkers and challenged Catholic dogma, and classified religion as a branch of philosophy, not as the ultimate source of knowledge and moral advice. The entire work was banned by royal decree and officially closed down after the first seven volumes in 1759; but because it had many highly placed supporters, notably Madame de Pompadour, work continued "in secret". In truth, secular authorities did not want to disrupt the commercial enterprise which employed hundreds of people. To appease the church's enemies of the project, the authorities had officially banned the enterprise, but they turned a blind eye to its continued existence.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Encyclop&#233;die played an important role in the intellectual ferment leading to the French Revolution. While it is debatable that the editors intended to have a radical influence on French society, it can hardly be denied that it did. The Encyclop&#233;die denied that the teachings of the Catholic Church could be treated as authoritative in matters of science. The editors also refused to treat the decisions of political powers as definitive in intellectual or artistic questions. Given that Paris was the intellectual capital of Europe at the time and that many European leaders used French as their administrative language, these ideas had the capacity to spread.</English>
		<French>.</French> 
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_EAST_INDIA_COMPANY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Following the voyages of the early Portugese and Spanish explorers around the coast of Africa, India, the East Indies, China and Japan, many European nations established trading posts and plantation colonies to exploit the abundant herbs, spices, fruits and precious stones so much in demand in Europe. In order to attract investment in the new colonies and spread the risk of trade with such far-off areas of the world, a number of joint stock companies were formed under royal charter or license in England, France, the Netherlands and other European countries. 
[TAB]The first was the British East India Company, founded in 1600 for trade in India and China. Trading largely in cotton, silk, dye, tea and opium, it was enormously profitable and even established absolute rule over the Indian sub-continent from 1757 to 1858. Another was the Dutch East India Company, formed in 1602 which developed a monoply in the nutmeg and clove trade in the Spice Islands, Java and Sumatra, establishing vast plantations using slave labour and ruling much of the East Indies on behalf of the Dutch Republic. Other notable East India Companies were formed by France, Portugal, Denmark and Sweden. </English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_WEST_INDIA_COMPANY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The late 16thC. saw the establishment of new European colonies in the New World, following the voyages of exploration by the Spanish aand Portugese and the conquest of the Aztec and Incan empires. The earliest colonies,
like Cuba, Hispaniola, Brazil and New Spain, were established as royal concessions to wealthy aristocrats who ruled in conjunction with the "Casa de Contracion" (House of Trade) which strictly controlled all exploration, imported goods, and the foundation and administration of colonies on behalf of the Crown.
[TAB]With the early 17thC. came the establishment of joint-stock companies in England, France and the Netherlands, selling shares to investors to spread the risk of trade and hazardous sea voyages in the development of colonial ventures in the New World.
The earliest companies were formed under Royal charters granted to the Virginia Company, the London Company and the Plymouth Company, set up to develop the Jamestown and New England colonies. Later examples included the French West India Company, the Dutch West India Company, the Danish West India Company, the Hudson Bay Company and the Compagnie de l'Occident.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_AZTEC_CONQUEST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In Feb. 1519, the Spanish conquistador, Hernan Cortes, landed with an army of 530 men on the coast of Mexico near present-day Veracruz. Gathering a large force including thousands of Tlaxcalan Indian allies he first massacred the Aztec town of Cholula then advanced on their capital, Tenochtitlan. Warily, Moctezuma, the Aztec emperor treated the invaders with caution and respect, suspecting that Cortes was an incarnation of the white feathered serpent god "Quetzalcoatl".
[TAB]At first the Spaniards seemed welcome but increasingly alienated their hosts with greater and greater demands for gold as tribute. As Cortes put it, "We Spaniards suffer from a disease that only gold can cure". All the Spanish demands were met but Cortes demanded more, finally imprisoning Moctezuma in his own palace to discourage any Aztec revolt. But warfare against the Aztecs continued for another year with great losses on both sides, first one gaing the upper hand then the other.
[TAB]Finally the Spaniards and their Tlaxcalan allies triumphed and Tenochtitlan fell in August 1521 when the last Aztec emperor, Cuauhtemoc, surrendered to Cortes. The "Council of the Indies" was instituted in the newly-renamed Mexico City in 1524 and the first "AUdienca" in 1535 as the lands of the Aztecs were formally incorporated by Charles V into the Spanish Empire as the province of "New Spain", the largest and potentially the most wealthy of his overseas possessions.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_INCA_CONQUEST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]When Spanish conquistadors led by Francisco Pizarro arrived in 1528 the Empire of the Inca extended the length of the Pacific coast from Columbia to Chile. This vast empire was unstable and difficult to govern, so when the Emperor, Huayna Capac and his heir died suddenly of smallpox, his empire was plunged into a civil war between two rival sons, Huascar and Atahualpa. 
[TAB]The arrival of a force of 182 Spanish soldiers, many with firearms and horses, caused great panic as smallpox and measles decimated the Incan and subject populations. Pizarro met Atahualpa demanding gold as tribute and conversion of the Inca to Christianity but despite complying with most of the Spanish demands, Atahualpa was captured and later executed by Pizarro in 1533. Despite the defeat of the rival Huascar, stiff Incan resistance continued until 1535 when Pizarro captured Cuzco and founded Lima as the capitol of the new Spanish colony. 
[TAB]After a period of civil war between rival Spanish factions Pizarro was himself assassinated in 1541 and it was not until 1542 that the last organized rebellion ended. Finally Spanish Royal authority was established in Lima with the creation of the Viceroyalty of New Castille later becoming the Viceroyalty of Peru as all Incan resistance came to an end with the capture and execution of the last Inca, Tupac Amaru, at Vilcabamba in 1572.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_HUDSON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In 1610, the English explorer, Henry Hudson lead an expedition to the NW coast of the Americas in search of a Northwest passage which might lead directly to India. Rounding the tip of Labrador he explored the east coast of Hudson Bay as far south as the lower shores of James Bay. The late 17thC saw the establishment of a French monopoly of the fur trade in the area from their bases in Quebec and Montreal, a monopoly the English Crown was keen to challenge.
[TAB]Finally, an English expedition guided by Cree Indians and French fur traders explored the Hudson Bay and James Bay area before founding Fort Rupert in 1668, putting them in direct competition with the French. "The Governor and Company of Adventurers of England Trading in Hudson Bay" was incorporated in 1670 by a Royal charter from King Charles II granting them a monopoly over the fur trade in the lands north of the Great Lakes which was known as "Rupert's Land".
[TAB]Frequent wars between the English and French saw both sides battle for control of the lucrative fur trade before the whole area as far as the Great Plains was ceded to Britain by the Treaty of Utrecht in 1713. The Company, with York Factory as its headquarters, was renamed as the Hudson's Bay Company and merged with the NorthWest Company of Montreal in 1821, controlling vast tracts of fur-producing lands as far west as the Rockies and the Missouri River.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_LOUISIANA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first Europeans to visit Louisiana were the Spanish in 1528, then by the conquistador, Hernado de Soto, who discovered the mouth of the Mississippi river in 1541. But it was not until the late 16thC. that the French established a foothold in the region, when Robert Cavalier de la Salle, exploring the river south from the Great lakes, first founded St. Louis and La Belise (Biloxi) in 1682. Once the French became established on the Mississippi the port of New orleans was founded in 1722.
[TAB]The region was first settled by German immigrants and French colonists from Saint Domingue who imported thousands of African slaves to develop vast tobacco, rice and cotton plantations along the floodplains of the river. Despite many slave revolts which caused much unrest, the port of New Orleans became the largest slave market in North America. The British conquest of Quebec brought a wave of French Acadian refugees, many of whom intermarried with escaped slaves and fled deep into the swamps of the interior, giving rise to the mixed race Creole and Cajun populations we see today.
[TAB]With the fall of French Canada and the Treaty of Paris in 1763, the Louisiana territories were awarded to the Spanish who ruled until 1800 when it was briefly acquired for the French by Napoleon Bonaparte. Finally, the vast territory leading up into Canada and far into the NorthWest was sold to the United States in 1803 as what became known as the "Louisiana Purchase".</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_NEW_ENGLAND_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In the early 16thC. following the Spanish and Portugese exploration and conquest of the New World, Iberian claims came into conflict with other European powers, chiefly the Dutch, French and English. French colonization focused on Quebec with its rich fur resources while the Dutch and English settled the east coast of North America. English immigration in the 17thC., often initiated by people fleeing from religious persecution in Europe, resulted in the founding of several colonies on the Northeast coast which soon became known as New England.
[TAB]The first was the New Plymouth colony, founded in 1620 by Puritan settlers under a patent from the London Virginia Company. Despite initial conflicts and the threat of starvation, the colony survived and attracted further emigration from England. The Massachusetts Bay Colony was established in 1629 with the arrival of 400 English settlers and further settlements were added in the following years, including the Connecticut, New Hampshire and Rhode Island colonies.
[TAB]The New England colonies prospered in subsequent years, with their abundant fish, fur and timber resources. The fur trade provided much needed income in the early years. A growing agricultural economy provided increasing amounts of food, exporting large quantities of wheat, corn and flax to England and her colonies in the West Indies. Fish was also an important food source and the the vast forests provided valuable timber, giving rise to a thriving whaling and ship-building industry in ports like Boston, Salem and Nantucket by the mid-18th.C.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_QUEBEC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Early French exploration of the New World centered chiefly on the search for a Northwest Passage to India. Following visits by Basque and Breton fishermen to the rich cod fisheries of the Grand Banks near Newfoundland, the French explorer Jacques Cartier explored the Gulf of St. Lawrence and the river as far as present-day Montreal in 1535. After years of French fishing and trading expeditions, Samuel de Champlain founded the town of Quebec in 1608 as the capital of the colony of New France and explored the Great Lakes region.
[TAB]France quickly developed a lucrative fur trade with the local Algonquin and Huron tribes by forging alliances with them against their enemies, the Iroquois. Though the population of the colony was rarely more than a few hundred, the French encouraged young men to live among the Huron,learning their language and customs. These men, known as "coureurs des bois" acted as fur traders, explorers and guides, helping to extend French influence beyond the Great Lakes and the Ohio River.
[TAB]New France prospered with increased immigration in 17thC and 18thCs., despite frequent wars with the English and their native allies. The towns of Trois Rivieres and Montreal were founded as the fertile plains of the St. Lawrence river were farmed, the forests provided valuable timber and Jesuit missionaries spread Christianity among friendly tribes. But New France finally fell with the English capture of Quebec in 1759 during the Seven Years War and most French territories in North America were ceded to Britain after the Treaty of Paris in 1763.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_VIRGINIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first English colony in the New World was at Roanoke in present-day Virginia when the English adventurer, Sir Walter Raliegh, sent two groups of colonists to the area in 1584-87 though their settlements eventually failed. A further attempt by the Virginia Company in 1607 established a colony at Jamestown which survived despite being ill-equiped, nearly vanishing in the winter of 1609-10. The colony grew and soon flourished as the first valuable cargo of Virginia-grown tobacco arrived in England in 1612.
[TAB]The Virginia colony began to prosper with a thriving tobacco industry and a lucrative agriculture and fur trade as more settlers from England and the first African slaves arrived from Angola. Despite repeated conflict with the local Powatan tribes, it grew rapidly and established control of the rich coastal plain by 1646. Meanwhile the Virginia Company's charter was revoked and the colony came under direct control of the Crown, who realized its truly great potential.
[TAB]Most Virginia colonists remained loyal during the English Civil War and many Royalists fled to the colony. establishing some of the area's most important families. After the Restoration, Charles II rewarded Virginia's loyalty with the nickname "Old Dominion" by which it is still known today. The Virginia Colony, with it's wealthy tobacco and cotton economy based on great plantations worked by slaves, became the richest British colony in North America, which it remained right up until the American Revolution.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_GOLD_COAST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]First explored by Prince Henry the Navigator in 1471, the Gold Coast was the region of West Africa now corresponding to the nation of Ghana. The Portugese built the first colony in 1482 with a castle at Elmina (or" the mine"), so named for the fabulous amounts of gold they discovered there. The Dutch also colonised the area from 1598 and absorbed all Portugese holdings in 1642 when the area became known as the Dutch Gold Coast, run by the Dutch West india Company centered on their capital and fortress town of Fort Nassau.
[TAB]There was also the Brandenburger Gold Coast founded in 1682 which became known as the Prussian Gold Coast. Sweden established a colony in 1650 but it was seized by Denmark in 1663, forming the basis of the Danish Gold Coast. The entire coastline became dotted by more than 30 forts and castles built to protect the interests of Dutch, Danish and British merchants, the largest concentration of military architecture outside Europe. Finally, by the 19thC. the whole area was ceded by the Dutch to the control of the British African Company.
[TAB]The opening of European plantations in the New World expanded the demand for African slaves, which soon overshadowed the importance of gold from the area. Much of the conflict between European nations on the coast and competing African kingdoms was a struggle for control of the highly profitable slave trade. By the 18thC. as much as 5000 slaves per year were shipped to the Americas from the Gold Coast alone. Later British control of the Gold Coast however became dominated by their efforts to eliminate and abolish the slave trade altogether.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_IVORY_COAST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first Europeans to explore the west coast of Africa in the late 15thC were the Portugese who traded along the Ivory Coast with native peoples for gold, ivory and pepper. The establishment of European plantation colonies in The New World during the 16thC. spawned a new demand for slaves, which soon became the major export of the native kingdoms in the West African coastal regions. The Ivory Coast, unlike the Gold Coast to the east, lacked sheltered harbours along its coastline, which prevented the Europeans from establishing permanent trading posts and forts.
[TAB]Seaborne trade, therefore, was irregular along the coast and the slave trade in particular had little effect pn the peoples of the Ivory Coast. A profitable trade in ivory however did develop in the 17thC, giving the region its name, but it declined and virtually died out by the late 18thC. due to the decimation of the local elephant population. Trade in gold, pepper and tropical fruits continued with the European colonies to the east but the Ivory Coast itself saw little European settlement or permanent trading links until well into the 17thC.
[TAB]The earliest French voyage to the West African coast was in 1483 but the first permanent settlement, Saint Louis in present-day Senegal, was not established until the mid-17thC. The first French presence in the Ivory Coast came with founding of a mission at Assimie near the borders of the Gold coast in 1637. But its status as an established colony did not come about until the early 1840's when the French signed treaties with local tribes and proclaimed a protectorate over the whole Ivory Coast with its first capital at Grand Bassam.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_EAST_AFRICA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Portugal was the first European nation to explore the east coast of Africa with Vasco da Gama visiting the area in 1498 on his way to India. Venice had previously controlled the trade routes between Europe and Asia but all land access to the Orient was effectively closed by the Ottoman Turks in the 15thC. Their in East Africa began in 1505 with the capture of Kilwa and Mombassa from the Omani Arabs who had previously controlled the lucrative coastal spice, coffee and slave trade based at the ports of Mombassa, Dar es Salaam and the island of Zanzibar.
[TAB]Throughout the 16thC. the Portugese dominated the Indian Ocean due to their strategic control of the East African ports and shipping lanes, their naval vessels demanding a high tariff on all goods transported to Europe from India. The construction of Fort Jesus at Mombassa in 1593 and the founding of the Mozambique colony at Lourenco Marques solidified Portugese control of East Africa, but that influence was often interrupted by Omani Arab, Dutch and British incursions in the 17th and 18th. centuries as they soon lost control of their Indian Ocean monopoly.
[TAB]Finally, Portugese dominance ended as they lost interest in the spice trade and were ousted from Mombassa and other ports by the Omani Arabs in 1730. Arab colonization of East Africa revived as they planted large clove estates and increased their supply of slaves to Europe. Despite the continuation of the Portugese colony of Mozambique, Omani Arab dominance of the coast continued until the early 19thC. when the British blockaded Zanzibar, Mombassa and other ports to eradicate the slave trade and occupied the territory which later became Kenya and Tanzania.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_CAPE_TOWN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The history of the Cape Colony began Bartholomeu Dias, a Portugese explorer, discovered the Cape of Good Hope in 1488. In 1497, Vasco da Gama sailed along the coast of South Africa seeking a sea route to India. Through the 16thC. various fleets paused on their way to the Indian Ocean in order to restock on water, vegetables and meat, but it was not until 1652 that the Dutch East India Company established the first resupply station in the Cape Colony with the founding of Capetown. Confined to trading for cattle with the local Khokhoi peoples, the Colony remained undeveloped for many years.
[TAB]But trading relations with local people became strained as more and more white-owned farms were established to feed the Cape Colony, encroaching on the surrounding area and causing war with the Khokhoi and Xhosa inhabitants. Nomadic Dutch farmers, known as "Trekboers", migrated deep into the dry, grassy interior from the richer but limited coastal areas, coming into increasing conflict with native cattle herders for the best grazing land. Throughout the 18thC. the Cape Colony remained largely an agricultural subsistence economy with only the promise of some rich mineral potential.
[TAB]Cape society became increasingly diverse from Europe as many Dutch colonists intermarried with local peoples creating the Cape Coloured mixed race population so predominant today. The emergence of "Afikaans" as a distinct Dutch dialect further distinguished the Cape population from their European roots. The beginning of the 19thC saw the discovery of vast quantities of gold and diamonds, sparking a fresh new wave of European immigration and speculation, prompting the British government to acquire Capetown and the Cape Colony from the Dutch East India Company in 1807.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_JAMAICA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Jamaica, the 3rd. largest island in the Caribbean, was populated by the Taino or Arawak people when Christopher Columbus arrived in 1494 to claim the area for Spain. The natives were largely exterminated by massacres and disease as the Spanish occupation began in 1509 with the founding of Villa de la Vega (now called Spanish Town) and African slaves imported to work the new sugar plantations which would become the mainstay of the island economy. Jamaica also became a base of operations for many European buccaneers attacking Spanish shipping, like the pirate captain Henry Morgan, in return for discouraging other European powers from attacking the island.
[TAB]Between 1555 and 1655, Spanish Jamaica was subject to numerous pirate attacks from their bases on the north coast, the last of these resulting in the English occupation of the island. In 1657 the new Governor of Jamaica invited English buccaneers to base themselves at Port Royal while attacking Spanish treasure fleets in order to deter Spanish aggression. Port Royal remained a major base for pirates and privateers until it was destroyed by an earthquake in 1692. After the disaster, Kingston was founded on the large natural harbour, rapidly becoming the major commercial centre of Jamaica.
[TAB]Many African slaves arrived via the Atlantic slave trade to work on the sugar cane and coffee plantations and sugar exports made Jamaica one the most valuable colonial possessions in the world for the next 150 years. Throughout that period there were rising racial tensions as Jamaica experienced one of the highest instances of slave uprisings of any Caribbean island.
[TAB]The colony's slave population came to outnumber whites by 20-1, and many escaped slaves, known as "Maroons" established independent communities in the mountainous interior innaccesible to the British. Continued racial unrest persisted into the 19thC., contributing to the abolishment of slavery throughout the British Empire in 1834.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_CUBA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In October 1492, Christopher Columbus landed on the coast of Cuba, which was inhabited by the indigenous Taino and Ciboney peoples, sometimes known as the Arawak, who were primarily farmers and hunter gatherers. In 1511, the first Spanish settlement was founded at Baracoa by the conquistador, Diego Velasquez de Cuellar, and other towns soon followed including the future capitol, San Christobal de la Habana in 1515. The Spanish enslaved the approx. 100,000 indigenous people, sending some to Spain as servants while putting the rest to the searching and mining of gold. Within a hundred years the indigenous poulation was all but exterminated by European infectious diseases and massacres.
[TAB]The Spanish colonists learned the growing of tobacco and smoking it in cigars, giving rise to an extensive system of tobacco plantations which earned valuable profits from the export of dried and cured tobacco products to Europe. A similiar system of sugar growing became established which soon became the prime export earner of the colony. Cuba remained a valuable Spanish possession for nearly 400 years with it's thriving plantation-based economy and an important mining sector particularly in gold and gems. But it's true value to the Spanish Crown was the income derived from the export of tobacco and sugar to Western Europe and later to North America.
[TAB]The plantation system was manned largely by slaves, firstly indigenous Indians and those imported from the colony of Hispaniola but later by slaves traded from West Africa. Early restrictive Spanish trade laws and the closure of Cuban ports to European traffic prevented the economy from flourishing in the early years but an easing of regulations, followed by the influx of African slaves and advances in sugar refining processes in the 17thC.-18thC brought a dramatic boom in the Cuban economy. Improvements in road transport, water mills and steam engines allowed Cuba to produce a higher quality of sugar than elsewhere in the Caribbean so that by 1800 Cuba became the world's leading supplier of sugar.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_HISPANIOLA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Derived from the Spanish "La Espanola", the island of Hispaniola today consists of Haiti and the Dominican Republic. Originally inhabited by the Taino or Arawak peoples, it was first visited by Christopher Columbus in 1492 during his first voyage to the New World. Although their initial site at La Navidad was destroyed, the first Spanish towns of La Isabella and Santo Domingo in 1496 were to become the oldest continually inhabited settlements in the Americas. The indigenous Taino population of the island became so rapidly decimated by European diseases like smallpox and measles and the harsh Spanish treatment that the initial population of about a half a million fell to less than 60,000 by 1535.
[TAB]As Spain conquered new regions in the Americas its initial interest in Hispaniola began to wane. Several Taino revolts in the early 16thC. continually troubled the Spanish colonists although some plantations were established around Santo Domingo as increasing numbers of African slaves were imported after 1510. Suger cane was introduced from the Canary Islands and the first sugar mill in the Americas was established in 1516 but many slaves began to escape and join Taino rebels in the mountainous interior. The Spanish gradually lost control of the northern and western parts of Hispaniola in the 17thC. as English, French and Dutch pirates established bases on the coasts and preyed constantly on Spanish shipping.
[TAB]French buccaneers settled on the nearby island of Tortuga in 1625 and moved onto the Western coast which they dubbed "Grande Terre", founding settlements like Cap Francois which were recognized by the French Crown in 1660. Now called "Saint Domingue" the colony attracted French settlers who established tobacco, indigo and coffee plantations with the first sugar mill being built in 1685. Spain ceded the western third of the island to France in 1697 as "Saint Domingue" grew increasingly wealthy with its exports of sugar, coffee and cotton, outproducing the entire British West Indies put together. Finally after increasing slave revolts and unrest, it broke free from Napoleonic France in 1804 becoming the Republic of Haiti.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PANAMA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In 1501, Rodrigo de Bastidas became the first European to explore the narrow isthmus of Panama which lay between the continents of North and South America. Christopher Columbas explored the Caribbean coast the following year and further Spanish expeditions followed to what became known as "Tierra Firma" (or dry land). In 1510 the settlement of Santa Maria la Antigua del Darien was founded by Vasco Nunez de Balboa, which was the first permanent settlement on the American mainland. After a number of violent engagements with the indigenous peoples, whose chiefs became allies and were baptized, Balboa became the first European to sight the Pacific Ocean in 1513.
[TAB]Renamed the "Castillo del Oro", the colony's capitol was moved to the present site of Panama City on the Pacific Coast in 1525. Roads were built linking it to the fortified ports of Porto Bello and Nombre de Dios to facilitate the trans-shipment of goods from west to east. It is estimated that as much as 60% of all gold entering Spain from the New World between 1531 and 1660 was shipped from these two ports alone. Exploration and conquest expeditions to the north and south secured the land and riches of Central and South America as a number of ships were built on the west coast enabling further exploration of the Pacific and a secure sea route to the Philippines and the East Indies.
[TAB]In 1538 the Real Audencia of Panama was established with jurisdiction from Nicaragua in the north to Columbia in the south. As Panama was colonized, the remaining indigenous Indians who had survived diseases, massacres and enslavement fled into the forests along with a number of escaped African slaves. And although Panama remained fairly prosperous for its first two centuries, its importance became minimal as its shipments of gold dwindled and Spain's power in Europe eroded. With the threat of piracy and advances in navigation making the sea route around Cape Horn more profitable, Panama further declined in the 18thC., finally gaining its independence from Spain in 1821.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_BRAZIL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In 1500 a fleet led by Pedro Alves Cabral, on its way to India via Africa, sighted the coast of Brazil and claimed the land in the name of Manuel I, King of Portugal. The leading sea powers, Castille and Portugal had effectively divided the New World between them in 1494, under the Treaty of Tordesillas which decided that land to the east of a fixed meridian should belong to Portugal while the rest of South America was assigned to Spain. But after Cabral's voyage Portugal concentrated its attentions on its lucrative possessions in Africa and India while showing little interest in Brazil, apart from occasional expeditions which mapped the coast and collected valuable brazil wood for its rich dye used in staining luxury textiles.
[TAB]The Portugese soon realized that other nations like the French were showing an interest in the area, so in 1530 they sent a expedition under Martim Afonso de Susa to patrol the coast and found the first settlements at Sao Vincente and Salvador on the NE coast. Brazil was set up as 15 private hereditary "captaincies" like Pernambuco, which prospered by growing sugar cane, and Sao Vincente,which profited from the traffic in indigenous slaves. But most failed, prompting the Crown to send Tome de Susa in 1549 to establish a centralized colonial government with it's capitol at Salvador, while setting up Jesuit missions to convert the local Indians and expelling a French Calvanist colony at Rio de Janeiro.
[TAB]Initial attempts at finding gold and silver having failed, the colonists turned to a plantation economy exporting tobacco, cotton and esp. sugar to Europe, employing indigenous labour at first but increasing numbers of African slaves. The sugar industry went into decline in the 17thC. due to competition from the Caribbean and Dutch attempts at settling the north coast finally ended in 1661. A gold rush in the early 18thC. brought thousands of immigrants and adventurers to Brazil and the capitol was moved to Rio de Janeiro in 1763, though as gold production declined Brazil sunk into stagnation by 1800. </English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_EAST_INDIES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The East Indies area is largely comprised of the present-day countries of Indonesia, Malaysia and the Philippines, and was first explored by Portugese navigators in the late 15th. and early 16th. centuries. In 1498, Vasco da Gama sailed around the coast of Africa, reaching India, and in 1510 the ports of Goa and Malacca were conquered by Afonso de Albuquerque. Later the Portugese explored much of East Asia, landing in Taiwan, Japan, Java and Timor and even the north coast of Australia. From 1595 and 1663, the Dutch-Portugese War primarily involved Dutch trading companies invading many Portugese colonies in the East Indies, resulting in the loss of Portugal's Indian Ocean trade monopoly.
[TAB]The Dutch founded a single East India Company in 1602 which was granted a monopoly over all East Asian trade, empowering it to build forts, maintain armies and conduct treaties with local rulers. In 1603 the first permanent Dutch trading post was set up in West Java and another at Jaykarta (later Batavia) in 1611. Expeditions by the English East India Company threatened the Dutch monopoly of the spice trade, though they largely withdrew from the East Indies by 1623, leaving Dutch control of the region secure. In 1619, Batavia became the capitol of the Dutch East Indies as they established large plantations using local slave labour with a complete monopoly of the export of pepper, nutmeg, and cloves to Europe.
[TAB]By 1670, the Dutch East India Company had become the richest private company in the world and a state-within-a-state, with over 150 merchant ships, 40 warships, 50,000 employees and an army of 10,000 soldiers. But the closure of its trading rights in Japan and China, wars with Britain disrupting its contact with Europe and competition from French and Danish companies for the pepper trade, made serious inroads in its trading monopoly. Despite attempts to diversify into crops like tea, coffee, cotton and sugar, the economic power of the Dutch East India Company declined throughout the 18thC. and many Dutch possesions in the East Indies were finally occupied by Britain during the Napoleonic wars.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_INDIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Portugese were the first Europeans to set up trading posts in India, landing near the city of Calicut in South India in 1498. The next three centuries were marked by the pursuit of trade and competition between European powers as the Dutch, French, British and Danes also established trading colonies on the Indian sub-continent. The Portugese founded a string of trading forts along the west coast, at Damman, Bombay and Goa from where the Portugese Viceroy governed their empire in Asia from 1530. The Dutch finally defeated the Portugese in most of India by 1660, who withdrew to their important trading enclave of Goa, where they remained until forcibly ousted by the Government of India in 1961.
[TAB]The Dutch also founded a number of trading posts in the mid-17thC., notably at Cochin on the Malabar Coast and Pulicat on India's east coast. But their most important possession was the port of Chinsura near present-day Calcutta on the Bengal coast which was founded in 1625, where they traded in opium, salt, muslin and spices. Other Indian trading posts were founded by the Danish East India Company and especially the French East India Company at Pondicherry on the east coast and Chandannagar in Bengal. Despite being in a state of continual conflict with the Dutch and the English, the French maintained a strong commercial presence on the Indian coast until the mid-19thC.
[TAB]The British first gained a colonial foothold in India in 1612 when the Mughal Emperor Jahangir signed a treaty with James I, giving the British East India Company exclusive rights to reside and conduct trade at Surat and surrounding territories. Other trading concessions were later established at Madras in 1639, Bombay (1668) and Calcutta (1690), trading chiefly in cotton, silk, tea, indigo dye and saltpetre. It greatly expanded in wealth and influence through the 18th.C, esp. with its monopoly on the saltpetre trade so vital to British miltary firearms in the Seven Years War and other conflicts and assumed direct rule over the Indian sub-continent on behalf of the British government from 1757 to 1858.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_FAR_EASTERN_TREATY_PORT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Portugal became the first European nation to establish a trading post in China in 1535 when traders obtained the right to anchor ships and carry out trading activities at Macau where a permanent settlement was later founded in 1553. Chinese and European merchants flocked to the port, which became an important link from Goa in India to Nagasaki in Japan and Mexico via Manila in the Philippines. Despite several Dutch attempts to occupy the colony, Macau enjoyed a lucrative monopoly until 1685 when the loss of Malacca severed its trade links with Goa. The closure of Japan to foriegn ships and the decision by the Chinese Emperor to allow trade with all other foriegn countries also hastened its decline in importance.
[TAB]Over the next century, the Dutch, French, Danish and Russians all established trading posts and forts on the Chinese coast, notably at Darien, Guangzou, Shanghai and Macau. The Dutch East India Company operated throughout East Asia, trading silver and copper from Japan to India and China in return for silk, cotton, porcelain and spices, and were instrumental in introducing European technology to China and Japan. From their trading post at Dejima, an artificial island off the coast of Nagasaki, the Dutch Protestants in fact were the only Europeans permitted to trade with the Japanese, who had become increasingly suspicious of the activities of Spanish and Portugese Jesuit missionaries.
[TAB]By the mid-17C., The English, Dutch, and the French had begun to challenge the Portugese monopoly of trade with Asia, forming joint-stock companies to raise the capital to finance voyages and establish trading missions. The British, Dutch and French East India Companies aimed to share the lucrative spice trade from the Indian sub-continent and the East Asian archipelago, also setting up trading posts on the Chinese coast at Darien, Canton, Shanghai and Macau where they exported silk, jade, ivory and porcelain to Europe in exchange for opium and gold. The British established a trading mission at HongKong which later grew into an important Crown colony and wealthy commercial centre in the 19th. and 20th. centuries.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_MALAYSIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The modern area of Malaysia consists mostly of the Malay Peninsula and the island of Sumatra, which was visited by Muslim traders in the 10thC., although Islam was not fully established until the 15thC, most prominently with the powerful Malacca Sultanate at the port of Melaka which spread Islam throught the archipelago. The first Europeans to arrive were the Portugese under the leadership of Afonso de Albuquerque who seized Melaka in 1511, making it the first centre of Portugese trading activities in the Far East. By the end of the 16thC. the colony grew very wealthy as the tin mines of northern Malaya were exploited by European traders and the Portugese gained control of the spice-rich Malaku islands.
[TAB]In 1607, the nearby Sultanate of Aceh rose to be the most powerful and wealthy state in the Malay archipelago, conquering the tin-producing region of Pahang on the Malayan Peninsula, putting it in direct conflict with the Portugese at Melaka. It soon controlled Sumatra and the surrounding islands but in 1629 a disastrous invasion by the Sultan's forces failed to oust the Portugese from their base. Soon after, the Dutch East India Company began to trade in the area from their base at Batavia in West Java, forming an alliance with the Sultan of Johore against their enemies, the Portugese and the Sultan of Aceh. Finally, in 1641 they succeeded in capturing Melaka, ending Portugese power in the East Indies for good.
[TAB]The economic importance of Malaya to Europe continued to grow in the 17thC. as the tea trade increased the demand for Malayan tin used to line tea chests and thousands of Arab and Chinese immigrants began to dominate economic activities in the town. English traders had always been present in the area but it was not until the mid-18thC. that British East India Company sought local bases for trade with China. Their first colonies were established when Penang was leased from the Sultan of Kedah in 1786, Dutch Melaka was occupied during the Napoleonic War and Singapore was acquired from the Sultan of Johore in 1819. The British then became the dominant economic and naval power in the region throught the 19th. and 20th. centuries.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PHILLIPPINES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The 7100 islands of the Philippines in the western Pacific Ocean were originally inhabited by a mixture of indigenous peoples who traded with the Malay archipelago from 700AD, adopting influences from Hinduism and Buddhism. There was no unifying state in the area though groups of islands were governed by various Rajahs who increasingly came under the influence of Arab traders and missionaries and they largely adopted Islam by the end of the 15thC.. The first European contact came in 1521, when the Spanish explorer, Ferdinand Magellan, arrived at Samar and Leyte and claimed the islands for Spain. Colonization began in 1565 when Miguel Lopez de Legazpi arrived from Mexico and founded the first European settlement on Cebu.
[TAB]In 1571 the Spanish occupied much of the Philippines and established Manila as the capital of the Spanish East Indies, naming their colony after King Philip II which was governed as a territory of the Vice-Royalty of New Spain from 1565 to 1821. The fragmented nature of the islands made them easy to occupy and political unification was achieved, with the exception of the Sultanate of Mindanao and remote highland villages in Luzon by the mid-17thC.. The Spanish introduced elements of Western civilization including the code of law, printing, silver coinage, the Gregorian calendar and Christianity, as well as food resources from Latin America like maize, pineapple, the potato, vanilla and chocolate.
[TAB]The Manilla galleons, which linked the Philippines with Acapulco, loaded spices, textiles, and fruit in return for silver bullion, arms and colonists from Mexico. The Spanish military fought various indigenous revolts and incursions from the Dutch and English as Jesuit missionaries converted most of the lowland population and established public schooling in the Spanish language. The Philipppines was never profitable as a colony during the early years of Spanish rule and a long war against the Dutch and its own Muslim inhabitants nearly bankrupted the colonial treasury, though later attempts at establishing a plantation economy based on rice, coffee, fruit and other foodstuffs brought relative prosperity by the 19thC..</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
