<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by XMLSPY 2004 Professional Ed. Release 2, Installed Multi + SMP for 3 users (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - RFCE Dawn of Man -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RHYES_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT</Tag>
		<English>The sun rises on the year %s1_year. The %s2_civ people are ready to settle down and found your first city.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, your people have vested absolute power in you, trusting that you can build a Civilization to stand the test of time!</English>
		<French>Le soleil se l&#232;ve sur l'an %s1_year. Les %s2_civ sont pr&#234;ts &#224; s'installer et &#224; fonder votre premi&#232;re ville.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, votre peuple vous a confi&#233; le pouvoir absolu et s'en remet &#224; vous pour b&#226;tir une civilisation qui r&#233;sistera &#224; l'&#233;preuve du temps !</French>
		<German>Die Sonne erhellt das Jahr %s1_year. Das %s2:3_civ Volk ist bereit, sich niederzulassen und Eure erste Stadt zu gr&#252;nden.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, Euer Volk hat Euch absolute Macht verliehen und vertraut darauf, dass Ihr eine Zivilisation errichtet, welche die Zeit &#252;berdauern wird!</German>
		<Italian>Il sole sorge nell'anno %s1_year. La popolazione %s2:2_civ &#232; infine pronta a stabilirsi e a fondare la tua prima citt&#224;.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, il tuo popolo ti ha conferito potere assoluto, credendo che tu possa sviluppare una civilt&#224; in grado di resistere alle prove del tempo!</Italian>
		<Spanish>El sol se alza en el a&#241;o %s1_year. Las gentes del %s2_civ est&#225;n listas para asentarse y fundar vuestra primera ciudad.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, vuestro pueblo os ha conferido poder absoluto, confiando en que pod&#225;is desarrollar una civilizaci&#243;n que supere los retos del tiempo.</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#209;&#238;&#235;&#237;&#246;&#229; &#226;&#238;&#241;&#245;&#238;&#228;&#232;&#242; &#226; %s1_year. %s2_civ &#235;&#254;&#228;&#232; &#227;&#238;&#242;&#238;&#226;&#251; &#231;&#224;&#241;&#229;&#235;&#232;&#242;&#252;&#241;&#255; &#232; &#238;&#241;&#237;&#238;&#226;&#224;&#242;&#252; &#226;&#224;&#248; &#239;&#229;&#240;&#226;&#251;&#233; &#227;&#238;&#240;&#238;&#228;.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, &#226;&#224;&#248;&#232; &#235;&#254;&#228;&#232; &#237;&#224;&#228;&#229;&#235;&#232;&#235;&#232; &#226;&#241;&#229;&#226;&#235;&#224;&#241;&#242;&#232;&#229;&#236; &#226;&#224;&#241;, &#228;&#238;&#226;&#229;&#240;&#232;&#226; &#242;&#238;, &#247;&#242;&#238; &#226;&#251; &#236;&#238;&#230;&#229;&#242;&#229; &#239;&#238;&#241;&#242;&#240;&#238;&#232;&#242;&#252; &#214;&#232;&#226;&#232;&#235;&#232;&#231;&#224;&#246;&#232;&#254;, &#247;&#242;&#238;&#225;&#251; &#226;&#251;&#228;&#229;&#240;&#230;&#224;&#242;&#252; &#232;&#241;&#239;&#251;&#242;&#224;&#237;&#232;&#229; &#226;&#240;&#229;&#236;&#229;&#237;&#229;&#236;!</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_SCREEN_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</English>
		<French>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</French>
		<German>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</German>
		<Italian>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</Italian>
		<Spanish>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</Spanish>
		<Russian>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</Russian>
	</TEXT>
		<!-- Civ Specific Dawn of Man -->
		<!-- DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_0 numbers are the iCivs.Consts.py -->
		<!-- 0 is Byzantium, 1 is France, 2 is Arabia, etc -->
	<TEXT> <!-- Byzantium -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_0</Tag>
		<English>After many glorious centuries under Rome, the great Constantine saw fit to split the mighty empire into two parts.[NEWLINE]It is the year 500 AD, the Western Roman Empire has fallen. While Rome will always have a place in your people's hearts, Constantinople is now the heart of the most glorious nation on Earth![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Justinian, you are now the sole ruler, THE Roman Emperor. Your nation is rich and strong, but be aware: huge riches attract many enemies, and some of the barbarians may be even stronger.[NEWLINE]Your people have faith that you can lead their mighty nation through the coming storm. Will you prevail, and lead the Byzantine Empire through another 1,000 years of glory?</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>E' l'anno 500 D.c. Dopo molti secoli sotto il dominio di Roma, Costantino ha deciso di dividere l'impero in due parit.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Mentre Roma avrà sempre un posto nei cuori dei tuoi sudditi, ora Costantinopoli è la città più potente del mondo![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Ora tu, Giustiniano, governi come Imperatore Romano. La tua nazione è forte, ma i barbari potrebbero esserlo di più. La tua gente crede che puoi condurre l'impero fuori dalla tempesta in arrivo. Vincerai e riuscirai a dare all'Impero Bizantino altri 1000 anni di gloria?</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- France -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_1</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 500 AD. As king of the Frankish people, you have lead their way in becoming the first barbarian tribe to set aside arianism and embrace catholicism, which will be the guiding principle in building a glorious civilization.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Your lands are vast and fertile, but the Burgundians in the Rhône valley will not always stay subdued, and the coasts may provide access to dangerous raiders from the north.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Arabia -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_2</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 635 AD. The prophet Muhammed, peace be upon him, accomplished what no one thought was possible - uniting the tribes of Arabia. You, Abu Bakr, has been chosen to succeed him as Caliph and expand the House of Islam.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]After a devastating war with Sassanid Persia and raging religious controversies between Chalcedonians and Monophysities, the land of the Byzantine Empire is ripe for conquest. You know you cannot miss this opportunity, and there will be many centuries to build up your forces before the western crusaders cast their gaze towards al-Quds.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Bulgaria -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_3</Tag>
		<English>After many years of civil war, your father had finally united your people in Great Bulgar, north of the Black Sea. Following his death, however, pushed by the Khazar hordes, you and your brothers had to divide the Bulgarians yet again and leave your old home in different directions.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is the year 680 AD. After years of travel through snow and heat, mountains and swamps, your followers and you finally reached the northern borders of the Eastern Roman Empire. Tired of traveling with no home, you gather your people for one last push, to cross the Danube river and to challenge the mighty Empire itself; to claim this lustful land as yours forever.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>Dopo molti anni di guerra civile, tuo padre ha infine riunito il tuo popolo nella Grande Bulgaria, a nord del Mar Nero. Dopo la sua morte, ovviamente, mandato via dalle orde dei Cazari, tu e i tuoi fratelli dovete dividere nuovamente i Bulgari e lasciare la vostra vecchia casa per andare in varie direzioni.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]E' l'anno 680AD. Dopo anni di vagabondaggi attraverso neve, montagne e paludi, tu e i tuoi compagni siete riusciti a raggiungere i confini settentrionali dell'Impero Romano d'Oriente. Stanchi di viaggiare senza fissa dimora, hai raccolto il tuo popolo per un ultima incursione, per attraversare il Danubio e sfidare il potente Impero; reclami le sue ricchissime terre come tue, per sempre.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Cordoba -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_4</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 711 AD. After the long struggle, the seemingly endless fleeing from the Sunni Muslims in the east, many thought your Umayyad line to be extinct.[NEWLINE]Not so! You, Abd-ar-Rahman III, lead your people to a new place which you call "Al-Andalus", where you and your people may finally find a new home[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]These new lands may easily be the richest you have ever seen, so with Allah's will you might be able to build a rich and happy Caliphate - full of poetry, art and religious toleration - which can even rival that of the prophet Muhammed![NEWLINE]You only have to worry about those fanatic Christians to the north...</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>E' l'anno 711AD. Puoi difficilmente credere alla tua fortuna. Gli stupidi seguaci del re Visigoto deposto Womba hanno appena invitato te e i tuoi compagni musulmani oltre lo stretto di Gibilterra. Dopo aver sconfitto il re Visigoto in carica, Rod, con un tradimento, è stato facile prendere il potere con l'aiuto degli Ebrei. Ora puoi costruire un ricco e felice Califfato, pieno di poesia, arte e tolleranza religiosa!</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Norse -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_5</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 780 AD. The winters in Scandinavia are harsh, but have bred a sturdy people and your longships are the envy of any sailor. Harald Hardrada, your loyal vikings are eager to show their strength to the whole world![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Far away Vinland, the coast of Normandy and the rich monastery of Lindisfarne beckons. Which path will you follow? Explore? Conquer? Trade? Maybe all three combined? The choice is yours, only one thing is certain: Be bold, be swift, be strong, and the halls of Valhalla will await you!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>E' l'anno 780 AD. Gli inverni in Scandinavia sono rigidi, ma hai addestrato un popolo robusto e le tue drakkar suscitano l'invidia di qualunque marinaio. Ora, la lontanissima Terranova, la costa della Normandia e il ricco monastero di Lindisfarne chiamano. Sii audace, sii veloce, sii forte, i portali del Vahlalla ti aspettano!</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Venice -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_6</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 810 AD. Fleeing the onslaught of the barbarian Lombards, your people and the remnants of the Byzantine Exarchate of Ravenna have settled on the inaccessible islands in the lagoon. The recent agreement between Charlemagne of the Franks and emperor Nicephorus in Constantinople means that you will be left alone for the time being. There has never been a better opportunity to build a rich trading empire that will dominate the seas!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Burgundy -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_7</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 843 AD. After your defeat at the hands of your brothers, you have signed the treaty of Verdun, accepting that the inheritance of the great empire that Charlemange built will be split into three, with you taking the middle part. Your exposed position - wedged between the powerful Frankish and German kingdoms - will require great diplomatic skills, but your knights should be the envy of all of Europe!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Germany -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_8</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 858 AD. The great Frankish inheritance have irrevocably been split into three, with the eastern part going to you. As the Byzantine Empress Irene rejected Charlemange's marriage proposal, you should instead build a Holy Roman Empire for yourself!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Kiev -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_9</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 880 AD. After the mighty walls of Constantinople hampered your attack in 866, you decided to settle down with some of your fellow Varangians. The land you just set yout foot on seems perfect for this.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The slavic people living here accept you as their leader, while your Swedish Vikings establish themselves as the local elite. Life is good, the land is fertile, you and your descendants will surely lead your new nation, the Kievan Rus into glory.[NEWLINE]If only you weren't having those dreams about reckless hordes raising in the east...</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Hungary -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_10</Tag>
		<English>It's the year 895 AD. While your glorious armies warred with the Byzantines and Bulgarians, the traitorous Pechenegs attacked your families and the remaining tribes in the homeland, Etelköz. Without defences they had to flee, and you know you cannot lead them back to their previous home.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]After taking your nation further to the west you finally reach the Carpathian-basin, which is everything your people ever needed: wealthy, fertile - and most importantly, easily defendable. Immediately falling in love with it, you claim these lands as yours forever.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]One thing has to be clear to you though: all the previous civilizations holding these lands before faded away throughout the centuries. You have to accept some of the more developed Western-European ways if you want to establish a long-living and successful nation in the middle of Europe.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Spain -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_11</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 910 AD. While the Moors never really held sway over your northern parts of Spain, the Caliphate of Cordoba under Abd-ar-Rahman III is stronger than ever. Christians are tolerated there, but lower taxes drive them towards conversion and eternal damnation. You must launch the Reconquista and liberate them before it is too late!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>E' l'anno 910AD. Sebbene i mori non domineranno mai davvero le zone settentrionali della Spagna, il Califfato di Cordoba governato da Abd-ar-Rahman III è più forte che mai. I Cristiani sono tollerati, ma la possibilità di pagare imposte più basse li spinge verso la conversione e l'eterna dannazione. Devi dare il via alla Reconquista e salvarli prima che sia troppo tardi!</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Poland -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_12</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 966 AD. Worried by the threat of a unified German Empire, you have accepted Christianity to protect your land against foreign aggression. With knowing your people are safe - at least for now - you can start to strengthen your position in Central Europe.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]If all your plans goes well, your nation will be a shining example of liberty and toleration for the rest of Europe - no inquisition will be needed, and the Szlactha will curb any autocratic tendencies!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Genoa -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_13</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1016 AD, together with the Pisans you have just defeated the muslim pirates. The need for security forces the republic you serve to assert an ever greater responsibility: the protection of the whole Italian peninsula.[NEWLINE]This is your chance to build a magnificent merchant republic! With enough resources, even the fabled cities of the eastern Mediterranean may lay at your hands.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>E' il 1016AD. Insieme con i Pisani, hai appena sconfitto i pirati musulmani, ma la necessità di maggiore sicurezzaobbliga la repubblica che servi a prendere sulle proprie spalle la responsabilità enorme di proteggere la Penisola Italiana. E' la tua occasione per costruire una splendida repubblica mercantile! Con una certa quantità di risorse, anche le favolose città del Mediterraneo orientale cadranno nelle tue mani.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- England -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_14</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1066 AD. The battlefield of Hastings lays quiet. Harold Godwinson is dead, but not before he took care of the Norwegians for you. Even though Scotland may be the source of trouble sometimes, the rich estates of England will fund the defense of your important possessions in France. No longer William the Bastard, henceforth you will be known as William the Conqueror!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Portugal -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_15</Tag>
		<English>Your small county of Portugal just decided to break the family ties with Leon and declared it's independence, creating the Kingdom of Portugal. It's 1139 AD, and you, Afonso Henriques, are the king of the newly formed country.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is time to strengthen your position by proceeding with the reconquista to the south, but you should also prepare for your ultimate goal: to expand beyond the Iberian Peninsula. Your position makes it ideal to claim the riches of North Africa and the Atlantic islands - and who knows, maybe even much further lands than those.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Lithuania -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_16</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1236 AD. Strange invaders - calling themselves Teutonic knights and worshipping a man on a cross - have disturbed the tranquility of the land. However, they are not invincible. You, Mindaugas, showed that they bleed and die, just like other men.[NEWLINE]It is high time to drive them out, as the religion of your ancestors is surely also the best for you. Make them proud!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Austria -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_17</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1282. In the last few decades your Habsburg dynasty was quickly gaining strength through the estates of the Holy Roman Empire. With recently acquiring the rich lands of Austria, you are much more powerful than you ever dreamt of. Still, your ambitions are forcing you to climb much higher, and who knows where will be the end?[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Navigate carefully through the intricate diplomacy of central Europe, and your dynasty will still stand proudly many hundreds of years from now!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>E' il 1282AD. Il Sacro Romano Impero ne ha avuto abbastanza degli eccessi degli Hohenstaufen. Federico II, detto Stupor Mundi, ha fatto venire molta voglia di stabilità e moderazione al popolo. La tua dinastia Asburgica gliele può dare. Naviga con attenzione attraverso l'intricata diplomazia dell'Europa Centrale, e la tua dinastia resisterà con orgoglio per centinaia di anni!</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Ottomans -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_18</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1359. Allah has truly shown his favour towards you. Firstly, the Black Death affected the Byzantines in the cities, but largely spared the countryside of the Turks. Secondly, the earthquake in Gallipoli 1354 levelled all the walls. The way to Europe is open, you need only to reach out and grasp it![NEWLINE]If you play your cards right, your Ottoman Empire will surely be unstoppable!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Moscow -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_19</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1380. The shadow of the Mongol Golden Horde has loomed over the land for more than a hundred years. With the people chafing under their oppression, fear has prevented effective resistance. All has changed now on the fields of Kulikovo, where you led your coalition to victory. The road ahead is long and arduous, but in the end, Mother Russia will prevail!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Sweden -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_20</Tag>
		<English>It is 1523 AD, a couple years after the outrages of the Stockholm Bloodbath, commited by the Danish king Kristian the Tyrant. You, Gustav Vasa, have lead a rebellion since to restore independence, succesfully uniting Sweden under a hereditary monarchy.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Now it's time to claim your rightful place as ruler over the Baltic sea. Contested in this by mighty rivals, success can only be achieved by superior military and tactics. One way is to break the ties with Rome and build a great nation based on the true Lutheran faith!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>E' il 1523 AD, un paio di anni dopo gli oltraggi del Bagno di sangue di Stoccolma, commessi dal re Danese Cristiano II il Tiranno. Tu, Gustavo Vasa, hai guidato una rivolta per ottenere l'indipendenza, e hai unito con successo la Svezia sotto una monarchia ereditaria.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Ora è il momento di reclamare il posto che ti spetta di diritto come dominatore del Mar Baltico. Essendo in contrasto con potenti rivali, il successo può essere ottenuto solo con la superiorità militare e tattica. Una strada da seguire può essere quella di spezzare i legami con Roma e costruire una grande nazione basata sul vero credo Luterano!</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!-- Dutch -->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT_21</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1581 AD. The Low Countries have been under control by the Spanish Empire for a long time. On July 22th this year, the Plakaat van Verlatinghe (Act of Abjuration) was signed by Philip II, making the Dutch officially independent. This could be the start of an empire that will become one of the most wealthiest civilizations in the world!</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>Es ist das Jahr 1581 n.Chr. Die Niederlande waren lange Zeit unter der Kontrolle des Spanischen Reiches. Am 22. Juli dieses Jahres wurde das Plakaat van Verlatinghe (Act of Abjuration) von Philip II unterzeichnet, wodurch Holland offiziell unabhängig wurde. Dies kann die Geburt eines Reiches sein, das die reichste Zivilisation der Welt werden kann!</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian>.</Russian>
	</TEXT>
		<!-- Civ Specific Dawn of Man -->
</Civ4GameText>
