<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by XMLSPY 2004 Professional Ed. Release 2, Installed Multi + SMP for 3 users (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Leaders -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHARLES_V</Tag>
		<English>Philip the Bold</English>
		<French>Philippe le Hardi</French>
		<German>Philipp der Kühne</German>
		<Italian>Filippo II di Borgogna</Italian>
		<Spanish>Felipe II de Borgo&#241;a</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHARLES_V_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Philip the Bold[\H1]
[BOLD]Duke of Burgundy[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] January 15, 1342 - April 27, 1404 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JOAN</Tag>
		<English>Joan of Arc</English>
		<French>Jeanne d'Arc</French>
		<German>Johanna von Orléans</German>
		<Italian>Giovanna d'Arco</Italian>
		<Spanish>Juana de Arco</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JOAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Joan of Arc[\H1]
[BOLD]National Herione of France[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.1412 - May 30, 1431 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABUBAKR</Tag>
		<English>Abu Bakr</English>
		<French>Abou Bakr</French>
		<German>Abu Bakr</German>
		<Italian>Ab&#252; Bakr</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ab&#252; Bakr</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABUBAKR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Abu Bakr as-Siddiq[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]The First of the Righteous Caliphs[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]573 - 634 CE[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]After Muhammad's death, previously dormant tensions between the Meccan immigrants, the Muhajirun, and the Medinan converts, the Ansar, threatened to break out and split the Ummah. The Ansar, the leaders of the tribes of Medina, met in a hall or house called saqifah, to discuss whom they would support as their new leader. When Abu Bakr was informed of the meeting, he, Umar, Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah and a few others rushed to prevent the Ansar from making a premature decision. Accounts of this meeting vary greatly. All agree that during the meeting Umar declared that Abu Bakr should be the new leader, and declared his allegiance to Abu Bakr, followed by Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah and Abu Bakr became the first Muslim caliph, who was given the title, Khalifa-tul-Rasool (Successor of messenger of Allah), a title only accepted by Sunni muslims.  After the meeting at saqifah, the Muslims who were not present were asked to submit to Abu Bakr, to give their pledge of allegiance. Most accounts agree that Ali (Muhammad's beloved companion, cousin and son-in-law) and his supporters initially refused to submit. After a period of time, the duration of which is disputed, the dissidents gave their bay'ah. Whether or not the process involved violence and intimidation, and whether or not Ali willingly swore allegiance to Abu Bakr have remained enduring controversies.</English>
		<French>[H1]Abu Bakr as-Siddiq[\H1]</French>
		<German>[H1]Abu Bakr as-Siddiqr[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Erster rechtgeleiteter Kalif[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 573-634</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Abu Bakr as-Siddiq[\H1].</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Abu Bakr as-Siddiq[\H1]</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SIMEON</Tag>
		<English>Simeon</English>
		<French>Sim&#233;on</French>
		<German>Simeon</German>
		<Italian>Simeone</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sime&#243;n</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SIMEON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Simeon I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Tsar of Bulgaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 864 - 927 AD [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Simeon was born in 864 as the third son of Knyaz Boris I. Simeon was born to a Christianized Bulgaria due to his father's reign. In his early years, Simeon learned the Greek language and received a theological education in Constantinople. Although Simeon's brother Vladimir was the designated heir of Boris, he was deposed after attempting to reintroduce paganism to Bulgaria and Simeon became king. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Under the Byzantine Emperor Leo VI, the Bulgarian marketplace was moved from Constantinople to Thessaloniki, where the Bulgarian merchants were heavily taxed. The merchants then required protection from Simeon, who invaded the Byzantine Empire in 894. However, the Bulgarian army was required back in the country after a Magyar invasion from the north. Later, the Magyars were convinced by the Byzantines to attack Bulgaria. Simeon, being unaware of this agreement, met another force of Byzantines from Italy. After agreeing to peace with the Byzantine commander, Simeon blocked off the Byzantine navy's route into the Danube. Simeon, after hearing of the Magyar attack, moved to confront them. The Magyars defeated Bulgaria and later pillaged its land, and Simeon agreed to peace with Byzantium in 895.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Now that the Byzantine threat was abolished, Simeon planned a campaign against the Magyars. Simeon defeated the Magyars and expanded Bulgarian territory. Simeon then defeated a Byzantine army after a dispute about Bulgarian prisoners in Thrace. The war ended and Byzantium was required to pay an annual tribute and cede lands to Bulgaria. However, Simeon often violated these treaties, conquering and attacking Byzantine territory on several occasions.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Leo VI's death paved the way for another Bulgarian invasion of Byzantium. Simeon was recognized as Emperor of the Bulgarians after negotiations with the Byzantines. In 917, the Byzantines planned a campaign against eh Bulgarians. In the Battle of Anchialos, one of the largest medieval battles in history, Simeon defeated the Byzantines. In order to cease Serbian unrest, Simeon removed the current Serbian ruler and replaced him with another, ensuring Bulgarian influence over Serbia.[PARAGRAPH: 1]After another government change in Constantinople, Simeon declared war on Byzantium to further assert his power. He captured several Byzantine cities and requested the help of the Arabs. However, the Arabs accepted peace with the Byzantines, thus ruining their alliance with Bulgaria. Simeon was forced to establish peace with Byzantium after the threat of a Serbian uprising, where he deposed the Serbian ruler. In 926, Simeon's troops invaded Croatia, but were defeated by the army of King Tomislav. In the last years of his life, Simeon prepared for another siege of Constantinople. On May 27, 927, Simeon died of heart failure in his palace in Preslav and was succeeded by his son Peter I.</English>
		<French>[H1]Sim&#233;on Ier[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Tsar de Bulgarie[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD] 864 - 927 ap. J.C.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Simeon a été soutenu dans 864 en tant que troisième fils de Knyaz Boris I. Simeon a été soutenu en Bulgarie christianisée due au règne de son père. En ses premières années, Simeon a appris la langue grecque et a reçu une éducation théologique à Constantinople. Bien que le frère Vladimir de Simeon ait été l'héritier indiqué de Boris, il a été déposé après avoir essayé de réintroduire le paganisme en Bulgarie et Simeon est allé bien au roi.[PARAGRAPH : 1]Sous le Lion bizantin d'empereur VI, le marché bulgare a été déplacé de Constantinople à Thessaloniki, où les négociants bulgares ont été fortement imposés. Les négociants ont alors eu besoin de la protection contre Simeon, qui a envahi l'empire bizantin dans 894. Cependant, l'armée bulgare a été priée en arrière dans le pays après une invasion magyare du nord. Plus tard, les Magyars ont été convaincus par le Byzantines d'attaquer la Bulgarie. Simeon, étant ignorant de cet accord, a rencontré une autre force de Byzantines d'Italie. Après avoir été d'accord sur la paix avec le commandant bizantin, Simeon bloqué outre de l'itinéraire de la marine bizantine dans le Danube. Simeon, après avoir entendu parler de l'attaque magyare, s'est déplacé pour les confronter. Par Magyars la Bulgarie défaite Simeon et plus tard pillé sa terre, et était d'accord sur la paix avec Byzance dans 895.[PARAGRAPH : 1]Maintenant que la menace bizantine a été supprimée, Simeon a projeté une campagne contre les Magyars. Simeon a défait les Magyars et a augmenté le territoire bulgare. Simeon a alors défait une armée bizantine après un conflit au sujet des prisonniers bulgares dans Thrace. La guerre finie et Byzance ont été exigées pour payer un hommage annuel et pour céder des terres en Bulgarie. Cependant, Simeon a souvent violé ces traités, conquérant et attaquant le territoire bizantin à plusieurs occasions.[PARAGRAPH : 1]Le Lion la mort de VI a préparé le terrain pour une autre invasion bulgare de Byzance. Simeon a été identifié comme empereur des Bulgares après des négociations avec le Byzantines. Dans 917, le bizantin a projeté une campagne contre hein des Bulgares. Dans la bataille d'Anchialos, une des plus grandes batailles médiévales dans l'histoire, Simeon a défait le Byzantines. Afin de cesser le malaise serbe, Simeon a enlevé la règle serbe courante et l'a remplacé avec des autres, assurant l'influence bulgare au-dessus de la Serbie.[PARAGRAPH : 1]Après qu'un autre changement de gouvernement à Constantinople, Simeon ait déclaré la guerre sur Byzance affirmer plus loin sa puissance. Il a capturé plusieurs villes bizantines et a demandé l'aide des Arabes. Cependant, les Arabes ont accepté la paix avec le Byzantines, de ce fait ruinant leur alliance avec la Bulgarie. Simeon a été forcé d'établir la paix avec Byzance après la menace d'un soulèvement serbe, où il a déposé le gouverneur serbe. Dans 926, les troupes de Simeon envahissent la Croatie, mais ont été défaites par l'armée du Roi Tomislav. En dernières années de sa vie, Simeon s'est préparé à un autre siège de Constantinople. Le 27 mai 927, Simeon mort de l'arrêt du coeur dans son palais dans Preslav et a été réussi par son fils Peter I.</French>
		<German>[H1]Simeon I.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Zar von Bulgarien[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 864 - 927 n. Chr. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Simeon wurde in 864 als der dritte Sohn von Knyaz Boris I. getragen. Simeon wurde zu einem Christianized Bulgarien wegen der Herrschaft seines Vaters getragen. In seinen frühen Jahren erlernte Simeon die griechische Sprache und empfing eine theological Ausbildung in Konstantinopolise. Obgleich Bruder Vladimir Simeons der gekennzeichnete Erbe von Boris war, wurde er abgesetzt, nachdem man versucht hatte, Heidentum nach Bulgarien wieder einzuführen und Simeon stand König.[PARAGRAPH: 1 Unter dem byzantinischen Kaiser-Löwen wurde VI, der bulgarische Markt von Konstantinopolise auf Thessaloniki verschoben, in dem die bulgarischen Kaufleute schwer besteuert wurden. Die Kaufleute benötigten dann Schutz vor Simeon, das das byzantinische Reich in 894 eindrang. Jedoch wurde die bulgarische Armee zurück im Land nach einer Magyarinvasion vom Norden angefordert. Später wurden die Magyars durch das Byzantines überzeugt, Bulgarien in Angriff zu nehmen. Simeon, seiend ahnungslos von dieser Vereinbarung, traf eine andere Kraft von Byzantines aus Italien. Nachdem dem Zustimmen Frieden mit dem byzantinischen Kommandanten, Simeon blockiert weg vom byzantinischen Weg der Marine in die Donau. Simeon, nachdem er von den Magyarangriff gehört hatte, bewog, um sie zu konfrontieren. Das Magyars besiegte Bulgarien und später geplündert seinem Land und Simeon stimmte Frieden mit Byzanz in 895 zu.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Nun da die byzantinische Drohung abgeschafft wurde, plante Simeon eine Kampagne gegen die Magyars. Simeon besiegte die Magyars und erweiterte bulgarische Gegend. Simeon besiegte dann eine byzantinische Armee nach einer Debatte über bulgarische Gefangene in Thrace. Der beendete Krieg und Byzanz wurden angefordert, einen jährlichen Tribut zu zahlen und Länder nach Bulgarien zu überlassen. Jedoch verletzte Simeon häufig diese Verträge und eroberte und nimmt byzantinische Gegend bei einigen Gelegenheiten in Angriff.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Löwe der Tod VI pflasterte die Weise für eine andere bulgarische Invasion von Byzanz. Simeon wurde als Kaiser der Bulgaren nach Vermittlungen mit dem Byzantines erkannt. In 917 plante das byzantinische eine Kampagne gegen wie Bulgaren. In der Schlacht von Anchialos, besiegte eine der größten mittelalterlichen Schlachten in der Geschichte, Simeon das Byzantines. Um serbische Ruhelosigkeit aufzuhören, entfernte Simeon die gegenwärtige serbische Lehre und ersetzte ihn mit anderen und stellte bulgarischen Einfluß über Serbien sicher.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Nachdem eine andere Regierung änderung in Konstantinopolise, Simeon Krieg auf Byzanz erklärte, seine Energie weiter zu erklären. Er nahm einige byzantinische Städte gefangen und bat um die Hilfe der Araber. Jedoch nahmen die Araber Frieden mit dem Byzantines an und so ruinierten ihr Bündnis mit Bulgarien. Simeon wurde gezwungen, Frieden mit Byzanz nach der Drohung eines serbischen Aufstiegs herzustellen, in dem er die serbische Lehre absetzte. In 926 dringen Truppen Simeons Kroatien ein, aber wurden von der Armee des Königs Tomislav besiegt. In den letzten Jahren seines Lebens, bereitete sich Simeon für eine andere Belagerung von Konstantinopolise vor. Am 27. Mai 927 wurde Simeon, das am Herzausfall in seinem Palast in Preslav gestorben wurde und von seinem Sohn Peter I. gefolgt.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Simeone I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Zar di Bulgaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD] 864 - 927 d.C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Simeon è stato sopportato in 864 come il terzo figlio di Knyaz Boris I. Simeon è stato sopportato ad un Christianized Bulgaria dovuto il regno del suo padre. Durante i suoi primi anni, Simeon ha imparato la lingua greca ed ha ricevuto una formazione theological a Constantinople. Anche se il fratello Vladimir del Simeon era l'erede indicato di Boris, deposed dopo avere tentato di rintrodurre il paganism in Bulgaria e Simeon ha stato bene al re.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Sotto il Leo Byzantine dell'imperatore VI, il mercato bulgaro è stato spostato da Constantinople verso Thessaloniki, dove i commercianti bulgari sono stati tassati pesante. I commercianti allora hanno richiesto la protezione da Simeon, che ha invaso l'impero Byzantine in 894. Tuttavia, l'esercito bulgaro è stato richiesto indietro nel paese dopo un'invasione del Magyar dal nord. Più successivamente, i Magyars sono stati convinti dal Byzantines attacare la Bulgaria. Simeon, essendo ignaro di questo accordo, ha venuto a contatto di un'altra forza di Byzantines dall'Italia. Dopo avere accosentitoe alla pace con il comandante Byzantine, Simeon ostruito fuori dell'itinerario del blu marino Byzantine nel Danubio. Simeon, dopo avere sentito parlare l'attacco del Magyar, si è mosso per confrontarlo. I Magyars hanno sconfitto la Bulgaria e più successivamente hanno saccheggiato la relativa terra e Simeon ha accosentito a pace con Byzantium in 895. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ora che la minaccia Byzantine si è abolita, Simeon ha progettato una campagna contro i Magyars. Simeon ha sconfitto i Magyars ed ha espanso il territorio bulgaro. Simeon allora ha sconfitto un esercito Byzantine dopo una disputa circa i prigionieri bulgari in Thrace. La guerra conclusa e Byzantium sono stati richiesti rendere tributo annuale e cedere le terre in Bulgaria. Tuttavia, Simeon ha violato spesso questi trattati, conquistanti ed attacanti il territorio Byzantine in parecchie occasioni.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Il Leo morte del VI ha aperto la strada per un'altra invasione bulgara di Byzantium. Simeon è stato riconosciuto come imperatore dei bulgari dopo le trattative con il Byzantines. In 917, il Byzantine ha progettato una campagna contro eh i bulgari. Nella battaglia di Anchialos, una di più grandi battaglie medioevali nella storia, Simeon ha sconfitto il Byzantines. Per cessare l'agitazione di Serbian, Simeon ha rimosso il righello corrente di Serbian e lo ha sostituito con un altro, accertando l'influenza bulgara sopra la Serbia.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Dopo che un altro cambiamento di governo a Constantinople, Simeon dichiari la guerra con Byzantium più ulteriormente di asserire la sua alimentazione. Ha bloccato parecchie città Byzantine ed ha chiesto l'aiuto degli arabi. Tuttavia, gli arabi hanno accettato la pace con il Byzantines, così rovinando la loro alleanza con la Bulgaria. Simeon è stato costretto a stabilire la pace con Byzantium dopo la minaccia di una rivolta di Serbian, in cui deposed il righello di Serbian. In 926, le truppe del Simeon invadono il Croatia, ma sono state sconfitte dall'esercito del re Tomislav. Durante gli anni scorsi della sua vita, Simeon si è preparato per un altro siege di Constantinople. Il 27 maggio 927, Simeon morto di guasto di cuore nel suo palazzo in Preslav ed è stato riuscito dal suo figlio Peter I.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Sime&#243;n I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Zar de Bulgaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD] 864 - 927 d. C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Simeon fue llevado en 864 como el tercer hijo de Knyaz Boris I. Simeon fue llevado a un Christianized Bulgaria debido al reinado de su padre. En sus años, Simeon aprendió la lengua griega y recibió una educación teológica en Constantinople. Aunque el hermano Vladimir de Simeon era el heredero señalado de Boris, lo depusieron después de procurar reintroducir paganism a Bulgaria y Simeon sintió bien al rey.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Debajo del Leo Byzantine del emperador VI, el mercado búlgaro fue movido desde Constantinople a Thessaloniki, donde gravaron a los comerciantes búlgaros pesadamente. Los comerciantes entonces requirieron la protección contra Simeon, que invadió el imperio Byzantine en 894. Sin embargo, requirieron al ejército búlgaro detrás en el país después de una invasión del Magyar del norte. Más adelante, se convenció a los Magyars por el Byzantines que atacaran Bulgaria. Simeon, siendo inconsciente de este acuerdo, resolvió otra fuerza de Byzantines de Italia. Después de convenir la paz con el comandante Byzantine, Simeon bloqueado de la ruta de la marina de guerra Byzantine en el Danubio. Simeon, después de oír hablar del ataque del Magyar, se movió para enfrentarlos. Los Magyars la Bulgaria derrotada Simeon y más adelante pillado su tierra, y convino la paz con Byzantium en 895.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Ahora que la amenaza Byzantine fue suprimida, Simeon planeó una campaña contra los Magyars. Simeon derrotó a Magyars y amplió el territorio búlgaro. Simeon entonces derrotó a ejército Byzantine después de un conflicto sobre presos búlgaros en Thrace. La guerra terminada y Byzantium fueron requeridos pagar un tributo anual y ceder tierras a Bulgaria. Sin embargo, Simeon violó a menudo estos tratados, conquistando y atacando el territorio Byzantine en varias ocasiones.[PARAGRAPH: 1]El Leo la muerte de VI pavimentó la manera para otra invasión búlgara de Byzantium. Simeon fue reconocido como emperador de los búlgaros después de negociaciones con el Byzantines. En 917, el Byzantine planeó una campaña contra eh búlgaros. En la batalla de Anchialos, una de las batallas medievales más grandes de la historia, Simeon derrotó el Byzantines. Para cesar malestar servio, Simeon quitó la regla servia actual y lo substituyó por otro, asegurando influencia búlgara sobre Serbia. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de que otro cambio del gobierno en Constantinople, Simeon declarara guerra en Byzantium afirmar más lejos su energía. Él capturó varias ciudades Byzantine y solicitó la ayuda de los árabes. Sin embargo, los árabes aceptaron paz con el Byzantines, así arruinando su alianza con Bulgaria. Simeon fue forzado establecer paz con Byzantium después de la amenaza de una sublevación servia, donde él depuso la regla servia. En 926, las tropas de Simeon invaden el Croatia, pero fueron derrotadas por el ejército de rey Tomislav. En los años pasados de su vida, Simeon se preparó para otro sitio de Constantinople. El 27 de mayo de 927, Simeon muerto de paro cardíaco en su palacio en Preslav y fue tenido éxito por su hijo Peter I.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABDARRAHMAN</Tag>
		<English>Abd-ar-Rahman III</English>
		<French>Abd al-Rahman III</French>
		<German>Abd ar-Rahman III.</German>
		<Italian>Abd al-Rahman III</Italian>
		<Spanish>Abderram&#225;n III</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABDARRAHMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Abd-ar-Rahman III[\H1]
[BOLD]Caliph of Cordoba[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 891 - 961 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	Abd-ar-Rahman III was born at 891, and became Caliph of Cordoba when he was twenty-two. During his reign, he successfully warred both the Fatimid Arabs and the Christian kingdoms at the North, having significant land gains (much of Central Iberia and part of Maghreb). In order to invade to North Africa, he reinforced the Cordoban fleet, turning it into a considerably strong power. Abd-ar-Rahman III was also noted for the tolerance shown to other religion faithfuls (Catholics and Jews). Moreover, he was a patron of science and arts. Specifically, his residence palace, the Medina Azahara, built at his reign, was modelled after the Ummayad Arab palace in Damascus, and he spent money to extend the library of Cordoba, turning the city in an important intellectual center. When, at 961, he died, he left the Caliphate of Cordoba at the colophon of its height.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Abd-ar-Rahman III.[\H1]
[BOLD]Kalif von Córdoba[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 891-961


	[BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD]
	Abd-ar-Rahman III. wurde 891 geboren, und wurde Kalif von Córdoba als er zweiundzwanzig Jahre alt war. Während seiner Regentschaft bekriegte er erfolgreich sowohl die fatimidischen Araber als auch die christlichen Königreiche im Norden und verzeichnete bedeutende Landgewinne (große Teile der Iberischen Halbinsel und ein Teil des Maghrebs). Um in Nordafrika einzufallen, verstärkte er die Cordobanische Flotte und machte es zu einer starken Macht. Abd-ar-Rahman III. war auch bekannt für die Toleranz anderen Religionsgläubigen (Katholiken und Juden) gegenüber. Zudem war er ein Schutzherr der Wissenschaft und Künste. Spezifisch wurde sein Palast, die Medina Azahara, gebaut während seiner Herrschaft, nach dem ummayadisch-arabischen Palast in Damaskus modelliert. Er gab Geld aus um die Bibliothek des Córdobas zu erweitern und machte die Stadt zu einem wichtigen intellektuellen Zentrum. Als er 961 starb, hinterließ er das Kalifat Córdoba auf dem Gipfel seiner Macht.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABUYUSUFYAQUB</Tag>
		<English>Abu Yaqub Yusuf</English>
		<French>Abu Yaqub Yusuf</French>
		<German>Abu Yaqub Yusuf I.</German>
		<Italian>Abu Yaqub Yusuf</Italian>
		<Spanish>Abu Yaqub Yusuf</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ABUYUSUFYAQUB_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Abu Yaqub Yusuf[\H1]
[BOLD]Second Almohad Amir[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1135 - July 29, 1184 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PHILIP_II</Tag>
		<English>Philip II</English>
		<French>Philippe II d'Espagne</French>
		<German>Philipp II.</German>
		<Italian>Filippo II di Spagna</Italian>
		<Spanish>Felipe II de España</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PHILIP_II_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Philip II[\H1]
[BOLD]King of Spain[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]May 21, 1527 - September 13, 1598


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	Philip II was King of Spain from 1556 until 1598; King of Naples from 1554 until 1598; king consort of England, as husband of Mary I, from 1554 to 1558; lord of the Seventeen Provinces from 1556 until 1581, holding various titles for the individual territories, such as duke or count; and King of Portugal and the Algarves as Philip I from 1580. He also ruled a vast empire in the Americas, including New Spain and Peru.
[TAB]Philip's policies were determined by a combination of Catholic fervour and dynastic self-interest. He found himself by default the chief defender of Catholic Europe, both against the Ottoman Turks and against the forces of the Protestant Reformation. He never relented from his war against heresy, preferring to fight on every front at whatever cost rather than countenance heterodoxy within his territories. These territories included his patrimony in the Netherlands, where the Protestant heresy had taken deep root. Following the Revolt of the Netherlands in 1568, Philip waged a long war for control of the Netherlands, which dragged in the English and the French and lasted for the rest of his life. In 1588, the Spanish armada was destroyed by a tempest off the southern cost of Ireland, thus thwarting his planned invasion of England. Concerned with the Muslim threat in the Mediterranean, Philip achieved a decisive victory against the Turks at the Lepanto in 1571, where the fleet of the Holy League was commanded by his illegitimate brother John of Austria. He also successfully secured his succession to the throne of Portugal in 1580.
[TAB]After basing himself in the Netherlands in the early years of his reign, Philip returned to the peninsula in 1559 and never left it again. Unlike his father, Charles V, Philip was thoroughly Spanish, a native speaker who chose to rule from Spain rather than to travel constantly around his states. Although sometimes described as an absolute monarch, Philip faced many constitutional constraints on his authority. Spain was not a single monarchy with one legal system but a federation of separate realms, each jealously guarding its own rights against those of the Crown of Castile. In practice, Philip often found his authority overruled by local assemblies, and his word was less authoritarian than British or French historians have always tried to characterize. The Kingdom of Aragon, where Philip was obliged to put down a rebellion in 1591–1592, was particularly unruly. He also grappled with the intractable problem of the large Morisco population in Spain, persuaded to convert to Christianity by his predecessors. In 1568, a Morisco Revolt broke out in the southern province of Granada in defiance of attempts to suppress Moorish customs, and Philip wisely decided the expulsion of the Moriscos from Granada and their dispersal to other provinces.
[TAB]Despite its immense dominions, Spain itself was an arid country with a sparse population that yielded a limited income to the crown. Philip faced major difficulties in raising taxes, the collection of which was largely farmed out to local lords. He was able to finance his military campaigns not only by taxing the local resources of his empire, but also the flow of income from the New World proved vital to his militant foreign policy. His exchequer several times was able to avoid bankruptcy. Philip's reign saw an extraordinary flourishing of cultural excellence in Spain, part of what is called the Golden Age, creating a lasting legacy in literature, music, and the visual arts.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Philipp II.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König von Spanien[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 21. Mai 1527 - 13. September 1598</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHRISTIAN_IV</Tag>
		<English>Christian IV</English>
		<French>Christian IV</French>
		<German>Christian IV.</German>
		<Italian>Christiano IV</Italian>
		<Spanish>Christi&#225;n IV</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHRISTIAN_IV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Christian IV[\H1]
[BOLD]King of Denmark and Norway[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] April 12, 1577 - February 28, 1648 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	King of Denmark and Norway (1588-1648), who led two unsuccessful wars against Sweden and brought disaster upon his country by leading it into the Thirty Years' War. He energetically promoted trade and shipping, left a national heritage of fine buildings, and won repute as a plucky, hard-drinking man of grim wit and great resource.
[TAB]Christian, the son of Frederick II of Denmark and Sophia of Mecklenburg, succeeded to the throne on the death of his father in 1588, but until his coronation in 1596 his country was governed by a regency of four members of the Rigsrad, the privy council, who also supervised his education. He was brought up as a Lutheran and studied Latin, French, Italian, and German as well as mathematics, navigation, drawing, military command, fencing, and dancing.
[TAB]After his coronation Christian succeeded in limiting the powers of the Rigsrad. He kept the most important offices vacant and surrounded himself with an entourage of aristocratic young officers and German officials drawn mainly from his dukedom of Holstein. The Rigsrad was opposed to a war against Sweden, but Christian threatened to declare war in his capacity as duke of Schleswig-Holstein, thus forcing the Rigsrad to sanction plans for a war (1611-13), with the aim of once more uniting Sweden with Denmark. Although Christian won the war, his victory remained essentially inconclusive.
[TAB]After the war Christian centred his efforts on the economic development of his kingdom; he founded new towns, particularly ports to strengthen defenses, enlarged the royal shipyards, and built beautiful buildings and castles in and around Copenhagen. When the Protestant cause in northern Germany was endangered, in 1624, Christian entered the Thirty Years' War, again in opposition to his councillors. His aims were to protect Danish interests in northern Germany, to stop the Swedish king from playing a role in European politics, and to take up the legacy of his father and grandfather as the leading member of the Lutheran Church and its defender against expanding Catholicism. In 1625 he began operations against the Catholic League in Germany led by Tilly, the Bavarian commander in chief, who defeated him at Lutter am Barenberge on Aug. 17, 1626. Tilly's and Wallenstein's troops next invaded and plundered Jutland, thus forcing Christian to form an alliance with the Swedish king Gustavus II Adolphus against the Catholics. After the Swedish-Danish army and fleet had forced Wallenstein to raise the siege of Stralsund, however, Christian severed the alliance and concluded a separate peace with the Holy Roman emperor at Lübeck in May 1629. Though Christian's prestige and even his faith in himself as a great captain were diminished, he had not lost any lands. After the war he continued to try to impede Swedish progress in northern Germany and to maintain his rights in the Baltic and the North Sea. He repeatedly raised the shipping tolls through The Sound into the Baltic in order to augment his income independently of the Rigsrad, but he thus alienated his old allies, the sea powers of England and the Netherlands. With the help of the Netherlands, Sweden attacked Denmark in December 1643; and, by the end of January 1644, Jutland was in their possession. Christian led the defense personally, blockading the Swedish ships for a time, and lost an eye in the naval battle of Kolberger Heide. Although this battle was inconclusive, the Danish fleet was later annihilated by the combined navies of Sweden and Holland, and Christian was compelled to conclude a humiliating peace in August 1645 that cost him possessions in the Baltic, Norway, and Scania. Throughout his reign the Rigsrad and the nobility had opposed his warlike policies and the ensuing strain on finances, and after this defeat even Christian's sons-in-law turned against him, forcing him to accept the increased power of the nobility. Though he died a bitter and broken man, Christian IV had ruled his kingdom for more than 50 years and is remembered as one of the most popular of Danish kings.
[TAB]Christian IV was inclined to occupy himself with every minor detail of his administration while losing sight of the larger problems. Not only did he personally lay down the lines of Denmark's mercantilistic policy, he even established the import duties; he started state-subsidized and privileged trading companies and manufacturies-all of them with no marked success-and insisted on auditing their accounts personally. He founded a new academy for young noblemen, provided funds for the students at the university and built them a new college, personally examined the knowledge of Latin and the religious orthodoxy of the clergymen due for promotion, made designs for new types of guns and tested them himself, inspected the contents of the new arsenals, acted as a judge even in minor cases, and tried out the new ships of his navy. Christian was a great builder and founder of cities. He founded the towns of Kristiania (now Oslo) and Kristiansand in Norway; Kristianstad and Kristianopel in what is now Sweden; Christianshavn in Denmark; and Glückstadt (which was to compete with Hamburg) in Holstein. Evidence of his unremitting industry are his more than 3,000 handwritten letters still preserved, written in an imaginative and vivid Danish prose and teeming with orders and questions on all subjects from the eternal laws of God to the brewing of stronger beer.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Christian IV.[\H1]
[BOLD]König von Dänemark und Norwegen[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 12. April 1577 - 28. Februar 1648</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HARALD_HARDRADA</Tag>
		<English>Harald Hardrada</English>
		<French>Harald Hardraada</French>
		<German>Harald Hardrada</German>
		<Italian>Harald Hardr&#229;de</Italian>
		<Spanish>Harald Hardrada</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HARALD_HARDRADA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Harald Hardrada[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Norway[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1015 - 1066[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Harald was the king of Norway from 1047 until 1066. He was also claimed to be the King of Denmark until 1062, often defeating King Sweyn's army and forcing him to leave the country. Many details of his life were chronicled in the Heimskringla. Among English-speakers, he is generally known as "Harold Hardrada" and remembered for his invasion of England in 1066. The death of Hardrada is often recorded as the end of the Viking era.  Born in 1015, Harald was the youngest of King Olaf II's three half-brothers born to Åsta Gudbrandsdatter. When Harald was 15, King Olaf was killed, trying to take the throne back from Canute the Great in 1030 at the Battle of Stiklestad. Harald took part in the battle and although wounded managed to escape before leaving Norway in exile. He was able to form a band of warriors out of men who had also been exiled as a result of Olaf's death. In 1031 Harald and his men reached the land of the Kievan Rus where they served the armies of Yaroslav I the Wise, the Grand Prince of the Rus. Harald is thought to have taken part in Grand Prince Yaroslav's campaign against the Poles and was appointed joint commander of defense forces.  Some years after Harald and his men had entered the land of the Rus, they packed up and left for the heart of the Byzantine Empire, the city of Constantinople. At the time, the Byzantine Empire was the wealthiest empire in Medieval Europe and the Near East. Harald and his men pledged themselves to the service of the armies of the empire. Harald's forces joined the elite mercenary unit known as the Varangian Guard. It was not long until Harald had proven himself in battle and gained the respect of his fellow guardsmen. Harald became the leader of the entire force and used this power to undertake his own missions. Harald's forces won a great many victories in North Africa, Syria and Sicily. Through ingenuity, he and his men were able to besiege and defeat a number of castles. A contemporary source reports such tactics as attaching burning resin to birds, setting the castle ablaze, digging a tunnel and feigning reluctance to fight, only to launch an attack at the most advantageous moment. Harald was able to build a large fortune in plunder from his victories. Harald took part in the suppression of the uprising of Peter Delyan, who attempted to restore the Bulgarian Empire in 1040-1041. In the Norse sagas, he is hailed as "Devastator of Bulgaria" and "Scourge of the Bulgarians" due to his participation, and is even thought to have cut down Peter Delyan in the field of battle. Some authors go as far as to theorize that Harald named Oslo after a Bulgarian he fell in love with, possibly named Slava or Oslava, though these theories are not known to have any actual base. According to Snorri Sturluson, who quoted the skald Stuf, Harald also made a raid into the country of Palestine and was able to conquer the city of Jerusalem: "Here it is told that this land came without fire and sword under Harald's command. He then went out to Jordan and bathed therein, according to the custom of other pilgrims. Harald gave great gifts to our Lord's graves, to the Holy Cross, and other holy relics in the land of Jerusalem. He also cleared the whole road all the way out to Jordan, by killing the robbers and other disturbers of the peace." This story would have made Harald the forerunner of the Crusaders, whose kingdom was a century old at the time of Snorri Sturluson - a claim of obvious prestige valued to later Norwegian monarchs. In 1225, when the saga was written, Snorri was championing the cause of the Norwegian monarchy and urging a unification of Iceland with Norway. Byzantine and Islamic sources of Harald's own time do not mention such a conquest of Jerusalem. It is, however, quite plausible that as a Christian Harald did go on pilgrimage to Jerusalem with his men, and that they did fight and defeat robbers infesting the pilgrims' route to the Holy City - without intending or effecting the city's conquest from the Muslims.  Using the wealth he had built during his service to the Byzantine Empire, Harald returned to Norway in 1045. He brought with him a number of men who served with him, and, as a result, became an immediate threat to the sitting king, Magnus I, who was the son of Olaf II and nephew of Harald and had returned from exile in 1035 to reclaim his father's throne after the death of Canute the Great. Sturluson writes, "When Harald returned to Constantinople from Jerusalem he longed to return to the North to his native land; and when he heard that Magnus Olafson, his brother's son, had become king both of Norway and Denmark, he gave up his command in the Greek service. And when the empress Zoe heard of this she became angry and raised an accusation against Harald that he had misapplied the property of the Greek emperor which he had received in the campaigns in which he was the commander of the army. On this account the Greek emperor had Harald made prisoner and carried to prison." Magnus I agreed to share power with his uncle Harald and the two became co-rulers. However, it was only a year later that Magnus would die. The circumstances surrounding his death were never truly explained. Speculation and increased tension between the two rulers led to the widespread belief that Magnus was killed by Harald so that he alone would control Norway.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DANDOLO</Tag>
		<English>Enrico Dandolo</English>
		<French>Enrico Dandolo</French>
		<German>Enrico Dandolo</German>
		<Italian>Enrico Dandolo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Enrico Dandolo</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DANDOLO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Enrico Dandolo[\H1]
[BOLD]Doge of Venice[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1107 - 1205 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	He is remembered primarily for his role in the Fourth Crusade which ultimately conquered Constantinople and ended (for a time) the Byzantine Empire.
	He became the 39th Doge of Venice on 1 January 1193, Dandolo was already old and blind, but deeply ambitious, and displayed tremendous mental and (for his age) physical strength. He was at least in his seventies when he became Doge. Some accounts say he was already 85 years old when he became Doge. His remarkable deeds over the next eleven years bring that age into question, however. Others have hypothesized that he may have been in his mid-70s when he became Venice's leader.In 1202 the knights of the Fourth Crusade were stranded in Venice, unable to pay for the ships they had commissioned after far fewer troops arrived than expected. Dandolo developed a plan that allowed the crusaders' debt to be suspended if they assisted the Venetians in restoring nearby Zara to Venetian control. At an emotional and rousing ceremony in San Marco di Venezia, Dandolo "took the cross" (committed himself to crusading) and was soon joined by thousands of other Venetians. Dandolo became an important leader of the crusade.
	Venice was the major financial backer of the Fourth Crusade, supplied the Crusaders' ships, and lent money to the Crusaders who became heavily indebted to Venice. Because of the crusaders' continued delays, provisions were also a problem for the enterprise.
	Although they were supposed to be sailing to Egypt, Dandolo convinced them to stop at Zara, a port city on the Adriatic that was claimed both by Venice and by the Kingdom of Hungary. Dandolo encouraged the crusaders to attack the city which had rebelled from Venice. A small number of Crusaders refused to help; but the others realized that the conquest of the rebel town and subsequent wintering there was the only way to hold the faltering crusade together. Zara was besieged and captured on November 15, 1202.
	Shortly afterwards, Alexius Angelus, son of the deposed Byzantine emperor Isaac II, arrived in that city. Dandolo agreed to go along with crusade leaders plan to place Alexius Angelus on the throne of the Byzantine Empire in return for Byzantine support of the crusade. This ultimately led to the conquest and sack of Constantinople on April 13, 1204, an event at which Dandolo was present and in which he played a directing role. The Catholic Crusaders then took permanent control of the Eastern Orthodox capital of Constantinople (or Byzantium) and established a Catholic state, the Latin Empire. Venice gained title to three-eighths of the Byzantine Empire as a result of the 4th Crusade. The Byzantine Empire was never again as powerful as it had been prior to the Fourth Crusade.</English>
		<French></French>
		<German>[H1]Enrico Dandolo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Doge von Venedig[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 1107 - 1205</German>
		<Italian/>
		<Spanish/>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LOUIS_XIV</Tag>
		<English>Louis XIV</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Louis XIV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Ludwig XIV.</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Luigi XIV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Luis XIV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LOUIS_XIV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Louis XIV [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of France [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1643-1715[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Born to King Louis XIII of France, Louis XIV was raised in the most opulent court in Europe. His every need was catered to, and he was given an excellent education, even if he was too lazy and spoiled to appreciate it. Louis XIII died when his son was five, and the regency passed to the queen mother, Anne of Austria. For the next 18 years she ruled France with the able assistance of Cardinal Mazarin, who may or may not have also been her lover, while Louis lived in pampered splendor. [PARAGRAPH:1]It was upon Mazarin's death in 1661 that the 22-year-old Louis XIV began to take an active interest in ruling his country. Much to everyone's surprise, he was good at it. First he gathered all of the power into his own hands, bypassing the old bureaucratic patronage system that Mazarin and his predecessors had used. He enticed the great nobles to his court, where he heaped upon them titles, honorary positions, and financial rewards, while at the same time undermining their actual power. In Louis' court, great noblemen - whose parents had fought for the crown of France itself - fought each other for the privilege of watching Louis shave. [PARAGRAPH:1]In person Louis was said to possess a great natural dignity and bearing. He was unfailingly courteous and usually honest, but he could dissimulate with the best of them when need-be. [PARAGRAPH:1]During his early reign Louis's court was known for its debauchery, and Louis himself had several mistresses. As his reign progressed, however, Louis became more devout, and he even married his last mistress (although in secret). Louis also became a patron of the arts, and literature and painting flourished under his rule. He built many great buildings and palaces, including the grand palace at Versailles. [PARAGRAPH:1]Despite France's wealth, the country remained virtually bankrupt, not only because it had to pay for all the gifts that Louis gave his favorites, but, more importantly, it had to pay for all the wars of conquest that Louis embarked upon. Although a sound and thoughtful ruler at home, Louis had a great thirst for international "glory" - which in his terms meant victory on the battlefield. He constantly fought his neighbors, often for the most trivial reasons, gaining little but glory from the wars. Though he left the army and navy in splendid condition, he left his country's treasury bare. [PARAGRAPH:1]Louis XIV died after ruling France for 72 years.</English>
		<French>[H1]Louis XIV [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi de France[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD] 1638 - 1715[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Fils du roi de France Louis XIII, Louis XIV est &#233;lev&#233; dans la cour la plus luxuriante d'Europe. Tous ses besoins sont satisfaits et il re&#231;oit une excellente &#233;ducation, m&#234;me s'il est trop paresseux et trop g&#226;t&#233; pour l'appr&#233;cier. Louis XIII meurt alors que son fils n'a que cinq ans et la r&#233;gence est confi&#233;e &#224; la reine-m&#232;re, Anne d'Autriche. Durant les 18 ann&#233;es suivantes, elle dirige la France avec l'aide du talentueux cardinal Mazarin, qui est peut-&#234;tre &#233;galement son amant, tandis que Louis est choy&#233; et vit dans la splendeur. [PARAGRAPH:1]C'est apr&#232;s la mort de Mazarin en 1661 que Louis XIV, alors &#226;g&#233; de 22 ans, commence &#224; manifester un vif int&#233;r&#234;t pour la gestion de son pays. A la surprise quasi g&#233;n&#233;rale, il se montre tr&#232;s comp&#233;tent. Il rassemble d'abord tous les pouvoirs entre ses mains, contournant le vieux syst&#232;me bureaucratique de patronage que Mazarin et ses pr&#233;d&#233;cesseurs utilisaient. Il attire les grands nobles &#224; sa cour et leur offre titres, fonctions honoraires et r&#233;compenses financi&#232;res tout en sapant leur pouvoir r&#233;el. A la cour de Louis XIV, les grands aristocrates, dont les parents avaient lutt&#233; pour la couronne de France, se battent pour avoir le privil&#232;ge de voir le roi se raser. [PARAGRAPH:1]On dit que Louis XIV poss&#232;de une grande dignit&#233; naturelle et une allure imposante. Il est &#233;ternellement courtois et g&#233;n&#233;ralement honn&#234;te, mais il peut dissimuler ces qualit&#233;s si le besoin s'en fait sentir. [PARAGRAPH:1]Au d&#233;but du r&#232;gne de Louis XIV, sa cour est c&#233;l&#232;bre pour sa d&#233;bauche, le roi lui-m&#234;me ayant plusieurs ma&#238;tresses. Au fil du temps, il gagne en d&#233;votion et &#233;pouse m&#234;me sa derni&#232;re ma&#238;tresse (secr&#232;tement toutefois). Louis devient &#233;galement m&#233;c&#232;ne, la litt&#233;rature et la peinture prosp&#232;rent sous son r&#232;gne. Il construit de nombreux b&#226;timents et ch&#226;teaux magnifiques, et notamment le grandiose ch&#226;teau de Versailles. [PARAGRAPH:1]Malgr&#233; la richesse de la France, le pays est au bord de la faillite, non seulement &#224; cause des cadeaux que Louis XIV offre &#224; ses favoris, mais aussi, et surtout, &#224; cause des guerres de conqu&#234;te dans lesquelles il s'est engag&#233;. La reconnaissance interne de sa gestion saine et r&#233;fl&#233;chie ne suffit pas &#224; Louis XIV, il recherche &#233;galement une "popularit&#233;" internationale qui passe par la gloire sur les champs de bataille. Il combat sans cesse ses voisins, souvent pour les raisons les plus insignifiantes, ces guerres ne lui apportant rien, si ce n'est la c&#233;l&#233;brit&#233;. Si &#224; sa mort, l'arm&#233;e et la marine sont dans un excellent &#233;tat, il l&#232;gue par ailleurs un pays sans aucune tr&#233;sorerie. [PARAGRAPH:1]Louis XIV meurt apr&#232;s avoir r&#233;gn&#233; pendant 72 ans sur la France.</French>
		<German>[H1]Ludwig XIV. [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]K&#246;nig von Frankreich [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte: [\BOLD] 1643-1715[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Ludwig XIV. war der Sohn K&#246;nig Ludwigs XIII. Der verw&#246;hnte Ludwig genoss eine hervorragende Ausbildung, wusste dies allerdings nicht zu sch&#228;tzen. Als Ludwig XIII. 1643 starb, wurde Ludwig als K&#246;nig inthronisiert. Bis zu seinem 13. Lebensjahr lebte er allerdings unter der Regentschaft seiner Mutter Anna von &#214;sterreich. Die tats&#228;chliche Macht &#252;bte in jener Zeit allerdings Kardinal Mazarin aus. Dieser bereitete Ludwig gezielt auf seine Rolle als Herrscher vor und beteiligte diesen Schritt f&#252;r Schritt an der Macht.[PARAGRAPH:1]Als Mazarin Anfang 1661 starb, war der inzwischen 22-j&#228;hrige K&#246;nig gut auf sein Amt vorbereitet und verk&#252;ndete dem Staatsrat, dass er fortan allein regieren werde. Auf diese Weise gelang es ihm, das noch unter Mazarin &#252;bliche b&#252;rokratische G&#252;nstlingssystem abzuschaffen. Den Adel &#252;berh&#228;ufte Ludwig mit Titeln, Ehrenposten und Geld, w&#228;hrend er dessen tats&#228;chliche Macht mehr und mehr untergrub. Fortan buhlten unz&#228;hlige Adlige, deren Eltern noch um die Krone gek&#228;mpft hatten, um die Gunst des jungen K&#246;nigs. [PARAGRAPH:1]Ludwig selbst war ein w&#252;rdevoller, h&#246;flicher und ehrlicher Monarch, der allerdings in der Lage war, selbst seine engsten Berater zu t&#228;uschen. [PARAGRAPH:1]Der junge K&#246;nig sch&#228;tzte Vergn&#252;gungen und hatte aufgrund seiner Anziehungskraft zahlreiche M&#228;tressen. Ludwig f&#246;rderte die K&#252;nste, um die K&#252;nstler des Landes zu beeinflussen und sie im Interesse seiner Politik zu instrumentalisieren. Auch die Errichtung zahlreicher Prachtbauten und Pal&#228;ste (Versailles) ist Ausdruck der k&#246;niglichen Selbstdarstellung. [PARAGRAPH:1]Als Ludwig im Jahr 1715 starb, hinterlie&#223; er das reichste K&#246;nigreich Europas, dessen staatliche Einnahmen die Steuern anderer L&#228;nder deutlich &#252;bertrafen. Ludwig wollte zeitlebens ein starker Herrscher sein und sehnte sich nach internationaler Anerkennung. Nicht zuletzt deshalb f&#252;hrte er zahlreiche Kriege und baute die franz&#246;sische Armee und seine Flotte aus. [PARAGRAPH:1]Ludwig XIV. war mit 72 Jahren Regentschaft der am l&#228;ngsten regierende Herrscher der Neuzeit.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Luigi XIV [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Francia [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vissuto nel: [\BOLD] 1643-1715[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Storia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Erede di re Luigi XIII di Francia, Luigi XIV crebbe nella pi&#249; ricca corte d'Europa. Ogni suo capriccio venne soddisfatto e la sua educazione fu eccellente, anche se era troppo pigro e viziato per apprezzarlo. Luigi XIII mor&#236; quando suo figlio aveva soltanto cinque anni e la reggenza pass&#242; in mano alla regina madre, Anna d'Austria. Per i 18 anni successivi, govern&#242; la Francia con l'abile assistenza del cardinale Mazarin, di cui era forse l'amante, mentre Luigi viveva tra il vizio e lo splendore.[PARAGRAPH:1]Alla morte di Mazarin, nel 1661, il ventiduenne Luigi XIV inizi&#242; a interessarsi al governo del proprio paese: con grande sorpresa di tutti, si rivel&#242; un abile governatore. Come prima cosa, riun&#236; tutto il potere nelle proprie mani, eliminando il vecchio sistema burocratico del patronato che Mazarin e i suoi predecessori avevano utilizzato, poi attir&#242; a corte i grandi nobili, dove avrebbe potuto ricoprirli di titoli, posizioni onorarie e ricompense finanziarie, erodendone allo stesso tempo il vero potere. Nella corte di Luigi, i grandi nobiluomini, i cui antenati in passato avevano lottato per la corona di Francia, ora lottavano per il privilegio di assistere alla rasatura di Luigi.[PARAGRAPH:1]Si dice che Luigi possedesse grande dignit&#224; e portamento naturali: era incredibilmente educato e solitamente onesto, ma poteva ingannare anche il pi&#249; attento osservatore, quando fosse stato necessario.[PARAGRAPH:1]All'inizio del suo regno, la corte di Luigi era famosa per la sua dissolutezza e Luigi stesso aveva diverse amanti. Con gli anni, tuttavia, Luigi divenne pi&#249; devoto e spos&#242; persino la sua ultima amante (sebbene in segreto). Luigi divenne inoltre un grande patrono delle arti, e letteratura e pittura fiorirono durante il suo governo. Costru&#236; sfarzosi edifici e palazzi, inclusa la sua reggia di Versailles.[PARAGRAPH:1]Nonostante la ricchezza della Francia, il paese rest&#242; praticamente in bancarotta, non solo perch&#233; doveva pagare per tutti i doni che Luigi distribuiva ai suoi favoriti, ma, soprattutto, poich&#233; doveva finanziare tutte le guerre di conquista intraprese da Luigi. Sebbene fosse un governatore serio e riflessivo a casa, Luigi aveva un grande desiderio di "gloria" internazionale, che per lui significava la vittoria sul campo di battaglia. Era sempre in lotta con i suoi vicini, spesso per le ragioni pi&#249; futili, nonostante questi scontri gli portassero soltanto la gloria. Al termine del suo regno, lasci&#242; l'esercito e la flotta navale in ottime condizioni, ma, al tempo stesso, prosciug&#242; la tesoreria nazionale.[PARAGRAPH:1]Luigi XIV mor&#236; dopo aver governato la Francia per 72 anni.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Luis XIV [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Francia [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;: [\BOLD] 1643-1715[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biograf&#237;a:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Hijo de Luis XIII de Francia, Luis XIV se cri&#243; en la corte m&#225;s opulenta de Europa. Todas sus necesidades estaban cubiertas y recibi&#243; una excelente educaci&#243;n, aunque fuera demasiado perezoso y mimado para apreciarla. Luis XIII muri&#243; cuando su hijo ten&#237;a cinco a&#241;os, y la regencia recay&#243; en las manos de la reina madre, Ana de Austria. Durante los dieciocho a&#241;os siguientes, Ana gobern&#243; con la ayuda del cardenal Mazarino (quien tal vez fuese tambi&#233;n su amante), mientras Luis viv&#237;a envuelto en un exceso de esplendor. [PARAGRAPH:1]Fue a la muerte de Mazarino, en 1661, cuando Luis XIV, a la saz&#243;n un joven de 22 a&#241;os, empez&#243; a interesarse m&#225;s activamente por el gobierno de su pa&#237;s. Para sorpresa generalizada, demostr&#243; grandes aptitudes. Para empezar, reuni&#243; todo el poder en sus propias manos, desmontando el anticuado sistema de patronazgo burocr&#225;tico empleado por Mazarino y sus predecesores. Reuni&#243; a todos los nobles importantes en su corte, donde los colm&#243; de t&#237;tulos, honores y recompensas econ&#243;micas, al mismo tiempo que minaba su poder real. En la corte de Luis, los grandes nobles, cuyos antecesores hab&#237;an luchado por la Corona de Francia, peleaban por el derecho a presenciar el afeitado del rey. [PARAGRAPH:1]Seg&#250;n parece, en persona Luis pose&#237;a gran dignidad y un porte regio. Siempre se mostraba cort&#233;s, y normalmente honesto, pero en caso necesario pod&#237;a ser tan sibilino como el que m&#225;s. [PARAGRAPH:1]Durante los primeros a&#241;os de su reinado, su corte se hizo famosa por su depravaci&#243;n, y el propio Luis tuvo varias amantes. Sin embargo, a medida que avanzaba el tiempo, la piedad del rey fue en aumento, e incluso lleg&#243; a casarse con su &#250;ltima amante (aunque en secreto).  Tambi&#233;n fue un mecenas de las artes, y bajo su reinado florecieron la literatura y la pintura. Construy&#243; muchos grandes edificios y palacios, incluido el enorme complejo palacial de Versalles. [PARAGRAPH:1]A pesar de la riqueza de Francia, el pa&#237;s se manten&#237;a virtualmente en estado de bancarrota, no solo porque hubiera que pagar los regalos que Luis hac&#237;a a sus favoritos, sino, y mucho m&#225;s importante, por la necesidad de costear las guerras de conquista en las que se embarcaba. Aunque desde el punto de vista interno era un gobernante razonable y sensato, Luis ten&#237;a una inagotable sed de "gloria" internacional... lo que, desde su punto de vista, significaba victorias en el campo de batalla. Constantemente se enfrentaba a sus vecinos, a menudo por las m&#225;s triviales de las razones sin que estas guerras proporcionaran gran cosa al pa&#237;s, aparte de gloria. Dej&#243; el ej&#233;rcito y la marina en magn&#237;ficas condiciones, pero a costa de agotar los cofres del reino. [PARAGRAPH:1]Luis XIV muri&#243; tras setenta y dos a&#241;os de reinado.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MEHMED</Tag>
		<English>Mehmed II</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Mehmet II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Mehmet II.</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Mehmet II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Mehmet II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MEHMED_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Mehmed II [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sultan of the Ottoman Empire [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1432 - 1481[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Mehmed II, also known as el-Fatih ("the Conqueror") was the sultan of the Ottoman Empire from 1451 - 1481 AD. He is best known for capturing the city of Constantinople, turning it into the new Ottoman capital and destroying the Byzantine Empire in the process. Mehmed was born in Edirne, which was then the capital of the Ottoman state, in 1432. He was fascinated by military matters from an early age; by the time that he reached maturity and ascended to the position of sultan (in 1451), Mehmed was prepared to begin the attack upon the city of Constantinople. [PARAGRAPH:2]During the thousand-year history of the Byzantine Empire, Constantinople had withstood sieges many times. It had only been captured once, by the Fourth Crusaders in 1204. But by the fifteenth century the Byzantine Empire was a battered shell of its former self: while it still held Constantinople, it retained only a few small territories outside the city's walls (mainly in Greece). [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmed began the siege by constructing a pair of fortresses on both sides of the straights surrounding the city, thus preventing reinforcement by sea. When Mehmed attacked in 1453, the Byzantines were horribly outnumbered: there were only 7000 defenders to meet an army of roughly 100,000 Turks. Help was not forthcoming from the West, which remained hostile to the Byzantines because of the split between the Catholic and Orthodox churches. [PARAGRAPH:2]Using enormous primitive cannon, the Ottomans battered the walls of Constantinople for weeks (although the rate of fire was so slow that the defenders were able to repair much of the damage as it took place). On May 29 Mehmed finally ordered an assault at a damaged section of the walls. The assault was successful, and the attackers succeeded in breaking into the city streets. The city's fate was sealed. The last Emperor, Constantine XI, died in battle, and the ancient empire was extinguished forever. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmed gave his soldiers a day to loot the city (which was a customary practice at the time), during which a large portion of the populace was slaughtered, raped, or enslaved. After his soldiers' greed and lust were sated, Mehmed made every effort to rebuild the city and repopulate it with Turks. (Despite this odious "ethnic cleansing" at the beginning of his reign, Mehmed generally treated his non-Islamic subjects well, granting them permission to practice their religion freely, as well as a great deal of local autonomy.) The Byzantine administration was largely preserved intact and was given the task of running the Ottoman Empire. [PARAGRAPH:2]Upon consolidating his control over Constantinople, Mehmed finished off the last remnants of the Byzantine Empire by conquering some small states in Greece and in 1461 he conquered the tiny Empire of Trebizond on the Black Sea. He then tried to extend his empire into Europe, but in 1462 he was defeated by Prince Vlad III (the real Count Dracula) of Wallachia, and at the Battle of Vaslui in 1475 he suffered a major loss to the Moldavian Prince Stefan. These defeats put an end to that campaign. However, Mehmed still had ambition - and plenty of it. [PARAGRAPH:2]Believing that his conquest of Rome made him the legitimate ruler of the late Roman Empire, at the end of his life Mehmed embarked on an ambitious but foolhardy campaign to reunite his divided empire. The campaign began well; the Ottomans invaded Italy, and in 1840 the city of Otranto was easily captured. However, a rebellion in Albania the same year threatened the Ottoman supply lines, forcing the Ottomans to divide their forces. The following year a large Christian army led by the pope pushed the Ottomans from Italy. Mehmed died in 1481, putting an end forever to his dream of recapturing the ancient glory of Rome. [PARAGRAPH:2]In large, history has judged Mehmed kindly. He is recognized for his military success and his strong rule, and later Ottoman sultans would seek to follow his example. Mehmed's conquest of Constantinople was one of the most important events in Western history, signifying the end of the medieval period. His attack upon Italy may have been foolish, but it ultimately did little to harm the young Ottoman Empire that was his legacy. [PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
		<French>[H1]Mehmet II [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sultan de l'Empire ottoman [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates: [\BOLD] 1432 - 1481[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Mehmet II, dit el-Fatih ("le Conqu&#233;rant") est le sultan de l'Empire ottoman entre 1451 et 1481 ap. J.-C. Il est surtout connu pour sa prise de la ville de Constantinople, la transformant en nouvelle capitale de l'Empire ottoman et d&#233;truisant parall&#232;lement l'Empire byzantin. Mehmet est n&#233; en 1432 &#224; Edirne, qui est alors la capitale de l'Etat ottoman. D&#232;s son plus jeune &#226;ge, il est fascin&#233; par les questions militaires et lorsqu'il atteint l'&#226;ge adulte et acc&#232;de &#224; la fonction de sultan, en 1451, Mehmet est pr&#234;t &#224; attaquer la ville de Constantinople. [PARAGRAPH:2]Au cours de l'histoire mill&#233;naire de l'Empire byzantin, Constantinople a r&#233;sist&#233; &#224; de nombreux si&#232;ges et n'a &#233;t&#233; prise qu'en 1204, lors de la quatri&#232;me croisade. Cependant, au XVe si&#232;cle, l'Empire byzantin n'est plus que l'ombre de lui-m&#234;me : s'il poss&#232;de encore Constantinople, il ne comporte plus que quelques petits territoires hors des murs de la ville, essentiellement en Gr&#232;ce. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet assi&#232;ge Constantinople en construisant deux forteresses sur les deux rives des d&#233;troits qui encerclent la ville, pour &#233;viter tout renfort par la mer. Lorsque Mehmet attaque en 1453, les Byzantins sont bien moins nombreux : on compte environ 7000 d&#233;fenseurs de la ville contre une arm&#233;e d'environ 100 000 Turcs. L'Occident n'est pas pr&#234;t &#224; apporter son aide car il reste hostile aux Byzantins en raison de la division entre les Eglises catholique et orthodoxe. [PARAGRAPH:2]A l'aide d'&#233;normes canons primaires, les Ottomans bombardent les murs de Constantinople pendant des semaines. La fr&#233;quence de feu est cependant si lente que les d&#233;fenseurs peuvent r&#233;parer la majorit&#233; des dommages subis. Le 29 mai, Mehmet donne finalement l'assaut sur une portion endommag&#233;e du mur et l'emporte, les attaquants parvenant &#224; gagner les rues de la ville. Le destin de la ville est scell&#233;. Le dernier empereur, Constantin XI, meurt au combat et l'ancien empire dispara&#238;t &#224; jamais. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet conc&#232;de une journ&#233;e &#224; ses soldats pour piller la ville, ce qui est une pratique courante &#224; cette &#233;poque. Une grande partie de la population est alors massacr&#233;e, viol&#233;e ou r&#233;duite &#224; l'esclavage. Une fois leur avidit&#233; et leur luxure assouvies, Mehmet s'efforce de reb&#226;tir la ville et de la repeupler de Turcs. Malgr&#233; cet odieux "nettoyage ethnique" au d&#233;but de son r&#232;gne, Mehmet traite en g&#233;n&#233;ral correctement ses sujets non-islamiques, les autorisant &#224; pratiquer leur religion librement et leur offrant une grande autonomie locale. L'administration byzantine est en grande partie maintenue et est charg&#233;e de g&#233;rer l'Empire ottoman. [PARAGRAPH:2]Pour renforcer son contr&#244;le sur Constantinople, Mehmet fait dispara&#238;tre les derniers vestiges de l'Empire byzantin en conqu&#233;rant quelques petits Etats en Gr&#232;ce et, en 1461, il s'empare du petit Empire de Tr&#233;bizonde sur la mer Noire. Il essaie ensuite d'&#233;tendre son empire en Europe mais en 1462, il est vaincu par le prince Vlad III de Valachie, l'authentique comte Dracula et lors de la bataille de Vaslui en 1475, il conna&#238;t une s&#233;v&#232;re d&#233;faite contre le prince moldave Stefan le Grand. Ces d&#233;faites mettent fin &#224; cette campagne. Cependant, Mehmet reste tr&#232;s ambitieux. [PARAGRAPH:2]Pensant que la conqu&#234;te de Rome ferait de lui le dirigeant l&#233;gitime du d&#233;funt Empire romain, &#224; la fin de sa vie, Mehmet s'engage dans une campagne ambitieuse et t&#233;m&#233;raire pour r&#233;unir l'empire divis&#233;. La campagne commence bien : les Ottomans envahissent l'Italie et, en 1840, ils s'emparent facilement de la ville d'Otrante. Cependant, la m&#234;me ann&#233;e, une r&#233;bellion en Albanie menace les voies de ravitaillement et oblige les Ottomans &#224; diviser leurs forces. L'ann&#233;e suivante, une importante arm&#233;e chr&#233;tienne men&#233;e par le pape expulse les Ottomans d'Italie. Mehmet meurt en 1481, enterrant &#224; jamais son r&#234;ve de recr&#233;er la gloire antique de Rome. [PARAGRAPH:2]De mani&#232;re g&#233;n&#233;rale, Mehmet a &#233;t&#233; appr&#233;ci&#233;. Il est reconnu pour ses succ&#232;s militaires et sa gestion s&#233;v&#232;re ; il servira ult&#233;rieurement de mod&#232;le aux sultans ottomans. La prise de Constantinople par Mehmet constitue l'un des &#233;v&#233;nements les plus importants de l'histoire occidentale, mettant fin &#224; la p&#233;riode m&#233;di&#233;vale. Ses attaques en Italie peuvent para&#238;tre ridicules mais elles n'ont finalement que peu affaibli le jeune Empire ottoman qui constituait son h&#233;ritage. [PARAGRAPH:2]</French>
		<German>[H1]Mehmet II [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sultan des Osmanenreiches [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte: [\BOLD] 1432 - 1481[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Mehmet II., der den Beinamen el-Fatih (der Eroberer) trug, war von 1451 bis 1481 nach Christus Sultan des Osmanenreiches. Berühmt wurde er vor allem durch die Einnahme der Stadt Konstantinopel, die er zur Hauptstadt des Osmanischen Reiches machte, und die anschließende Zerschlagung des Byzantinische Reiches. Mehmet wurde 1432 in Edirne geboren, der damaligen Hauptstadt der Osmanen. Die Kriegskunst hatte ihn schon in jungen Jahren fasziniert und als er als Erwachsener zum Sultan aufstieg (1451), war er bereits gut darauf vorbereitet, den Angriff auf Konstantinopel anzuführen. [PARAGRAPH:2]Im Laufe der tausendjährigen Geschichte des Byzantinischen Reiches hatte Konstantinopel zahlreichen Belagerungsangriffen standgehalten. Nur ein einziges Mal wurde die Stadt tatsächlich eingenommen, und zwar 1204 durch die Kreuzfahrer des Vierten Kreuzzugs. Im 15. Jahrhundert war das Byzantinische Reich jedoch nur noch ein Schatten seiner Selbst: Konstantinopel konnte zwar noch gehalten werden, aber außerhalb der Stadtmauern gab es nur noch wenige kleine Gebiete (hauptsächlich Griechenland), die unter byzantinischer Kontrolle standen. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet begann die Belagerung, indem er zwei Festungen auf beiden Seiten der Ebenen um die Stadt errichtete und so verhinderte, dass auf dem Seeweg Verstärkung eintreffen konnte. Als Mehmet im Jahr 1453 angriff, waren die Byzantiner deutlich in der Unterzahl: Lediglich 7.000 Defensiveinheiten standen einer Armee von etwa 100.000 Türken gegenüber. Aus dem Westen war keine Unterstützung zu erwarten, weil die dortigen Länder aufgrund der Teilung der katholischen und orthodoxen Kirchen feindlich blieben. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mithilfe einer gigantischen primitiven Kanone nahmen die Osmanen wochenlang die Stadtmauern von Konstantinopel unter Beschuss (allerdings waren die Abstände zwischen den einzelnen Schüssen so groß, dass die Verteidiger den entstandenen Schaden in der Zwischenzeit bereits repariert hatten). Am 29. Mai befahl Mehmet schließlich einen Sturmangriff auf einen beschädigten Bereich der Mauer. Dieser Angriff verlief erfolgreich und die Belagerer konnten sich tatsächlich Zugang zur Stadt verschaffen. Damit war das Schicksal Konstantinopels besiegelt. Der letzte byzantinische Kaiser, Konstantin XI., starb während der Schlacht und das altehrwürdige Reich war für immer ausgelöscht. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet gab seinen Soldaten einen Tag Zeit, um die Stadt zu plündern (das war zur damaligen Zeit so üblich), währenddessen ein großer Teil der Bevölkerung getötet, vergewaltigt oder versklavt wurde. Nachdem seine Soldaten ihre Habgier und Wollust befriedigt hatten, setzte Mehmet alles daran, die Stadt wieder aufzubauen und mit Türken zu bevölkern. (Trotz der abscheulichen "ethnischen Säuberung", die Mehmet zu Beginn seiner Regentschaft durchführte, behandelte er auch seine nicht islamischen Untertanen relativ gut, indem er ihnen gestattete, ihren Glauben ungehindert zu praktizieren und ihnen auch ein hohes Maß an Autonomie zugestand.) Die byzantinische Verwaltungsstruktur blieb größtenteils intakt und hatte nun die Aufgabe, das Osmanenreich aufrechtzuerhalten. [PARAGRAPH:2]Nachdem er seine Vorherrschaft über Konstantinopel gefestigt hatte, vernichtete Mehmet auch die letzten Überreste des Byzantinischen Reiches, indem er zunächst einige kleinere Gebiete in Griechenland und 1461 das winzige Kaiserreich Trapezunt am Schwarzen Meer eroberte. Danach versuchte er, sein Reich nach Europa auszudehnen, wurde aber 1462 von Prinz Vlad III. (dem echten Graf Dracula) in der Wallachei besiegt und erlitt auch 1475 in der Schlacht von Vaslui im Kampf gegen den moldawischen Prinzen Stefan den Großen erhebliche Verluste. Diese Niederlagen setzten seinem Feldzug in dieser Region zwar ein Ende, dessen ungeachtet verfolgte Mehmet aber weiterhin große Ziele - und nicht wenige davon. [PARAGRAPH:2]Da er der festen Überzeugung war, durch die Eroberung Roms zum rechtmäßigen Herrscher des Römischen Reiches aufsteigen zu können, begann Mehmet kurz vor seinem Tod noch einen weiteren ehrgeizigen, aber auch tollkühnen Feldzug, der sein geteiltes Reich einen sollte. Zunächst begann alles gut: Die Osmanen fielen in Italien ein und eroberten 1480 ohne größere Probleme die Stadt Otranto. Allerdings gefährdete eine Rebellion in Albanien im selben Jahr den Nachschub der Osmanen, so dass diese gezwungen waren, ihre Truppen aufzuteilen. Und im darauf folgenden Jahr wurden die Osmanen von einer großen päpstlichen Armee aus Italien vertrieben. Mit Mehmets Tod im Jahr 1481 endete auch sein Traum von der Wiedergeburt des alten Glanzes des Römischen Reiches. [PARAGRAPH:2]Aufgrund seiner Leistungen hat Mehmet seinen Platz in der Geschichte durchaus verdient: Seine militärischen Erfolge und seine geradlinige Regentschaft dienten als Vorbild für viele spätere osmanische Sultane. Darüber hinaus zählt die Eroberung Konstantinopels durch Mehmet II. zu den wichtigsten Ereignissen der westlichen Geschichtsschreibung und kennzeichnete das Ende des Mittelalters. Sein Angriff auf Italien mag dagegen eher dumm gewesen sein, andererseits fügte er dem jungen Osmanischen Reich, das Mehmets Vermächtnis war, aber auch kaum nennenswerten Schaden zu. [PARAGRAPH:2]</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Mehmet II [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sultano dell'Impero ottomano [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vissuto nel: [\BOLD] 1432 - 1481[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Storia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Mehmet II, anche noto come el-Fatih (&quot;il Conquistatore&quot;) fu sultano dell'Impero ottomano tra il 1451 e il 1481 d.C. Egli è famoso soprattutto per aver conquistato Costantinopoli, facendola diventare la capitale del suo impero e ponendo fine a quello bizantino. Mehmet nacque a Edirne, l'allora capitale dello stato ottomano, nel 1432. Sin da piccolo era affascinato dalle questioni militari e quando raggiunse l'età adulta e salì al trono di sultano (1451), Mehmet era pronto a sferrare l'attacco nel cuore di Bisanzio. [PARAGRAPH:2]Nel corso della storia millenaria dell'Impero bizantino, Costantinopoli aveva resistito a più di un assedio. Era stata conquistata solo una volta, durante la quarta crociata, nel 1204. Ma nel quindicesimo secolo l'Impero bizantino era solo l'ombra di quel ch'era stato in passato: oltre a Costantinopoli comprendeva pochi altri territori, per lo più in Grecia. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet iniziò l'assedio costruendo due fortezze ai lati delle pianure che circondavano la città, impedendo così l'arrivo di rinforzi dal mare. Quando sferrò l'attacco, nel 1453, i Bizantini erano in terribile inferiorità numerica: soltanto 7.000 difensori contro circa 100.000 Turchi. Né potevano sperare in aiuti da occidente, che era loro rimasto ostile per via dello scisma tra la chiesa cattolica e quella ortodossa. [PARAGRAPH:2]Usando degli enormi cannoni primitivi, gli Ottomani colpirono per settimane le mura di Costantinopoli (anche se la frequenza dei colpi era tanto bassa da permettere la riparazione dei danni tra un colpo e l'altro). Il 29 maggio Mehmet ordinò infine l'assalto contro una sezione danneggiata delle mura. L'assalto andò a buon fine e gli invasori si riversarono per le strade della città. Il destino di Costantinopoli era segnato. L'ultimo imperatore, Costantino XI, morì in battaglia e il suo antico impero venne cancellato per sempre. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet concesse ai suoi soldati un giorno per saccheggiare la città (pratica comune del tempo), nel corso del quale buona parte della popolazione venne massacrata, violentata o resa schiava. Quando l'avidità e la bramosia delle sue truppe si fu sedata, Mehmet compì ogni sforzo per ricostruire la città e ripopolarla di Turchi. Nonostante questo odioso atto di pulizia etnica all'inizio del suo regno, Mehmet trattò poi bene i suoi sudditi non islamici, concedendo libertà di religione e larga autonomia alle comunità locali. L'amministrazione bizantina venne preservata quasi per intero affinché gestisse l'Impero ottomano. [PARAGRAPH:2]Dopo aver consolidato il proprio controllo su Costantinopoli, Mehmet cancellò l'Impero bizantino conquistando alcuni staterelli in Grecia e (1461) il piccolo Impero di Trebisonda sul Mar Nero. Egli cercò poi di espandersi in Europa, ma nel 1462 fu sconfitto dal principe Vlad III (il vero conte Dracula) di Valacchia e nella battaglia di Vaslui del 1475 fu pesantemente sconfitto dal principe moldavo Stefan. Mehmet decise perciò di concludere questa campagna, ma la sua ambizione non era ancora stata placata del tutto. [PARAGRAPH:2]Credendo che la conquista di Roma l'avrebbe reso il legittimo sovrano dell'antico Impero romano, negli ultimi anni della sua vita Mehmet si imbarcò in una ambiziosa quanto temeraria campagna per riunire l'impero diviso. La campagna partì bene; gli Ottomani invasero l'Italia e nel 1480 conquistarono facilmente Otranto. Una ribellione in Albania nello stesso anno minacciò tuttavia le linee di rifornimento all'esercito, costringendo gli Ottomani a dividersi su due fronti. L'anno successivo una grande armata cristiana guidata dal Papa respinse gli Ottomani fuori dall'Italia. Mehmet morì nel 1481, senza aver realizzato il suo sogno di ripristinare l'antica gloria di Roma. [PARAGRAPH:2]Nel complesso, la storia giudica Mehmet favorevolmente. A lui vengono riconosciuti numerosi successi militari e una guida sicura, tanto da essere preso a esempio dai sultani suoi successori. La sua conquista di Costantinopoli fu uno degli eventi più importanti della storia dell'occidente, che tradizionalmente segna la fine del periodo medievale. La sua invasione dell'Italia potrebbe sembrare un atto sciocco, ma non ebbe gravi ripercussioni sull'Impero ottomano che aveva contribuito a forgiare. [PARAGRAPH:2]</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Mehmet II [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sultán del Imperio Otomano [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;: [\BOLD] 1432 - 1481[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biograf&#237;a:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Mehmet II, conocido tambi&#233;n como el-Fatih (&quot;el Conquistador&quot;), fue sultán del Imperio Otomano entre 1451 y 1481 d. C. Su logro más famoso es haber conquistado la ciudad de Constantinopla y haberla convertido en la nueva capital otomana, además de destruir al Imperio Bizantino en el proceso. Mehmet nació en Edirne, capital por entonces del estado otomano, en 1432. Las cuestiones militares lo fascinaron desde muy temprana edad y así, cuando ascendió al trono de sultán (en 1451), estaba preparado para emprender el ataque contra la ciudad de Constantinopla. [PARAGRAPH:2]A lo largo de sus mil años de historia, Constantinopla había soportado numerosos asedios. Solo había sido capturada en una ocasión, durante la Cuarta Cruzada (1204). Pero, en el siglo XV, el Imperio Bizantino no era más que una sombra de su pasada gloria; aunque aún conservaba Constantinopla, más allá de las murallas solo poseía algunos pequeños territorios. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet inició el asedio construyendo un par de fortalezas a ambos lados de los estrechos que rodean la ciudad, para de este modo impedir que recibiera refuerzos por mar. Cuando inició el ataque, los bizantinos se enfrentaron a una inferioridad num&#233;rica espantosa. Solo había siete mil defensores para hacer frente a un ej&#233;rcito de aproximadamente cien mil turcos. Y, además, no cabía esperar ayuda desde el oeste, que seguía siendo hostil a los bizantinos a causa de la separación entre las iglesias católica y ortodoxa. [PARAGRAPH:2]Usando unos enormes cañones primitivos, los otomanos bombardearon durante semanas las murallas de la ciudad (aunque la cadencia de fuego era tan limitada que los defensores pudieron reparar gran parte del daño a medida que se producía). Por fin, el 29 de mayo, Mehmet ordenó un ataque contra una sección dañada de la muralla. El asalto se saldó con &#233;xito y los atacantes lograron llegar a las calles de la ciudad. El destino de Constantinopla estaba sellado. El último emperador, Constantino XI, murió en combate, y su antiquísimo imperio se extinguió con &#233;l. [PARAGRAPH:2]Mehmet dio a sus soldados un día para saquear la ciudad (una práctica muy normal en la &#233;poca), durante el que gran parte de la población fue asesinada, violada o esclavizada. Saciada la codicia y la lujuria de sus soldados, Mehmet hizo todo lo posible por reconstruir la ciudad y repoblarla con turcos. A pesar de esta odiosa &quot;limpieza &#233;tnica&quot; con la que inició su reinado, en general Mehmet trató bien a sus súbditos no islámicos y les concedió permiso para practicar su religión libremente, además de concederles gran autonomía. La administración bizantina quedó en gran parte intacta y recibió la misión de gobernar el Imperio Otomano. [PARAGRAPH:2]Tras consolidar su control de Constantinopla, Mehmet acabó con los últimos vestigios del Imperio Bizantino con la conquista de los pequeños estados de Grecia y, en 1461, del imperio de Trebisonda, en el mar Negro. A continuación trató de extender su imperio hacia Europa, pero fue derrotado por el príncipe Vlad III (el conde Drácula histórico) de Valaquia en 1462 y, más tarde, en 1475, sufrió un importante rev&#233;s frente al príncipe moldavo Stefan. Estas derrotas pusieron punto final a esta campaña. Sin embargo, Mehmet seguía teniendo ambiciones, y muchas. [PARAGRAPH:2]Creyendo que la conquista de Roma lo convertiría en el legítimo señor del Imperio Romano, al final de su vida se embarcó en una ambiciosa pero absurda campaña para reunificar el imperio dividido. La campaña tuvo un buen comienzo: los otomanos invadieron Italia y, en 1480, la ciudad de Otranto fue capturada con facilidad.  Sin embargo, una rebelión en Albania sucedida el mismo año amenazó sus líneas de abastecimiento y obligó a los otomanos a dividir sus fuerzas. Al año siguiente, un nutrido ej&#233;rcito dirigido por el Papa los expulsó de Italia. Mehmet murió en 1481 y con &#233;l se perdió para siempre el sueño de reconquistar la ancestral gloria de Roma. [PARAGRAPH:2]En conjunto, la historia ha deparado a Mehmet un juicio favorable. Se le reconoce su &#233;xito como militar y su firmeza como gobernante, y los posteriores sultanes otomanos lo tomarían como ejemplo. La conquista de Constantinopla por Mehmet fue uno de los acontecimientos más importantes de la historia del mundo occidental, y representa el final de la era medieval. Puede que su ataque a Italia fuera absurdo, pero al fin y al cabo no hizo apenas daño al joven Imperio Otomano, que sería su legado. [PARAGRAPH:2]</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_YAROSLAV</Tag>
		<English>Yaroslav</English>
		<French>Iaroslav</French>
		<German>Jaroslaw</German>
		<Italian>Jaroslav</Italian>
		<Spanish>Yaroslav</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_YAROSLAV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Yaroslav I the Wise[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Grand Prince of Kievan Rus[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.988 - 1054


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Jaroslaw I der Weise[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Großfürst der Kiewer Rus[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 988 - 1054</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MATTHIAS</Tag>
		<English>Matthias Corvinus</English>
		<French>Matthias Corvin</French>
		<German>Matthias Corvinus</German>
		<Italian>Mattia Corvino</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mat&#237;as Corvino</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MATTHIAS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Matthias Corvinus[\H1]
[BOLD]King of Hungary[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] February 23, 1443 - April 6, 1490


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
[TAB]Matthias Corvinus was born in Kolozsvar, Transylvania, and was the second son of John Hunyadi. After the death of Matthias's father, there was a struggle between Hungary's various barons and its Habsburg King. The gentry and the people of Pest finally came out in support of Matthias as king, while most barons also agreed to support him.
[TAB]On January 20, 1458, Matthias was elected king by the Diet. At this time, he was the hostage of the king of Bohemia who released under the condition of marrying his daughter. Matthias was finally crowned after several wars with Bohemia and the new Emperor Frederick III gave him the Holy Crown. Only the age of 15, Matthias began his reign by building public health, education, and a new legal system. Matthias was also a fan of art and culture, as many artists were present in his court. [TAB]Matthias gained independence by dividing the barons and raising a large royal army. At this time, Hungary reached its greatest territorial extent of the era. Matthias was victorious in several campaigns against the Ottoman Empire by raising the Kingdom of Hungary to be a world power. After that, Matthias was intent in conquering large parts of the Holy Roman Empire. By the end of his reign, he was in control of places such as Moravia, Silesia, Lusatia, half of Austria, and Vienna.
[TAB]Although Vlad III Dracula, Prince of Wallachia, had many successes against the Ottoman Empire, Matthias imprisoned him after a disagreement between the two rulers. Hungary decided to help Dracula in his fight of the threatening Ottomans, but he was assassinated. This was a major blow to the position of Hungary. In 1467, a conflict arose between Matthias and the Moldavian Prince Stephen III, after he became worn out by Hungary's policies and their presence at Kilia. A revenge lead by Stephen leads to the defeat of Matthias at the Battle of Baia. Matthias died in 1490 in Vienna, Austria, and his empire collapsed after his death because of the fact that his son was not accepted as king.</English>
		<French>[H1]Matthias Corvin[\H1]
[NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi de Hongrie[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD] 23 F&#233;vrier 1443 - 6 Avril 1490


	[BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD]
	Matthias Corvin est n&#233; en Kolozsvar, Transylvanie, qui &#233;tait le deuxième fils de Jean Hunyadi. Après la mort du père de Mathias, il y avait une lutte entre les diff&#233;rents barons de la Hongrie et de ses Habsbourg Roi. La noblesse et le peuple de Pest enfin venue à l'appui de Matthias comme roi, tandis que la plupart des barons &#233;galement accept&#233; de le soutenir.
[TAB]Le 20 janvier 1458, Matthias a &#233;t&#233; &#233;lu roi par la Diète. À ce moment, il &#233;tait l'otage du roi de Boehme qui relâch&#233; à la condition de marier sa fille. Matthias a finalement &#233;t&#233; couronn&#233; après plusieurs guerres avec la Bohême et le nouvel empereur Fr&#233;d&#233;ric III lui a donn&#233; la Sainte Couronne. Seul l'âge de 15, Matthias a commenc&#233; son règne par la construction de sant&#233; publique, d'&#233;ducation, et d'un nouveau système juridique. Matthias a &#233;galement &#233;t&#233; un fan de l'art et la culture, comme de nombreux artistes &#233;taient pr&#233;sents dans sa cour.
[TAB]&#233;lever une grande arm&#233;e royale. À cette &#233;poque, la Hongrie a atteint sa plus grande &#233;tendue territoriale de l'&#233;poque. Matthias a &#233;t&#233; victorieuse dans plusieurs campagnes contre l'Empire ottoman en &#233;levant le royaume de la Hongrie d'être une puissance mondiale. Après cela, Matthias &#233;tait r&#233;solu à conqu&#233;rir une grande partie du Saint Empire romain germanique. À la fin de son règne, il &#233;tait dans le contrôle des lieux tels que la Moravie, Sil&#233;sie, Lusace, la moiti&#233; de l'Autriche, et à Vienne.
[TAB]Bien que Vlad III Dracula, le Prince de la Valachie, de nombreux succès contre l'Empire ottoman, Matthias lui emprisonn&#233; après un d&#233;saccord entre les deux dirigeants. La Hongrie a d&#233;cid&#233; d'aider Dracula dans son combat de la menace Ottomans, mais a &#233;t&#233; assassin&#233;. Ce fut un grand coup port&#233; à la position de la Hongrie. En 1467, un conflit a &#233;clat&#233; entre Matthias et le Prince moldave &#201;tienne III, après avoir us&#233; il est devenu par la Hongrie de la politique et de leur pr&#233;sence à Kilia. Une vengeance dirig&#233; par Stephen conduit à la d&#233;faite de Matthias à la bataille de Baia. Matthias est mort en 1490 à Vienne, Autriche, et son empire s'est effondr&#233; après sa mort en raison du fait que son fils n'a pas &#233;t&#233; accept&#233; comme roi.</French>
		<German>[H1]Matthias Corvinus[\H1]
[BOLD]K&#246;nig von Ungarn, "Matthias der Gerechte"[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 23. Februar 1443 - 6. April 1490


	[BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD]
	Matthias Corvinus wurde in Kolozsv&#225;r (dt. Klausenburg), Siebenb&#252;rgen, als zweiter Sohn J&#225;nos Hunyadis geboren. Nach dem Tod seines Vaters, brach ein innenpolitischer Kampf zwischen dem ungarischen Adel und dem habsburger K&#246;nig von Ungarn aus. Die Bev&#246;lkerung von Pest sowie der Gro&#223;teil des Adels unterst&#252;tzten Matthias als K&#246;nig.
[TAB]Am 20. Januar 1458 wurde Matthias durch den Reichstag zum K&#246;nig gew&#228;hlt. Zu diesem Zeitpunkt war er Gefangener des K&#246;nigs von B&#246;hmen, der ihn unter der Bedingung frei lie&#223;, dass er seine Tochter heiratet. Nach mehreren Kriegen mit B&#246;hmen wurde Matthias schlie&#223;lich zum K&#246;nig Ungarns gekr&#246;nt, die Heilige Krone empfing er vom neuen Kaiser, Friedrich III. Schon im Alter von 15 Jahren begann Matthias seine Herrschaft durch den Aufbau eines Gesundheits- und Bildungswesens und die Einf&#252;hrung einer neuen Rechtssystems. Matthias war auch ein F&#246;rderer von Kunst und Kultur, was auch viele K&#252;nstler an seinem Hof zog.
[TAB]Matthias erreichte seine Unabh&#228;ngigkeit vom Adel indem er diesen spaltete und eine k&#246;nigliche Armee ("fekete sereg", schwarze Armee) aufstellte. Unter seiner Regentschaft erreichte Ungarn seine gr&#246;&#223;te territoriale Ausdehnung. Matthias f&#252;hrte mehrere erfolgreiche Feldz&#252;gen gegen das Osmanische Reich und machte Ungarn damit zur Weltmacht. Danach entschloss sich Matthias gro&#223;e Teile des Heiligen R&#246;mischen Reiches zu erobern. Zum Ende seiner Regierungszeit kontrollierte Ungarn unter anderem M&#228;hren, Schlesien, die Lausitz, halb &#214;sterreich und Wien.
[TAB]Obwohl sein Vasall Vlad III Dracula, F&#252;rst der Walachei, viele Erfolge gegen das Osmanische Reich feierte, lie&#223; Matthias ihn nach einem Streit in den Kerker werfen. Schlie&#223;lich entschloss sich Ungarn aber dazu Dracula in seinem Kampf gegen die Osmanen zu unterst&#252;tzen. Als dieser einem Anschlag zum Opfer fiel, schw&#228;chte dies die Position Ungarns erheblich. 1467 entbrannte ein Konflikt zwischen Matthias und dem moldawischen Prinzen Stefan, nachdem dieser der Politik Ungarns und dessen Pr&#228;senz in Kilia &#252;berdr&#252;ssig wurde. Stefan schlug das ungarische Heer in der Schlacht von Baia und startete einen erfolgreichen Gegenangriff. Sp&#228;ter normalisierten sich die diplomatischen Beziehungen wieder. Matthias starb 1490 unerwartet in Wien, sein Reich zerbrach nach seinem Tod da sein unehelicher Sohn als K&#246;nig nicht akzeptiert wurde.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Mattia Corvino[\H1]
[BOLD]Re d'Ungheria[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Vissuto tra il:[\BOLD] 23 febbraio 1443 - 6 aprile 1490


	[BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD]
	Mattia Corvino nacque in Transilvania, nella cittadina di Kolozsv&#225;r (in italiano antico: Claudiopoli), ed era il secondo figlio del generale e nobile ungherese J&#225;nos Hunyadi. Dopo la morte del re d'Ungheria Ladislao VI scoppi&#242; un conflitto fra i vari baroni ungheresi e la corona Asburgo per la successione al trono. La piccola nobilt&#224; ed il popolo di Pest alla fine decisero di supportaere Mattia; altrettanto fece la maggior parte dei baroni.
[TAB]Il 20 gennaio 1458 Mattia fu eletto re dalla Dieta. In quel periodo egli era ostaggio del re di Boemia, che, per rilasciarlo, impose come condizione che Mattia sposasse sua figlia. Mattia venne perci&#242; incoronato solo dopo una serie di guerre contro la Boemia; il nuovo imperatore asburgo Federico III gli don&#242; la Corona Sacra, simbolo della monarchia ungherese. A soli 15 anni Mattia si impegn&#242; a migliorare la salute pubblica, l'educazione e a redigere un nuovo sistema di leggi. Mattia fu inoltre un appassionato d'arte e della cultura in genere, cosicch&#233; grazie al suo mecenatismo la sua corte fu sempre frequentata da ogni sorta di artisti.
[TAB]Mattia riusc&#236; a restare indipendente dall'influenza dei baroni grazie alla diplomazia (divise i baroni e li mise l'uno contro l'altro) ma anche grazie al potere militare; riusc&#236; infatti ad organizzare una grande armata reale comandata da persone fidate. Sotto Mattia, l'Ungheria raggiunse la massima estensione territoriale della sua storia. Grazie alle vittorie ottenute in alcune campagne contro l'Impero Ottomano, il Regno d'Ungheria divenne una potenza di rango mondiale. Sull'altro confineo, l'obiettivo di Mattia fu di conquistare la maggior parte possibile di territorio del Sacro Romano Impero. Verso la fine del suo regno, egli controllava Moravia, Slesia, Lusatia, met&#224; dell'Austria e Vienna.[TAB]Sebbene Vlad III Dracula, principe di Valacchia, avesse ottenuto parecchie vittorie contro l'Impero Ottomano, Mattia, in un primo momento suo alleato, nel 1462 lo improgion&#242; dopo un disaccordo. Durante il suo periodo di cattivit&#224;, Vlad III riottenne la fiducia di Mattia che lo liber&#242; nel 1474 impegnandolo nella riconquista della Valacchia, ricaduta nel frattempo in mano ottomana, a nome del Regno d'Ungheria. Vlad III riusc&#236; nell'impresa ma la sua fu una vittoria di Pirro, dato che un rinnovato esercito ottomano lo sconfisse e lo uccise. Questa fu una grave perdita per la posizione dell'Ungheria. Nel 1467, un nuovo conflitto scoppi&#242; tra Mattia ed il principe di Moldavia Stefano III, dopo che quest'ultimo era stato danneggiato dalle scelte politiche ungheresi e a causa della presenza di questi nella citt&#224; di Kiliya (nell'odierna Ucraina). Stefano III riusc&#236; a battere Mattia nella battaglia di Baia. Mattia mor&#236; nel 1490 a Vienna, in Austria, e dopo la sua morte il suo impero collass&#242; soprattuto perch&#233; che suo figlio non fu accettato come re.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Mat&#237;as Corvino[\H1]
[BOLD]Rey de Hungr&#237;a[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD] 23 de Febrero de 1443 1 6 de Abril de 1490


	[BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD]
	Matthias Corvinus naci&#243; en Kolozsvar, Transilvania, que fue el segundo hijo de Juan Hunyadi. Despu&#233;s de la muerte del padre de Mat&#237;as, hubo una lucha entre los diferentes barones de Hungr&#237;a y su Habsburg Rey. La aristocracia y el pueblo de las plagas y finalmente sali&#243; en apoyo de Matthias como rey, mientras que la mayor&#237;a de los barones tambi&#233;n estuvo de acuerdo en apoyo de &#233;l. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El 20 de Enero, 1458, Mat&#237;as fue elegido rey por la Dieta. En este momento, &#233;l era el reh&#233;n del rey de Boehme que liberados con la condici&#243;n de casarse con su hija. Matthias finalmente fue coronado despu&#233;s de varias guerras con Bohemia y el nuevo emperador Federico III le dio la Santa Corona. S&#243;lo la edad de 15, Matthias comenz&#243; su reinado mediante la construcci&#243;n de la salud p&#250;blica, la educaci&#243;n, y un nuevo sistema jur&#237;dico. Matthias tambi&#233;n es un ventilador del arte y la cultura, como muchos artistas estuvieron presentes en su corte.
[TAB]Matthias accedi&#243; a la independencia dividiendo la recaudaci&#243;n de los barones y un gran ej&#233;rcito real. En este momento, Hungr&#237;a alcanz&#243; su m&#225;xima extensi&#243;n territorial de la &#233;poca. Matthias fue victorioso en varias campañas contra el Imperio Otomano por elevar el Reino de Hungr&#237;a a ser una potencia mundial. Despu&#233;s de eso, Matthias intenci&#243;n era conquistar gran parte del Sacro Imperio Romano. Al final de su reinado, fue en el control de lugares como Moravia, Silesia, Lusacia, la mitad de Austria, y Viena.
[TAB]Aunque Vlad III Dr&#225;cula, pr&#237;ncipe de Valaquia, hab&#237;a muchos &#233;xitos contra el Imperio Otomano, Matthias lo encarcelaron despu&#233;s de un desacuerdo entre los dos gobernantes. Hungr&#237;a decidi&#243; ayudar a Dr&#225;cula en su lucha de la amenazando otomanos, pero fue asesinado. Esto fue un gran golpe a la posici&#243;n de Hungr&#237;a. En 1467, surge un conflicto entre Matthias y el moldavo Stephen Prince III, despu&#233;s de que &#233;l se convirti&#243; en llevarse a cabo por las pol&#237;ticas de Hungr&#237;a y su presencia en Kilia. A la venganza conducir por Stephen conduce a la derrota de Matthias en la Batalla de Baia. Matthias muri&#243; en 1490 en Viena, Austria, y su imperio se derrumb&#243; despu&#233;s de su muerte por el hecho de que su hijo no fue aceptado como rey.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_STEPHEN</Tag>
		<English>Istvan I</English>
		<French>&#201;tienne Ier</French>
		<German>Stephan I.</German>
		<Italian>Stefano I</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esteban I</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_STEPHEN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Saint Stephen I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]First Christian King of Hungary[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 969 - August 15, 1038[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]King Stephen the Great or St. Stephen of Hungary (Szent Istv&#225;n in Hungarian, &#138;tefan in Slovak) was the first king of Hungary. His father was the Magyar chieftain Geza: his mother was Sarolt (Polish: Adelajda) from the Polish dynasty of the Piasts, and Stephen was given the name Vajk (meaning hero) at birth. Born a pagan in the town of Esztergom, Vajk was baptized, as a precondition of accepting the crown from Rome, at age 10 by Saint Adalbert of Prague, and given the baptismal name Stephen (in honor of the original early Christian Saint Stephen), protector of the church at Passau).[PARAGRAPH:2]He was married in 995 to Gizella of Bavaria (though some sources give other years for the marriage), the daughter of Henry II the Wrangler, and his wife Gisela of Burgundy. Stephen and Gizella had at least three children; we know the names of the sons Imre (Henry or Emeric) and Ott&#243; (Otto) and the daughter Hedvig (Hedwig). All of Stephen's children apparently predeceased him and left no descendants to claim the throne upon his death, so that the crown had to be contended for by his nephews and cousins.[PARAGRAPH:2]Between 995 and 997, Stephen (under the name "Vajk") was the prince of Nitra (a Slovak Christian center and the capital of the Nitrian principality in present day south-western Slovakia) and was living in Nitra together with his wife.[PARAGRAPH:2]After battling and defeating the pagan nobles who opposed him (including his uncle, a powerful warlord named Kopp&#225;ny), Stephen became the Sovereign of Magyars in Transdanubia in 997 and till 1006 managed to successfully unite virtually all the Magyar clans. The victory over Kopp&#225;ny was achieved also thanks to the substantial material and military assistance from the Slovak Christian noblemen Poznan and Hunt. According to Hungarian tradition, Pope Silvester II sent a magnificent jeweled gold crown to Stephen (which became the symbol of Hungary under the name of the Holy Crown) along with an apostolic cross and a letter of blessing in the beginning of January, 1001 to officially recognize him as a Christian king of Europe.[PARAGRAPH:2]Stephen divided Hungary into 40-50 counties, and continued the work of his father Geza by applying the decimal organizational system of his ancestors and setting up ten dioceses in Hungary, ordering every ten villages to erect one church and maintain a priest. He founded the cathedrals of Sz&#233;kesfeh&#233;rv&#225;r and Esztergom, the Nunnery of Veszpr&#233;m, the Benedictine Abbey of Pannonhalma, and the Monastery of Saint Peter and Paul in obuda. Inside the abbeys and monasteries, schools were established and they became important centers of culture. Saint Astricus served as Stephen's advisor, and Stephen also had Saint Gerard Sagredo as the tutor for his son Saint Emeric (Imre).[PARAGRAPH:2]Stephen discouraged pagan customs and strengthened Christianity with various laws, including ending the use of the old Hun-Magyar runic alphabet and making Latin the official language of the royal court. Stephen gave generously to the churches, personally visited them often, and supervised their construction. He often disguised himself as a peasant whenever he traveled, and freely gave money to any poor people he met (in one account, Stephen was beaten and robbed by a group of beggars to whom he was giving alms, but he forgave them and spared their lives).[PARAGRAPH:2]He intended to retire to a life of holy contemplation and hand the kingdom over to his only surviving son Imre, but in 1031 Imre was wounded in a hunting accident and died.[PARAGRAPH:2]Stephen mourned a very long time over the loss of his favorite son Imre, which took a great toll on his health. He eventually recovered, but he never regained his original vitality. Having no children left, he could not find anyone among his remaining relatives who was able to rule the country competently and willing to maintain the Christian faith of the nation. Unable to choose an heir, King Stephen died at Sz&#233;kesfeh&#233;rv&#225;r (a city he built in central Hungary) on the Feast of the Assumption, and was buried there. Both his nobles and his subjects were said to have mourned for 3 straight years afterwards.[PARAGRAPH:2]Shortly after his death, healing miracles were said to have occurred at his tomb. Stephen was canonized by the Vatican as Saint Stephen of Hungary in 1083. Catholics venerate him as the patron saint of: Hungary, kings, the death of children, masons, stonecutters, and bricklayers. His feast is on September 2, but in Hungary his chief festival is observed on August 20, the day on which his sacred relics were transferred to the city of Buda; this day is a public holiday in Hungary.[PARAGRAPH:2]His crown, known as the Holy Crown, is currently (since 2000) enshrined in the Hungarian Parliament building, in Budapest.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Stephan I. der Heilige[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Erster K&#246;nig von Ungarn[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 969 - 1038[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Szent Istv&#225;n (in Deutschland auch als Stephan I. der Heilige bekannt, geb. 969 bei  Esztergom, gest. 15.08.1038) aus dem Geschlecht der &#193;rp&#225;den war der erste K&#246;nig Ungarns und ist heute der Nationalheilige des Landes. Er christianisierte die heidnischen Magyaren. Sein Gedenktag ist der 20. August, der in Ungarn Nationalfeiertag ist. Die r&#246;misch-katholische Kirche gedenkt dieses Heiligen am 16. August.Zusammen mit seinem Vater G&#233;za wurde Istv&#225;n 985 von Adalbert von Prag getauft. W&#228;hrend der Gro&#223;f&#252;rst G&#233;za trotz der Taufe im Grunde Heide blieb, erhielt Istv&#225;n eine christliche Erziehung. Diese wurde noch verst&#228;rkt durch die Verheiratung Istv&#225;ns mit der bayrischen Herzogstochter Gisela. Zudem festigte die Hochzeit das B&#252;ndnis Ungarns mit den bayerischen F&#252;rsten, die noch 991 einen Feldzug gegen die Ungarn gef&#252;hrt hatten, und besiegelte die Bindung der Ungarn an die Westkirche. Als Istv&#225;n 997 die Nachfolge seines Vaters als Gro&#223;f&#252;rst antrat, war er vermutlich Christ aus &#220;berzeugung. Am Anfang seiner Herrschaft musste er sich zun&#228;chst gegen seinen Vetter Kopp&#225;ny durchsetzen, der selbst den Anspruch auf den F&#252;rstenstuhl erhob.Die K&#246;nigskr&#246;nung Istv&#225;ns im Jahre 1000 durch einen p&#228;pstlichen Gesandten am 17. August 1000 in Esztergom war verbunden mit der Installierung dieser Landeskirche und vermutlich auch mit der Schenkung des K&#246;nigreichs Ungarn an den Papst, der es darauf als Lehen an Istv&#225;n zur&#252;ck gab. Dieser Schritt, analog zur Schaffung des K&#246;nigreichs Polen, sollte die Herrschaft S Istv&#225;ns und die Kontinuit&#228;t der Thronfolge in seiner Familie sichern.Istv&#225;n setzte als K&#246;nig die Christianisierung fort. Er holte vor allem deutsche Ordensleute als Missionare ins Land. Dar&#252;ber hinaus ordnete er die politische Struktur Ungarns neu. Die alten Stammesgebiete ersetzte er durch rund 40 Grafschaften (v&#225;rmegye). Jeder Graf (isp&#225;n) diente nicht nur als Regionalverwalter, sondern auch als Heerf&#252;hrer der freien Krieger, der Jobagionen, seiner Grafschaft.Am 2. September 1031 verungl&#252;ckte Istv&#225;ns einziger Sohn Imre bei einer B&#228;renjagd t&#246;dlich, so dass die Frage der Nachfolge pl&#246;tzlich offen und umstritten war. Istv&#225;n I. ernannte schlie&#223;lich Peter Orseolo, den Sohn seiner Schwester Maria, zu seinem Nachfolger. 1038 verstarb auch Istv&#225;n und wurde neben seinem Sohn in der Marienkirche in Sz&#233;kesfeh&#233;rv&#225;r beigesetzt. Seine Gebeine wurden sp&#228;ter nach Buda &#252;bertragen. Seine bis heute unverweste rechte Hand ist ein nationales Heiligtum. Die Stephanskrone gilt heute, obwohl sie nicht die urspr&#252;ngliche Krone Istv&#225;ns ist, als Zeichen der Einigung und war &#252;ber Jahrhunderte die einzig g&#252;ltige bei der Kr&#246;nung ungarischer K&#246;nige. Sie ist auch Teil des Wappens.1083 wurde Istv&#225;n zusammen mit seinem Sohn heilig gesprochen. Sp&#228;ter sprach ihn auch die orthodoxe Kirche heilig damit ist er der erste Heilige beider Konfessionen seit der Spaltung.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Stefano I d'Ungheria[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Primo re cristiano d'Ungheria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vissuto tra il:[\BOLD] 969 - 1038[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2:1][BOLD]Storia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Stefano I d'Ungheria, conosciuto anche come Santo Stefano d'Ungheria (Szent Istv&#225;n in ungherese, &#138;tefan in slovacco), fu il primo re d'Ungheria. Suo padre, Geza, era un capotrib&#249; magiaro: sua madre era Sarolt (in polacco: Adelajda) della dinastia polacca dei Piasts, e a Stefano fu dato alla nascita il nome di Vajk (che significa "eroe"). Nato pagano nel paese di Esztergom, per essere accettato come futuro re dalla Chiesa di Roma, Vajk fu battezzato all'et&#224; di 10 anni da Sant'Adalberto da Praga, e gli fu dato il nome battesimale di Stefano (in onore dell'omonimo ed originale antico Santo cristiano), protettore della chiesa di Passau.[PARAGRAPH:2]Si spos&#242; nel 995 (secondo alcune fonti la data del matrimonio &#232; diversa) con Gisella di Baviera, la figlia di Enrico II di Baviera il litigioso e di sua moglie Gisella di Burgundia. Stefano e Gisella ebbero almeno due figli maschi: Imre (Emerico od Enrico) ed Ott&#243; (Ottone) ed una femmina: Hedvig (Edvige). Tutti e tre morirono prematuramente e non lasciarono eredi che potessero reclamare il trono dopo la morte di Stefano; a causa di ci&#242; la corona fu quindi oggetto di aspre contese da parte dei suoi nipoti e cugini.[PARAGRAPH:2]Tra il 995 e il 997, Stefano (col nome "Vajk") fu principe di Nitra (una comunit&#224; cristiana slovacca e la capitale della provincia omonima; oggi &#232; una citt&#224; della Slovacchia sudoccidentale) e visse l&#236; assieme alla moglie.[PARAGRAPH:2]Dopo aver combattuto e sconfitto i nobili pagani che gli si erano opposti (incluso suo zio, un potente nobile guerriero di nome Kopp&#225;ny), Stefano divenne Sovrano dei Magiari in Transdanubia nel 997 fino al 1006, periodo in cui si adoper&#242; per unire virtualmente tutti i clan magiari. La vittoria su Kopp&#225;ny fu ottenuta anche grazie alla sostanziale assistenza materiale e militare da parte dei nobili slovacchi cristiani Poznan ed Hunt. In accordo con la tradizione ungherese, all'inizio del Gennaio 1001 Papa Silvestro II invi&#242; a Stefano una magnifica corona d'oro incastonata di gioielli (che divenne il simbolo dell'Ungheria col nome di "Santa Corona") assieme alla Croce Apostolica e ad una lettera di benedizione che lo riconosceva ufficialmente Re Cristiano d'Europa.[PARAGRAPH:2]Stefano divise l'Ungheria in 40-50 regioni, continu&#242; il lavoro di suo padre Geza nell'applicare il sistema organizzativo dei suoi antenati detto delle "decime": riorganizz&#242; amministrativamente l'Ungheria in dieci diocesi, ordinando di erigere una chiesa (e di mantenerne il parroco) ogni dieci villagi. Fond&#242; le Cattedrali di Sz&#233;kesfeh&#233;rv&#225;r e di Esztergom, il monastero di Veszpr&#233;m, l'Abbazia benedettina di Pannonhalma, e il Monastero dei Santi Pietro e Paolo ad &#211;buda. All'interno delle abbazie e dei monasteri, furono aperte delle scuole che divennero importanti centri di cultura. Sant'Astrico fu il consigliere di Stefano, che ebbe anche San Gerardo Sagredo come tutore di suo figlio Sant'Emerico (Imre).[PARAGRAPH:2]Stefano scoraggi&#242; le usanze pagane e rafforz&#242; la cristianit&#224; con varie leggi, inclusa la messa al bando del vecchio alfabeto runico unno-magiaro e rendendo il latino la lingua ufficiale della corte regale. Stefano si mostr&#242; sempre generoso nei confronti delle chiese, personalmente le visit&#242; spesso, e supervision&#242; la loro construzione. Quando viaggiava, spesso si travestiva da contadino e liberamente donava delle monete alla povera gente che incontrava (in un caso, Stefano fu aggredito e derubato da un gruppo di briganti a cui aveva fatto elemosina; ma lui se ne dimentic&#242; e risparmi&#242; le loro vite).[PARAGRAPH:2]Stefano era intenzionato a ritirarsi ad una vita di contemplazione spirituale e consegn&#242; il regno al suo unico figlio sopravvissuto, Imre; ma nel 1031 quest'ultimo fu ferito in una battuta di caccia e mor&#236;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Stefano pianse a lungo per la perdita del suo figlio favorito Imre, alla cui cura egli aveva dedicato gran parte del suo tempo. Stefano probabilmnte si riprese, ma non manifest&#242; pi&#249; la sua originale vitalit&#224;. Non avendo pi&#249; figli, egli non riusc&#236; a trovare fra i suoi familiari una persona capace di governare il paese con la competenza e la volont&#224; necessarie per sostenere la fede cristiana nella nazione. Incapace di scegliere un erede, Re Stefano mor&#236; a Sz&#233;kesfeh&#233;rv&#225;r nel giorno della Festa dell'Assunzione, e l&#236; fu seppellito; Si dice che la sua corte di nobili e la sua servit&#249; piansero la sua scomparsa per tre anni interi.[PARAGRAPH:2]Immediatamente dopo la sua morte si sparse la voce di miracoli curativi che si verificavano presso la sua tomba. Stefano fu canonizzato dal Vaticano come Santo Stefano d'Ungheria nel 1083. I cattolici lo venerano come il santo patrono d'Ungheria, dei re, dei bambini morti, dei muratori e dei cavatori. La sua ricorrenza cade il 2 settembre, ma in Ungheria la festa principale &#232; osservata il 20 Agosto, il giorno in cui le sue sacre spoglie furono trasferite nella citt&#224; di Buda; questo &#232; un giorno di festa nazionale in Ungheria.[PARAGRAPH:2]La sua corona, conosciuta come la "Santa Corona", attualmente (dal 2000) &#232; conservata nel palazzo del Parlamento Ungherese, a Budapest.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BARBAROSSA</Tag>
		<English>Frederick Barbarossa</English>
		<French>Frédéric Barberousse</French>
		<German>Friedrich Barbarossa</German>
		<Italian>Frederico Barbarossa</Italian>
		<Spanish>Frederico Barbarroja</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BARBAROSSA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Frederick Barbarossa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Germany, Italy, Burgundy and Holy Roman Emperor[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1122 - June 10, 1190[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Frederick I Barbarossa was elected King of Germany at Frankfurt on 4 March 1152 and crowned in Aachen on 9 March, crowned King of Italy in Pavia in 1154, and finally crowned Holy Roman Emperor by Pope Adrian IV on 18 June 1155. He was crowned King of Burgundy at Arles on 30 June 1178. The name Barbarossa came from the northern Italian cities he attempted to rule, and means "red beard". Before his royal election, he was by inheritance Duke of Swabia (1147-1152, as Frederick III). He was the son of Duke Frederick II of the Hohenstaufen dynasty. His mother was Judith, daughter of Henry IX, Duke of Bavaria, from the rival House of Welf, and Frederick therefore descended from Germany's two leading families, making him an acceptable choice for the Empire's prince-electors.[PARAGRAPH:1] He was born in Waiblingen, the son of Frederick II of Hohenstaufen, duke of Swabia, and the nephew of Conrad III, king of Germany. Conrad III, favouring Frederick over his own son, on his deathbed recommended to the German princes that Frederick be chosen for the German kingship and the imperial throne. Accordingly, after the death of his uncle in 1152, Frederick Barbarossa was made German king and elected Holy Roman emperor (see Holy Roman Empire). He conceived of his imperial title as a grant from God, through the German princes, and wished to restore the glory of the Roman Empire. He consequently decided to consolidate the imperial position in Germany and Italy and began by issuing a general order for peace among the princes of Germany, at the same time granting them extensive concessions. In 1154 he proceeded to Italy, where he received the Lombard crown at Pavia. The following year he was crowned Holy Roman emperor by Pope Adrian IV, whose authority Frederick had reinstated before his coronation.[PARAGRAPH:1] In 1156 Pope Adrian aroused Frederick against the papacy by implying in a letter to him that the emperor held lands only as a fief from the pope. Two years later Frederick incurred the hostility of the Lombards by demanding recognition of all his royal rights, including his power to appoint the imperial podesta, or governor, in every town. Such cities as Milan, Piacenza, Brescia, and Cremona considered that demand a denial of their communal liberties and in 1158 began a struggle that lasted until 1183 and required Frederick to lead five expeditions to Italy. Between 1158 and 1162 Frederick warred with Milan and its allies, subduing that city and confirming claims to other Italian cities. Meanwhile Frederick had set up a series of antipopes in opposition to the reigning pope, Alexander III, who supported the cause of the Milanese and their allies and who, in 1165, excommunicated Frederick. By attacking the Leonine City in Rome in 1167-1168, Frederick was able to install one of the antipopes, Paschal III, on the papal throne. The Lombard League, consisting of the cities of Milan, Parma, Padua (Padova), Verona, Piacenza, Bologna, Cremona, Mantua (Mantova), Bergamo, and Brescia, was formed in 1167 and eventually acknowledged Pope Alexander as leader. During the next seven years the league acquired military strength, rebuilt Milan, constructed the fortress city of Alessandria, and organized a federal system of administration. The fifth expedition (1174-1176) of Frederick to Italy terminated in defeat by the Lombard League at Legnano. The defeat was significant in military history, because it was the first major triumph of infantry over a mounted army of feudal knights. Frederick was forced in 1177 to acknowledge Alexander III as pope and in 1183 to sign the Peace of Constance, agreeing to the demands of the Lombards for autonomy but retaining imperial authority over the towns.[PARAGRAPH:1] Although imperial control in Italy was virtually ended by his defeat at Legnano, Frederick managed to enhance his prestige in central Europe. He made Poland tributary to the empire, raised Bohemia to the rank of a kingdom, and erected the margravate of Austria into an independent hereditary duchy. His own power as emperor in Germany was firmly established in 1180, when he ended his long struggle with the Welfs by putting down a revolt led by the Welf Henry the Lion and depriving him of most of his lands.[PARAGRAPH:1] Frederick initiated the Third Crusade in 1189, and in the next year, having resigned the government of the empire to his son Henry, later Holy Roman Emperor Henry VI, set out for Asia Minor. After gaining two great victories over the Muslims at Philomelion (now Aksehir) and Iconium (now Konya), he has drowned in the Calycadnus (now G&#246;ksu) River in Cilicia (now in Turkey) on June 10, 1190.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Friedrich Barbarossa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Heiliger Römischer Kaiser[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 1122 - 1190</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CASIMIR</Tag>
		<English>Casimir III</English>
		<French>Casimir III</French>
		<German>Kasimir III.</German>
		<Italian>Casimiro III</Italian>
		<Spanish>Casimiro III</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CASIMIR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Casimir III the Great [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Poland [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1310 - 1370[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Casimir III was born in Kowal, at April 30, 1310. Last of the Piast Dynasty, king of Poland from 1333, the son of Wladyslaw I the Short (Wladyslaw I Lokietek). [PARAGRAPH:1]Casimir is the only Polish king who did receive and maintain the title of the great in Polish history (Boleslaw I Chrobry was once also called the great, but not today), and the title is well deserved. When he received the crown, his hold on it was in danger, as even his neighbours did not recognise his title and instead called him "king of Krakow. The economy was ruined, and country was depopulated and tired with wars. At the time of his death, it had doubled in land area (mostly through joining lands in today's Ukraine, then Duchy of Halicz), grew prosperous, wealthy and had great prospects to the future. Although he is depicted as a peaceful king in children books, he in fact waged many victorious wars and was preparing other ones just before he died. [PARAGRAPH:1]He built many new castles, reformed the Polish army, as well as Polish civil and criminal laws. At the Sejm in Wislica, March 11, 1347, he introduced salutary legal reforms in the jurisprudence of his country. He sanctioned a code of laws for Great and Little Poland, which gained for him the title of "the Polish Justinian". He founded the University of Krakow although his death stalled the development of the university (and that's why today it is called Jagiellonian instead of Casimirian).He organised a meeting of kings in Krakow in 1364 which showed the wealth of Polish kingdom. [PARAGRAPH:1]Casimir was sonless. Apparently he deemed his own descendants either unsuitable to inherit or too young. Thus, and in order to provide a clear line of succession instead of problems of uncertainty, he arranged his sister Elisabeth, Dowager Queen of Hungary, and her son Louis, King of Hungary to be his successors in Poland. Louis was proclaimed polish king in Casimir's death in 1370, but Elisabeth held much of the practical power until her death in 1380.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Kasimir III.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König Polens[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 30. April 1310 - 5. November 1370[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Kasimir III. wurde am 30. April 1310 in Kowal geboren. Er wurde am 25. April 1333 König Polens, und regierte 37 Jahre lang, in denen er viele Festungen in seinem Königreich baute, das Gesetzsystem reformierte, die Universität Krakaus gründete, und, am wichtigsten von allem, viele siegreiche Kriege kämpfte. Gewinne dieser Kriegen schließen einen großen Teil der Ukraine und das Herzogtum Halytsch ein. Außerdem beachtenswert ist die Tatsache, dass er die Juden in seinem Land schützte, und diejenigen dazu ermunterte, die in anderen Ländern leben, nach Polen zu emigrieren. Zu seinen Tod, am 5. November 1370, hatte Polen eine viel gesündere Wirtschaft, und seine Größe hatte sich verdoppelt. Aus diesen Gründen nennen Historiker ihn Kasimir den Großen.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOBIESKI</Tag>
		<English>Jan Sobieski</English>
		<French>Jean Sobieski</French>
		<German>Johann Sobieski</German>
		<Italian>Giovanni Sobieski</Italian>
		<Spanish>Juan Sobieski</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOBIESKI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]John III Sobieski[\H1]
[BOLD]King of Poland, Ruler of the Commonwealth[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1629 - 1696


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	Jan (John) Sobieski was born 1629 at Olesko, Poland, to Jakub (James) Sobieski (1580-1646), Voivod of the Ruthenian Voivodship and Castellan of Krakow and Zofia Teofillia (Danilowicz), granddaughter of Hetman Stanislaw Zebewski. He had won fame as an outstanding military commander in wars against the Ottomans, Tatars, Muscovites, Cossacks and Swedes.
[TAB]In 1665 he became Great Marshal of the Crown, and in 1666 Field Crown Hetman. In 1668 he was appointed by King Jan II Kazimierz the Great Crown Hetman and Commander-in-Chief of the Polish Army. After a distinguished military career, and following the death of Jan II Kazimierz's successor, Michal Korybut Wisniowiecki, Sobieski was on May 21, 1674, elected by the szlachta (nobility) to be King of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth, and was crowned February 2, 1676.
[TAB]Jan Sobieski's military prowess, demonstrated in war against the Ottoman Empire, contributed to his election as King of Poland. One of his ambitions was to unify Christian Europe in a crusade to drive the Turks out of Europe. He made alliance with the Holy Roman Emperor and joined the Holy League initiated by Pope Innocent XI to preserve Christendom.
[TAB]Sobieski planned to occupy Prussia with Swedish cooperation and French support. This undertaking was doomed because of war with Turkey and the opposition of the Commonwealth's magnates.
[TAB]Sobieski's greatest success came September 12, 1683, with his victory at the Battle of Vienna, in command of Polish, Austrian and German troops, against the Turks under Kara Mustafa. The Pope and other foreign dignitaries hailed Sobieski as the "Savior of Vienna and Western European civilization." In a letter to his wife he wrote, "All the common people kissed my hands, my feet, my clothes; others only touched me, saying: 'Ah, let us kiss so valiant a hand!'"
[TAB]Upon reaching Vienna, he joined up with the Austrians and Germans. Sobieski planned to attack on the 13th of September, but he had noticed that the Turkish resistance was weak and ordered full attack on September 12, 1683. At 4:00 a.m. Sobieski's army of about 81,000 men attacked a Turkish army that numbered about 130,000. Sobieski charged with husaria forward and soon after the Turkish battle line was broken as the Turks scattered in confusion. At 5:30 p.m., Sobieski entered the deserted tent of Kara Mustafa and the battle of Vienna was over.
[TAB]King Jan III Sobieski, nicknamed by the Turks the "Lion of Lechistan", and the last great king of Poland, died in Wilan, Poland on June 17, 1696. His wife, Maria Kasimira, died in 1716 in Blois, France and her body was returned to Poland. They are interred together in Wawel Castle, Krakow, Poland.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Johann III Sobieski[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König von Polen[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 1629 - 1696</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_IVAN_IV</Tag>
		<English>Ivan IV</English>
		<French>Ivan IV</French>
		<German>Iwan IV.</German>
		<Italian>Ivan IV</Italian>
		<Spanish>Iván IV</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_IVAN_IV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Ivan "the Terrible" IV[\H1]
[BOLD]First Tsar of Russia[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] August 25, 1530 - March 18, 1584


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	Ivan IV was the Grand Duke of Muscovy from 1533 to 1547 and was the first ruler of Russia to assume the title of tsar. His long reign saw the conquest of Kazan Khanate and Siberia and subsequent transformation of Russia into a multiethnic and multiconfessional state. This tsar retains his place in the Russian tradition simply as Ivan Grozny, which is traditionally translated into English as Ivan the Terrible.
[TAB]Ivan (or Ioann, as his name is rendered in Church Slavonic) was a long-awaited son of Vasili III. Upon his father's death, he formally came to the throne at the age of three, but his minority was dominated by regents. Initially his mother Elena Glinskaya acted as regent, but she died when Ivan was only eight. She was replaced as regent by boyars from the Shuisky family until Ivan assumed power in 1544. According to his own letters, Ivan customarily felt neglected and offended by the mighty boyars from the Shuisky and Belsky families. These traumatic experiences may have contributed to his hatred of the boyars and to his mental instability. He was known to throw cats and dogs out of the Kremlin windows, among other cruel acts.
[TAB]Ivan was crowned king with Monomakh's Cap at the Cathedral of the Dormition at age sixteen on January 16, 1547. Despite calamities triggered by the Great Fire of 1547, the early part of his reign was one of peaceful reforms and modernization. Ivan revised the law code (known as the sudebnik), created a standing army (the streltsy), established the first Russian parliament of the feudal estates (the Zemsky Sobor), the council of the nobles (known as the Chosen Council), and confirmed the position of the Church with the Council of the Hundred Chapters, which unified the rituals and ecclesiastical regulations of the entire country. He introduced the local self-management in rural regions, mainly in the Northeast of Russia, populated by the state peasantry. During his reign the first printing press was introduced to Russia (although the first Russian printers Ivan Fedorov and Pyotr Mstislavets had to flee from Moscow to the Grand Duchy of Lithuania).
[TAB]Ivan formed new trading connections, opening up the White Sea and the port of Arkhangelsk to the Muscovy Company of English merchants. In 1552 he defeated the Kazan Khanate, whose armies had repeatedly devastated the Northeast of Russia, and annexed its territory. In 1556, he annexed the Astrakhan Khanate and destroyed the largest slave market on the river Volga. These conquests complicated the migration of the aggressive nomadic hordes from Asia to Europe through Volga and transformed Russia into a multinational and multiconfessional state. He had St. Basil's Cathedral constructed in Moscow to commemorate the seizure of Kazan. Legend has it that he was so impressed with the structure that he had the architects blinded, so that they could never design anything as beautiful again.
[TAB]Other less positive aspects of this period include the introduction of the first laws restricting the mobility of the peasants, which would eventually lead to serfdom. The dramatic change in Ivan's personality is traditionally linked to his near-fatal illness in 1553 and the death of his first wife, Anastasia Romanovna in 1560. Ivan suspected boyars of poisoning his wife and of plotting to replace him on the throne with his cousin, Vladimir of Staritsa. In addition, during that illness Ivan had asked the boyars to swear an oath of allegiance to his eldest son, an infant at the time. Many boyars refused, deeming the tsar's health too hopeless to survive. This angered Ivan and added to his distrust of the boyars. There followed brutal reprisals and murders of innocent people, including Metropolitan Philip and Prince Alexander Gorbatyi-Shuisky.
[TAB]Also problematic was the 1565 formation of the Oprichnina. The Oprichnina was the section of Russia (mainly the Northeast) directly ruled by Ivan and policed by his personal servicemen, the Oprichniki. This whole system of Oprichnina has been viewed by some historians as a tool against the omnipotent hereditary nobility of Russia (boyars) who opposed the absolutist drive of the tsar, while others have interpreted it as a sign of the paranoia and mental deterioration of the tsar.
[TAB]The later half of Ivan's reign was far less successful. Although Khan Devlet I Giray of Crimea repeatedly devastated Moscow region and even set Moscow on fire in 1571, the tsar supported Yermak's conquest of Tatar Siberia, adopting a policy of empire-building, which led him to launch a victorious war of seaward expansion to the west, only to find himself fighting the Swedes, Lithuanians, Poles, and the Livonian Teutonic Knights.
[TAB]For twenty-four years the Livonian War dragged on, damaging the Russian economy and military and failing to gain any territory for Russia. In the 1560s the combination of drought and famine, Polish-Lithuanian raids, Tatar invasions, and the sea-trading blockade carried out by the Swedes, Poles and the Hanseatic League devastated Russia. The price of grain increased by a factor of ten. Epidemics of the plague killed 10,000 in Novgorod. In 1570 the plague killed 600-1000 in Moscow daily. Ivan's closest advisor, Prince Andrei Kurbsky, defected to the Lithuanians, headed the Lithuanian troops and devastated the Russian region of Velikiye Luki. This treachery deeply hurt Ivan. As the Oprichnina continued, Ivan became mentally unstable and physically disabled. In one week, he could easily pass from the most depraved orgies to prayers and fasting in a remote northern monastery.
[TAB]Because he gradually grew unbalanced and violent, the Oprichniks under Malyuta Skuratov soon got out of hand and became murderous thugs. They massacred nobles and peasants, and conscripted men to fight the war in Livonia. Depopulation and famine ensued. What had been by far the richest area of Russia became the poorest. In a dispute with the wealthy city of Novgorod, Ivan ordered the Oprichniks to murder inhabitants of this city, which was never to regain its former prosperity. Between thirty and forty thousand might have been killed during the infamous Massacre of Novgorod in 1570; many others were deported elsewhere. Yet the official death toll named 1,500 of Novgorod big people (nobility) and only mentioned about the same number of smaller people. Many modern researchers estimate number of victims between two and three thousand. (After the famine and epidemics of 1560s the population of Novgorod did not exceed 10,000-20,000.)
[TAB]In 1581, Ivan beat his pregnant daughter-in-law for wearing immodest clothing, causing a miscarriage. His son, also named Ivan, upon learning of this, engaged in a heated argument with his father, which resulted in Ivan striking his son in the head with his pointed staff, causing his son's (accidental) death. This event is depicted in the famous painting by Ilya Repin, Ivan the Terrible and his son Ivan on Friday, November 16, 1581 better known as Ivan the Terrible killing his son.
[TAB]Although it is thought by many that Ivan died while setting up a chess board, it is more likely that he died while playing chess with Bogdan Belsky on March 18, 1584. When Ivan's tomb was opened during renovations in the 1960s, his remains were examined and discovered to contain very high amounts of mercury, indicating a high probability that he was poisoned. Modern suspicion falls on his advisors Belsky and Boris Godunov (who became tsar in 1598). Three days earlier, Ivan had allegedly attempted to rape Irina, Godunov's sister and Feodor's wife. Her cries attracted Godunov and Belsky to the noise, whereupon Ivan let Irina go, but Belsky and Godunov considered themselves marked for death. The tradition says that they either poisoned or strangled Ivan in fear for their own lives. The mercury found in Ivan's remains may also be related to treatment for syphilis, which it is speculated that Ivan had. Upon Ivan's death, the ravaged kingdom was left to his unfit and childless son Feodor.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Iwan "der Schrecklicher" IV.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Erster Zar Russlands[NEWLINE]Lebte: [\BOLD] 1530 - 1584

[TAB][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD]
[TAB]Der Sohn Wassilis III., geboren am 25. August 1530 in Moskau, verlor im Alter von drei Jahren seinen Vater und wurde nach blutigen Machtkämpfen zwischen Gruppen der Bojaren 1547 nach byzantinischem Zeremoniell zum Zaren gekrönt. Er stärkte die Zentralgewalt durch Reformen von Verwaltung, Rechtswesen und Armee und förderte den niederen Dienstadel auf Kosten der mächtigen Bojaren.
[TAB]Mit der Eroberung der Khanate Kasan 1552 und Astrachan 1556 dehnte er seinen Einfluß bis Sibirien aus. Im Westen scheiterte er jedoch bei dem Versuch, in Livland einen Zugang zur Ostsee zur erkämpfen. Der dadurch ausgelöste langandauernde Krieg mit Polen-Litauen und Schweden 1558-83 ruinierte die Wirtschaft.
[TAB]Mißtrauisch bis zum Verfolgungswahn, unterdrückte der Zar jede Unbotmäßigkeit mit brutalen Strafgerichten. Als Terrorinstrument hatte er sich 1565 die Truppe der Opritschnina geschaffen. In einem Wutanfall erschlug er sogar seinen eigenen Sohn.
[TAB]Andererseits war er hochgebildet und literarisch begabt. Bei seinem Tod am 18. März 1584 in Moskau war der Staat so zerrüttet, dass er wenig später zusammenbrach.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SIMONE</Tag>
		<English>Simone Boccanegra</English>
		<French>Simone Boccanegra</French>
		<German>Simone Boccanegra</German>
		<Italian>Simone Boccanegra</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sim&#243;n Boccanegra</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SIMONE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Simone Boccanegra[\H1]
[BOLD]First Doge of Genoa[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] ? - 1363 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_WILLIAM</Tag>
		<English>William I</English>
		<French>Guillaume Ier</French>
		<German>Wilhelm I.</German>
		<Italian>Guglielmo I</Italian>
		<Spanish>Guillermo I</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_WILLIAM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]William the Conqueror[\H1]
[BOLD]First Norman King of England, Duke of Normandy[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.1028 - September 9, 1087 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_AFONSO</Tag>
		<English>Afonso Henriques</English>
		<French>Alphonse Henriques</French>
		<German>Afonso Henriques</German>
		<Italian>Alfonso Henriques</Italian>
		<Spanish>Alfonso Henriques</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_AFONSO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Afonso Henriques[\H1]
[BOLD]First King of Portugal[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] July 25, 1109 - December 6, 1189 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	Afonso I of Portugal, more commonly known as Afonso Henriques and also known as the Conqueror (o Conquistador), was the first King of Portugal, declaring his independence from Leon. He fought several successful campaigns against the Moors and, on July 26, 1139, he obtained an overwhelming victory in the Battle of Ourique, and straight after was unanimously proclaimed King of Portugal by his soldiers. This meant that Portugal was no longer a vassal county of Leon-Castile, but an independent kingdom in its own right. Next, he assembled the first assembly of the estates-general at Lamego, where he was given the crown from the archbishop of Braga, to confirm the independence.
[TAB]Independence, however, was not a thing a land could choose on its own. Portugal still had to be acknowledged by the neighbouring lands and, most importantly, by the Roman Catholic Church and the Pope. Afonso wedded Mafalda of Savoy, daughter of Count Amadeo III of Savoy, and sent Ambassadors to Rome to negotiate with the Pope. In Portugal, he built several monasteries and convents and bestowed important privileges to religious orders. In 1143, he wrote to Pope Innocent II to declare himself and the kingdom servants of the Church, swearing to pursue driving the Moors out of the Iberian peninsula. Bypassing any king of Castile or Leon. Afonso declared himself the direct liegeman of the Papacy. Thus, Afonso continued to distinguish himself by his exploits against the Moors, from whom he wrested Santar&#233;m and Lisbon in 1147. He also conquered an important part of the land south of the Tagus River, although this was lost again to the Moors in the following years.
[TAB]Meanwhile, King Alfonso VII of Castile (Afonso's cousin) regarded the independent ruler of Portugal as nothing but a rebel. Conflict between the two was constant and bitter in the following years. Afonso became involved in a war, taking the side of the Aragonese king, an enemy of Castile. To ensure the alliance, his son Sancho was engaged to Dulce Berenguer, sister of the Count of Barcelona, and princess of Aragon. Finally, in 1143, the Treaty of Zamora established peace between the cousins and the recognition by the Kingdom of Castile and Leon that Portugal was an independent kingdom.
[TAB]In 1179 the privileges and favours given to the Roman Catholic Church were compensated. In the papal bull "Manifestis Probatum", Pope Alexander III acknowledged Afonso as King and Portugal as an independent land with the right to conquer lands from the Moors. With this papal blessing, Portugal was at last secured as a country and safe from any Castilian attempts of annexation.
[TAB]In 1184, in spite of his great age, he had still sufficient energy to relieve his son Sancho, who was besieged in Santar&#233;m by the Moors. He died shortly after, in 1185.
[TAB]The Portuguese revere him as a hero, both on account of his personal character and as the founder of their nation.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Afonso Henriques[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Erster König von Portugal[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 25. Juli 1109 - 6. Dezember 1189</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MARIA_THERESA</Tag>
		<English>Maria Theresa</English>
		<French>Marie-Th&#233;r&#232;se</French>
		<German>Maria Theresia</German>
		<Italian>Maria Teresa</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mar&#237;a Teresa</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MARIA_THERESA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Maria Theresa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Archduchess of Austria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Theresa was the eldest daughter of Elisabeth Christine of Brunswick-Wolfenbuttel and Emperor Charles VI who allowed her to succeed the Habsburg Monarchy. Her transition to the throne was all but simple. Opposition to her succession to the throne led to the War of the Austrian Succession in 1740. After Emperor Charles VII, who claimed the throne, died in 1745, Maria Theresa claimed the throne for her husband, Francis I. She was technically the empress consort, but was the de facto ruler of the nation. In 1745, she also began styling herself as the Holy Roman Empress.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Maria Theresa helped commence financial and educational reforms, promoted commerce, agriculture, and reorganized the army. Many of her actions strengthened Austria as a whole and its resources. After a continuous conflict with Prussia, the Seven Years' War and eventually to the War of the Bavarian Succession. She became the dowager empress after the death of Francis and succession of her son Joseph as emperor in 1765. Maria Theresa brought unity to the Habsburg Monarchy and is considered one of its most talented rulers.[PARAGRAPH: 1]While Bavaria and France posed a continuous threat to Austria, it was Frederick the Great who became Maria's primary foe during her reign. Maria Theresa focused the majority of her policies towards the defeat or Prussia. Because of these reforms, the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle gave the Austrian Netherlands back to Maria Theresa. In exchange, Maria ceded Parma, Piacenza, and Guastalla to the Infante Philip of Spain. After being defeated in the First and Second Silesian Wars, Maria Theresa began to modernize her realms with the assistance of Freidrich Wilhelm Graf von Gaugwitz. Of her many reforms, she increased the size of the army by 200% and increased taxes to guarantee a steady income for the military. She also centralized the government by combining the Austrian and Bohemian chancelleries into one administrative office.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Like other Habsburgs, Maria Theresa was a devout Roman Catholic. She was educated by Jesuits at Mariazell, and in later life was short of the religious pessimism of other royal figures of her time. Her conservative outlook involved a poor view of other faiths. In 1741, she expelled the Jewish people from Prague.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Maria Theresa dropped Great Britain as an ally and allied herself with Russia and France. When she felt her army was strong enough, she prepared an attack on Prussia in 1756. However, it was Frederick II who attacked first, invading Saxony and starting the Seven Years' War. When Maria Theresa signed the Treaty of Hubertsburg in 1763, the war ended recognizing Prussia as the owner of most of Silesia.[PARAGRAPH: 1]After her husband's death in 1765, Maria Theresa became separated from her people. Her focus changed to maintaining peace, rather than regaining Silesia. She named her son, Joseph II, as coregent and Emperor. However, he received limited powers because she felt he was too haughty for the full responsibilities. In 1767, Maria Theresa was infected with smallpox. However, she recovered and became a strong supporter of inoculation. In her later years, she focused on reforming laws along the lines of enlightened absolutism.[PARAGRAPH: 1]In 1771, she and Joseph II issued to Robot Patent, a reform that regulated the serf's payments in her lands. Other reforms included outlawing witch-burning and torture, and taking capital punishment the off the penal code. In 1772, Maria Theresa founded the Imperial and Royal Academy of Science and Literature in Brussels. Mandatory education was introduced in 1774 in order to form an educated class of citizens, from which civil servants were recruited. Maria Theresa continued issuing various police laws throughout Austria. She died in 1780 in Vienna, being the only female to rule the Habsburg Dynasty, which lasted 650 years. Her son Joseph II was her successor.</English>
		<French>[H1]Marie-Thérèse[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Archiduchesse d'Autriche[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Theresa est la fille aînée de Christine Elisabeth de Brunswick Wolfenbuttel, et l'empereur Charles VI, qui lui a permis de réussir la monarchie des Habsbourg. Sa transition vers le trône était tout sauf simples. L'opposition à sa succession au trône conduit à la guerre de Succession d'Autriche en 1740. Après l'empereur Charles VII, qui a revendiqué le trône, est mort en 1745, Maria Theresa revendiqué le trône à son mari, François I. Elle était techniquement consort de l'impératrice, mais était de facto le dirigeant de la nation. En 1745, elle a aussi commencé style elle-même comme la Sainte impératrice romaine. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Maria Theresa aidé commencer financières et les réformes de l'éducation, de promouvoir le commerce, l'agriculture, et réorganisation de l'armée. Beaucoup de ses actions de renforcement de l'Autriche dans son ensemble et de ses ressources. Au terme d'un conflit avec la Prusse, la guerre de Sept Ans et, finalement, à la guerre de Succession de Bavière. Elle est devenue la dowager impératrice après la mort de François et de la succession de son fils Joseph empereur en 1765. Maria Theresa unité portées à la monarchie des Habsbourg et est considéré comme l'un de ses dirigeants les plus talentueux. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Alors que la Bavière et la France fait peser une menace continue à l'Autriche, il a été Frédéric le Grand, qui est devenu le principal ennemi Maria durant son règne. Maria Theresa concentré la majorité de ses politiques en faveur de la défaite ou la Prusse. En raison de ces réformes, le traité d'Aix-la-Chapelle a donné les Pays-Bas autrichiens retour à Marie Thérèse. En échange, Maria cède Parme, Plaisance, Guastalla et à l'Infante Philip de l'Espagne. Après avoir été battu lors des Première et Deuxième Guerres de Silésie, Maria Theresa a commencé à moderniser son royaume avec l'aide de Freidrich Wilhelm von Gaugwitz. De ses nombreuses réformes, elle a augmenté les effectifs de l'armée de 200% et une augmentation des impôts pour assurer un revenu stable pour les militaires. Elle a également centralisé, le gouvernement autrichien en combinant les chancelleries et de Bohême dans un bureau administratif. [PARAGRAPH: 1] À l'instar d'autres Habsbourg, Maria Theresa était une fervente catholique. Elle a été instruite par les Jésuites à Mariazell, et en fin de vie a été de courte de la religieuse pessimisme des autres personnalités royales de son temps. Ses perspectives conservatrices impliqué une mauvaise opinion des autres religions. EN 1741, elle a expulsé le peuple juif de Prague. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Maria Theresa chuté Grande-Bretagne comme des alliés et s'est alliée avec la Russie et la France. Quand elle a senti son armée est assez forte, elle a préparé une attaque contre la Prusse en 1756. Toutefois, il a été Frédéric II, qui a attaqué en premier, envahissent la Saxe et de commencer la guerre de Sept Ans. Lorsque Maria Theresa signé le Traité de Hubertsburg en 1763, la guerre a pris fin en reconnaissant la Prusse en tant que propriétaire de la majeure partie de la Silésie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Après le décès de son mari en 1765, Maria Theresa devient séparée de son peuple. Sa tendance a changé pour le maintien de la paix, plutôt que de reconquérir la Silésie. Elle a nommé son fils, Joseph II, comme coregent et de l'empereur. Cependant, il a reçu des pouvoirs limités, car elle a estimé qu'il était trop arrogant pour la totalité des responsabilités. En 1767, Maria Theresa a été infecté par la variole. Toutefois, elle a récupéré et est devenu un fervent partisan de l'inoculation. Dans ses dernières années, elle s'est concentrée sur la réforme des lois allant dans le sens de l'absolutisme éclairé. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1771, elle et Joseph II brevets délivrés aux robots, une réforme qui régissaient le serf dans ses paiements de terres. D'autres réformes figurent proscrivant sorcières brûlant et de la torture, et prenant le large de la peine capitale du code pénal. En 1772, Maria Theresa fondé l'Académie royale et impériale de la science et de la littérature à Bruxelles. L'enseignement obligatoire a été introduite en 1774 afin de former une classe de citoyens instruits, dont les fonctionnaires ont été recrutés. Maria Theresa continué délivrance différentes lois de police dans toute l'Autriche. Elle est décédée en 1780 à Vienne, étant la seule femme à la règle de la dynastie des Habsbourg, qui a duré 650 ans. Son fils Joseph II était son successeur.</French>
		<German>[H1]Maria Theresia[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Erzherzogin von Österreich[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Theresia war die älteste Tochter von Elisabeth Christine von Braunschweig - Wolfenbüttel und Kaiser Karl VI, der sich ihr Erfolg der Habsburger Monarchie. Ihrem Übergang zum Thron war aber einfach. Widerspruch zu ihrem Thronfolge führte zu dem Krieg des österreichischen Erbfolgekrieg 1740. Nach Kaiser Karl VII., die behauptet, den Thron, starb 1745, Maria Theresia beansprucht den Thron für ihren Mann, Franz I. Sie war technisch die Kaiserin Gefährtin, war aber der de facto Herrscher des Landes. Im Jahre 1745, begann sie auch Styling selbst als das Heilige Römische Kaiserin. [ABSATZ: 1] Maria Theresia geholfen beginnen finanzielle und pädagogische Reformen, gefördert Handel, Landwirtschaft und der Armee reorganisiert. Viele ihrer Aktionen gestärkt werden Österreich als Ganzes und ihrer Ressourcen. Nach einem ständigen Konflikt mit Preußen, des Siebenjährigen Krieges und schließlich zu dem Krieg der Bayerischen Erbfolgekrieg. Sie wurde die Kaiserin Witwe nach dem Tod des Franziskus und der Abfolge von ihrem Sohn Joseph als Kaiser in 1765. Maria Theresia brachte Einheit in der Habsburger Monarchie und gilt als einer der talentiertesten Herrscher. [ABSATZ: 1] Während Bayern und Frankreich stellte eine ständige Bedrohung für Österreich, es war Friedrich der Große, Maria wurde in erster Linie Feind während ihrer Regierungszeit. Maria Theresia konzentrierte sich die Mehrheit ihrer Politik gegenüber der Niederlage oder Preußen. Aufgrund dieser Reformen, den Vertrag von Aix la Chapelle gab der österreichischen Niederlande zurück zu Maria Theresia. Im Gegenzug, Maria abgetretenen Parma, Piacenza und Guastalla an den Infanten Philipp von Spanien. Nach der Niederlage im Ersten und Zweiten Schlesischen Kriege, Maria Theresia begann zu modernisieren, ihre Bereiche mit Hilfe von Freidrich Wilhelm Graf von Gaugwitz. Ihrer vielen Reformen, sie erhöht die Größe der Armee um 200% und höhere Steuern zu garantieren, ein geregeltes Einkommen für das Militär. Sie auch zentral die Regierung durch die Kombination der österreichischen und böhmischen Kanzleien in einer Verwaltungsbehörde. [ABSATZ: 1] Wie andere Habsburger, Maria Theresia war ein gläubiger römisch-katholisch. Sie wurde von den Jesuiten in Mariazell, und im späteren Leben war kurz der religiösen Pessimismus der anderen königlichen Zahlen ihrer Zeit. Ihre konservativen Ausblick an einen schlechten Blick auf andere Religionen. IN 1741, sie trieben die Juden aus Prag. [ABSATZ: 1] Maria Theresia ging Großbritannien als Verbündeter und verbündeten sich mit Russland und Frankreich. Wenn sie das Gefühl hatte, ihre Armee sei stark genug, sie bereit, einen Angriff auf die Preußen 1756. Allerdings war es Friedrich II., der erste Angriff, der Invasion Sachsen und Starten des Siebenjährigen Krieges. Wenn Maria Theresia unterzeichnet den Vertrag von Hubertsburg 1763 endete der Krieg in Anerkennung Preußen als Eigentümer der meisten Schlesien. [ABSATZ: 1] Nach dem Tod ihres Mannes im 1765, Maria Theresia wurde getrennt von ihren Menschen. Ihr Schwerpunkt auf die Erhaltung des Friedens, anstatt wieder in Schlesien. Sie benannt ihrem Sohn, Joseph II., Kaiser und Mitregenten. Allerdings erhielt er beschränkte Befugnisse, weil sie das Gefühl hatte, er war zu stolz für die volle Verantwortung. Im Jahre 1767, Maria Theresia wurde mit Pocken infiziert. Doch sie erholte sich und wurde ein starker Befürworter der Impfung. In ihren späteren Jahren hat sie sich auf die Reform der Gesetze im Sinne des aufgeklärten Absolutismus. [ABSATZ: 1] In 1771, die sie und Joseph II. ausgestellt Robot Patent, eine Reform, reguliert die Leibeigener der Zahlungen in ihrem Land. Weitere Reformen sind Verbot Hexe - Brennen und Folter, die Todesstrafe und die aus dem Strafgesetzbuch. Im Jahre 1772, Maria Theresia gegründet, die Imperial und Königliche Akademie der Wissenschaften und Literatur in Brüssel. Obligatorische Ausbildung wurde im Jahre 1774 im Hinblick auf eine gebildete Klasse der Bürger, von denen Beamte wurden eingestellt. Maria Theresia setzte die Ausstellung verschiedene Gesetze Polizei in ganz Österreich. Sie starb im Jahre 1780 in Wien, die einzige weibliche Regel Dynastie der Habsburger, die seit 650 Jahren. Ihr Sohn Joseph II. war ihr Nachfolger.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Maria Teresa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Arciduchessa d'Austria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Teresa è stata la figlia maggiore di Elisabeth Christine di Brunswick - Wolfenbuttel e Carlo VI, che hanno permesso di riuscire Monarchia degli Asburgo. La sua transizione verso il trono, ma è stato tutto semplice. Opposizione alla sua successione al trono ha portato alla guerra di successione austriaca nel 1740. Dopo l'imperatore Carlo VII, che hanno rivendicato il trono, morì nel 1745, Maria Teresa rivendicato il trono di suo marito, Francesco I. Era tecnicamente l'imperatrice consorte, ma de facto, è stato il dominatore della nazione. Nel 1745, ha iniziato Styling anche se stessa come il Sacro Romano imperatrice. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Maria Teresa contribuito a cominciare finanziaria e le riforme educative, di promozione del commercio, dell'agricoltura, e riorganizzato l'esercito. Molte delle sue azioni rafforzato l'Austria nel suo complesso e delle sue risorse. Dopo un continuo conflitto con la Prussia, il Sette Anni 'Guerra e infine alla guerra di successione bavarese. Ella divenne il dowager imperatrice dopo la morte di Francesco e la successione del figlio Giuseppe come imperatore nel 1765. Maria Teresa unità portato alla Habsburg Monarchia ed è considerato uno dei più dotati governanti. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Mentre Baviera e la Francia pone una continua minaccia per l'Austria, è stato Federico il Grande, che è diventato il principale nemico Maria durante il suo regno. Maria Teresa concentrata la maggior parte della sua politica verso la sconfitta o di Prussia. A causa di queste riforme, il trattato di Aix -la Chapelle - Paesi Bassi ha dato l'austriaco torna a Maria Teresa. In cambio, Maria ceduto Parma, Piacenza e Guastalla a Filippo Infante di Spagna. Dopo essere stato sconfitto nella prima e seconda guerra Silesiana, Maria Teresa ha iniziato a modernizzare il suo regno con l'assistenza di Freidrich Wilhelm von Gaugwitz. Molte delle sue riforme, ha aumentato le dimensioni dell 'esercito del 200% e un aumento delle imposte per garantire un reddito stabile per il militare. Ha anche centralizzato combinando il governo austriaco e boemo cancellerie in un ufficio amministrativo. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Come altri Asburgo, Maria Teresa era una devota cattolica romana. E 'stata istruita da gesuiti a Mariazell, e più tardi nella vita è stata breve pessimismo dei religiosi di altre cifre reali del suo tempo. La sua prospettiva conservatrice ha coinvolto una scarsa considerazione di altre fedi. NEL 1741, ha espulso il popolo ebraico di Praga. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Maria Teresa abbandonato la Gran Bretagna come un alleato e si allearono con la Russia e la Francia. Quando ha sentito il suo esercito è stato abbastanza forte, ha preparato un attacco alla Prussia nel 1756. Tuttavia, è stato Federico II, che hanno attaccato in primo luogo, invadendo Sassonia e di partenza dei Sette Anni 'guerra. Quando Maria Teresa firmato il trattato di Hubertsburg nel 1763, la guerra si è conclusa Prussia riconoscere come il proprietario della maggior parte della Slesia. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Dopo la morte del marito nel 1765, Maria Teresa divenne separato dal suo popolo. Cambiato la sua attenzione per il mantenimento della pace, piuttosto che riconquistare la Slesia. Ha il nome di suo figlio, Giuseppe II, come coregent e imperatore. Tuttavia, egli ha ricevuto poteri limitati, perché ha ritenuto che fosse troppo arroganti per la piena responsabilità. Nel 1767, Maria Teresa è stato infettato con il vaiolo. Tuttavia, è guarita ed è diventato un grande sostenitore di inoculazione. Nel suo anno più tardi, ha focalizzato sulla riforma delle leggi sulla falsariga di assolutismo illuminato. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Nel 1771, lei e Giuseppe II del brevetto rilasciato a Robot, una riforma che regolamentato il serf di pagamenti nella sua terre. Altre riforme che proibisce la strega - inclusa la combustione e la tortura, la pena capitale e tenendo spento il codice penale. Nel 1772, Maria Teresa fondata Imperiale e Reale Accademia di Scienza e Letteratura, a Bruxelles. L'istruzione obbligatoria è stata introdotta nel 1774 al fine di formare una classe di cittadini istruiti, da cui i dipendenti pubblici sono stati assunti. Maria Teresa continuato rilascio varie leggi di polizia in tutta l'Austria. Morì nel 1780 a Vienna, essendo l'unica donna a governare la dinastia Asburgo, che è durata 650 anni. Suo figlio Giuseppe II è stato il suo successore.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]María Teresa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Archiduquesa de Austria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]María Teresa era la hija mayor de Christine Elisabeth de Brunswick Wolfenbuttel - y el emperador Carlos VI, que le ha permitido tener éxito la monarquía Habsburgo. Su transición al trono, pero era todo sencillo. La oposición a su sucesión al trono llevaron a la Guerra de la Sucesión de Austria en 1740. Después el emperador Carlos VII, que ha reivindicado el trono, murió en 1745, María Teresa reclamado el trono de su marido, Francisco I. Ella era técnicamente la emperatriz consorte, pero de hecho fue el gobernante de la nación. En 1745, ella comenzó también a sí misma como el estilo Holy Roman Empress. [APARTADO: 1] María Teresa ayudó a comenzar financiera y las reformas de la educación, promueve el comercio, la agricultura, y reorganizó el ejército. Muchas de sus acciones de fortalecimiento de Austria en su conjunto y de sus recursos. Después de un continuo conflicto con Prusia, el Seven Years' War y finalmente a la Guerra de la Sucesión Bávara. Se convirtió en la dowager emperatriz después de la muerte de Francisco y de la sucesión de su hijo Joseph como emperador en 1765. Maria Theresa trajo unidad a la monarquía Habsburgo, y se considera uno de sus más talentosos gobernantes. [APARTADO: 1] Si bien Bavaria y Francia que plantea una amenaza continua para Austria, es Federico el Grande, quien se convirtió en su principal enemigo Maria durante su reinado. Maria Theresa centrado la mayoría de sus políticas hacia la derrota o Prusia. Debido a estas reformas, el Tratado de Aix la Chapelle - dieron la vuelta a los Países Bajos de Austria Maria Theresa. A cambio, cedió Maria Parma, Piacenza y Guastalla para el Infante Felipe de España. Después de ser derrotado en la Primera y Segunda Guerras de Silesia, Maria Theresa comenzó a modernizar su reino con la ayuda de Freidrich Wilhelm Graf Von Gaugwitz. Muchas de sus reformas, que aumentó el tamaño del ejército en un 200% y un aumento de los impuestos para garantizar un ingreso constante para los militares. También centralizada por el gobierno austriaco y la combinación de las cancillerías de Bohemia en una oficina administrativa. [APARTADO: 1] Al igual que otros Habsburgo, María Teresa fue un devoto católico romano. Fue educado por los jesuitas en Mariazell, y más tarde en la vida es corta pesimismo de los religiosos de otras cifras reales de su tiempo. Su visión conservadora que participan una mala opinión de otros credos. EN 1741, que expulsó a los judíos de Praga. [APARTADO: 1] Maria Theresa disminuyó Gran Bretaña como aliado y aliados a sí misma con Rusia y Francia. Cuando ella sentía su ejército era lo suficientemente fuerte, se preparó un ataque a Prusia en 1756. Sin embargo, se Frederick II que atacaron primero, invadiendo Sajonia y de iniciar el Seven Years' War. Maria Theresa Cuando firmaron el Tratado de Hubertsburg en 1763, la guerra terminó reconociendo Prusia como propietario de la mayor parte de Silesia. [APARTADO: 1] Después de la muerte de su marido en 1765, María Teresa se convirtió separada de su pueblo. Su cambiado de enfoque para el mantenimiento de la paz, en lugar de recuperar Silesia. Ella nombró a su hijo, Joseph II, como coregent y Emperador. Sin embargo, recibió poderes limitados porque ella sentía que él era demasiado altivo para la plena responsabilidades. En 1767, María Teresa fue infectada con la viruela. Sin embargo, se recuperó y se convirtió en un firme defensor de la inoculación. En sus últimos años, se ha centrado en la reforma de las leyes a lo largo de las líneas de absolutismo ilustrado. [APARTADO: 1] En 1771, ella y José II a los robots de Patentes, una reforma que regula el siervo de los pagos en sus tierras. Otras reformas incluyen la prohibición de la quema de brujas y la tortura, y teniendo frente a la pena capital del Código Penal. En 1772, Maria Theresa Imperial y fundó la Real Academia de Ciencias y Literatura en Bruselas. La educación obligatoria se introdujo en 1774 con el fin de formar una clase de educación de los ciudadanos, a partir de la cual los funcionarios públicos han sido contratados. Maria Theresa siguió la emisión de diferentes leyes de policía en toda Austria. Murió en 1780 en Viena, al ser la única mujer a la regla la dinastía Habsburgo, que duró 650 años. Su hijo Joseph II fue su sucesor.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MAXIMILIAN</Tag>
		<English>Maximilian I</English>
		<French>Maximilien Ier</French>
		<German>Maximilian I.</German>
		<Italian>Massimiliano I</Italian>
		<Spanish>Maximiliano I</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MAXIMILIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Maximilian I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Holy Roman Emperor[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1459 - 1519


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Maximilian I.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Heiliger Römischer Kaiser[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 1459-1519</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_GUSTAVUS</Tag>
		<English>Gustav Vasa</English>
		<French>Gustave Vasa</French>
		<German>Gustav Wasa</German>
		<Italian>Gustavo Vasa</Italian>
		<Spanish>Gustavo Vasa</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_GUSTAVUS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Gustav I Vasa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Sweden, Father of the Swedish nation[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] May 12, 1496 - September 29, 1560[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB][PARAGRAPH:1]Gustav I, born Gustav Eriksson (Colloquial 15th century Upplandic, G&#246;sta Jerksson) and later known as Gustav Vasa, was King of Sweden from 1523 until his death. He was the first monarch of the House of Vasa, an influential noble family which came to be the royal house of Sweden for much of the 16th and 17th centuries. Gustav I was elected regent in 1521 after leading a rebellion against Christian II of Denmark, the leader of the Kalmar Union who controlled most of Sweden at the time.[PARAGRAPH:1] Gustav was an enigmatic person who has been referred to as both a liberator of the country and as a tyrannical ruler, which has made him the subject of many books. When he came to power in 1523, he was largely unknown, and he became the ruler of a still divided country without a central government. Though not as famous as most of his continental contemporaries, he became the first truly autocratic native Swedish sovereign and was a skilled propagandist and bureaucrat who laid the foundations for a more efficient centralized government. During his reign Protestantism was introduced in the country. In traditional Swedish history he has been labelled the founder of modern Sweden, and the "father of the nation". Gustav liked to compare himself to Moses, whom he believed to have also liberated his people and established a state. As a person, Gustav was known for ruthless methods and a bad temperament, but he also loved music, and had a certain sly wit.[PARAGRAPH:1] Gustav was born in Lindholmen, Sweden to a noble family, and was educated at the University of Uppsala. As a young man he entered the army, and from 1518 to 1519 he fought against Christian II, king of Denmark, who had invaded Sweden to regain the throne that the Danes had lost in 1501. Gustav was taken hostage but managed to escape. He was still a fugitive when he heard that Christian had massacred his father and other nationalist Swedish nobles in the Stockholm bloodbath of 1520. From 1521 to 1523, with an army of peasants, Gustav led a successful revolt and drove the Danes out of Sweden. His victory resulted in the dissolution of the Union of Kalmar, which in 1397 had placed Sweden and Norway under the Danish crown. Gustav was administrator of the kingdom from 1521 to 1523, when the Riksdag, or national assembly, elected him king. He strengthened his political hold and restored order by introducing the Reformation into Sweden. The Roman Catholic church had supported Christian II, and Gustav used this as an excuse for stripping the church of political power and confiscating its property. In 1527 he made Swedish bishops subject to royal power, and in 1529 he proclaimed Lutheranism the state religion. He joined with Norway in 1537 to defeat the German city of L&#220;beck, making Sweden economically independent of the Hanseatic League, a federation of German cities to enhance their commercial interests. Gustav created a strongly united state by introducing a sound financial administration, strengthening manufacturing, trade, and agricultural interests, and increasing the military forces. In 1544 he made the Swedish crown hereditary through his line, the house of Vasa. On his death, Gustav was succeeded by his son, Eric XIV.[PARAGRAPH:1] Gustav's heritage has been disputed. In 19th century Swedish history a folklore developed wherein Gustav was supposed to have had all kinds of adventures when he liberated Sweden from the Danes. The memory of Gustav has been honored greatly, resulting in embroidered history books, commemorative coins, and the annual ski event Vasaloppet (the largest ski event in the world with 15,000 participants). The city of Vaasa in Finland was named after the royal house of Vasa in 1606. Gustav is currently portrayed on the 1000 kronor note. Today most of these stories are considered to have no other foundation than legend and skilful propaganda by Gustav himself during his time. Gustav has been regarded by some as a power-hungry man who wished to control everything: the Church, the economy, the army and all foreign affairs. But in doing this, he also did manage to unite Sweden, a country that previously had no standardized language, and where individual provinces held a strong regional power. He also laid the foundation for Sweden's professional army that was to make Sweden into a regional superpower in the 17th century.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Gustav Wasa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König von Schweden[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 12. Mai 1496 - 29. September 1560[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB][PARAGRAPH:1]Gustav I. von Schweden wurde als Gustav Eriksson am 12. Mai 1496 geboren und ein Nachkomme einer edlen Familie. Während des schwedisch-dänischen Krieges führte Gustav die siegreiche Rebellion gegen die Dänen und wurde am 6. Juni 1523 zum König ernannt. Während seiner Regierung stand er vielen Aufständen in seinem Land gegenüber. Außerdem wurde der Protestantismus in diesem Zeitalter in Schweden eingeführt. Gustav I. starb am 29. September 1560, und wurde in der Kathedrale von Uppsala begraben. Ungeachtet der Tatsache, dass er autark und im Ausführen seiner Macht absolut war, ist es anerkannt, dass er der Gründer des modernen Schwedens war.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_THE_POPE</Tag>
		<English>The Pope</English>
		<French>Le Pape</French>
		<German>Der Papst</German>
		<Italian>Il Papa</Italian>
		<Spanish>El Papa</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_THE_POPE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]The Pope[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Bishop of Rome[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2:1]In the seventh century AD, Rome was under the nominal control of the Eastern Roman Empire, based in Constantinople. The Byzantines were unable or unwilling to protect the city from the growing Lombardian menace to the north, and more or less by default control of the city fell to the Catholic Bishop of Rome (who would later be titled "Pope"), the richest and most powerful man in the region. [PARAGRAPH:1]Using a cunning mixture of bribery as well as political and diplomatic power the Bishops had managed to keep the barbarians from the city, but the Lombardian pressure was increasing. Failing to get adequate aid from the Byzantines, the Bishops were forced to seek protection elsewhere. Pope Stephen II turned to Pepin the Short, a Frankish king who had just reunited the Frankish states. In exchange for the Church's sanction to Pepin's conquests, Pepin invaded Italy and drove the Lombards from Rome's gates. He also donated much of the captured land surrounding Rome to the Pope, greatly increasing the size of the Pope's holdings and creating the Papal States.[PARAGRAPH:1]In one stroke, the Pope had driven off the invaders and found a powerful counter to far-away Byzantine. The alliance between the Church and the Carolingians would be further cemented in 800 AD, when Pope Leo III crowned Pepin's son, Charlemagne, the first Emperor of the Holy Roman Empire.</English>
		<French>[H1]Le Pape[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ev&#234;que de Rome[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2:1]Au VIIe si&#232;cle, Rome &#233;tait symboliquement sous le contr&#244;le de l'Empire romain d'Orient, gouvern&#233; de Constantinople. Les Byzantins n'&#233;taient pas en mesure ? ou ne voulaient pas ? prot&#233;ger la ville de la menace grandissante que repr&#233;sentaient les Lombards au nord et Rome se trouva plac&#233;e sous l'autorit&#233; de son &#233;v&#234;que catholique (qui recevra plus tard le titre de "pape"), l'homme le plus puissant et le plus riche de la r&#233;gion.[PARAGRAPH:1]En m&#234;lant habilement la corruption aux manoeuvres politiques et diplomatiques, les &#233;v&#234;ques de Rome avaient r&#233;ussi &#224; tenir les barbares &#224; l'&#233;cart de la ville, mais les Lombards renfor&#231;aient leur pr&#233;sence. Comme les Byzantins ne leur apportaient pas l'aide n&#233;cessaire, les &#233;v&#234;ques furent oblig&#233;s d'aller chercher une protection ailleurs. Le pape Etienne II fit appel &#224; P&#233;pin le Bref, un roi franc qui venait de r&#233;unir les territoires francs. En &#233;change du consentement de l'Eglise pour ses conqu&#234;tes, P&#233;pin envahit l'Italie, chassa les Lombards arriv&#233;s aux portes de Rome et restitua au pape une grande partie des terres conquises autour de Rome. Il augmenta ainsi consid&#233;rablement les terres du pape et donna naissance aux Etats pontificaux.[PARAGRAPH:1]D'un seul coup, le pape avait repouss&#233; les envahisseurs et trouv&#233; un puissant rempart contre les Byzantins. L'alliance entre l'Eglise et les Carolingiens fut renforc&#233;e en 800 quand le pape L&#233;on III couronna Charlemagne, fils de P&#233;pin, premier empereur du Saint Empire romain.</French>
		<German>[H1]Der Papst[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Bischof von Rom[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2:1]Im 7. Jahrhundert n. Chr. stand Rom unter der Vorherrschaft des Ostr&#246;mischen Reiches, dessen Zentrum Konstantinopel war. Die Byzantiner waren nicht in der Lage oder willens, die Stadt vor der wachsenden Bedrohung durch die Langobarden im Norden zu besch&#252;tzen, und so fiel durch dieses Vers&#228;umnis die Kontrolle &#252;ber die Stadt an den katholischen Bischof von Rom, der sp&#228;ter den Titel Papst verliehen bekam und der reichste und m&#228;chtigste Mann der Region war.[PARAGRAPH:1] Durch eine geschickte Mischung aus Bestechung und politischer wie diplomatischer Macht konnten die Bisch&#246;fe die Barbaren aus der Stadt fernhalten, doch der Druck der Langobarden stieg stetig. Da von den Byzantinern keine ad&#228;quate Hilfe zu erwarten war, mussten sich die Bisch&#246;fe anderweitig um Hilfe bem&#252;hen. Papst Stephan II. wandte sich an Pippin den Kurzen, einen Frankenk&#246;nig, der erst kurz zuvor die fr&#228;nkischen Territorien vereint hatte. Als Gegenleistung f&#252;r die kirchliche Unterst&#252;tzung seiner Eroberungen, fiel Pippin in Italien ein und vertrieb die Langobarden, die bereits vor den Toren Roms standen. Er vermachte auch einen Gro&#223;teil der eingenommenen L&#228;ndereien um Rom dem Papst, wodurch er den kirchlichen Grundbesitz erheblich steigerte und die Grundlagen f&#252;r den Kirchenstaat legte.[PARAGRAPH:1]Mit einem Schlag hatte der Papst die Eindringlinge in die Flucht schlagen und gleichzeitig ein m&#228;chtiges Gegengewicht zum fernen Byzanz gefunden. Die Allianz zwischen der Kirche und den Karolingern wurde im Jahre 800 n. Chr. weiter gefestigt, als Papst Leo III. Pippins Sohn, Karl den Gro&#223;en, zum ersten Kaiser des Heiligen R&#246;mischen Reiches kr&#246;nte.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Il Papa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Il vescovo di Roma[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2:1]Durante il settimo secolo d.C. Roma era sotto il controllo nominale dell'Impero Romano d'Oriente, basato a Costantinopoli. I Bizantini erano incapaci o non intenzionati a proteggere la citt&#224; dalla crescente minaccia longobarda, a nord, e pi&#249; o meno automaticamente il controllo della citt&#224; ricadde sul vescovo cattolico di Roma (che pi&#249; tardi verr&#224; chiamato "papa"), il pi&#249; ricco e potente uomo della regione. [PARAGRAPH:1]Usando un'abile combinazione di corruzione e potere diplomatico e politico i vescovi erano riusciti a mantenere i barbari lontani dalla citt&#224;, ma la pressione longobarda stava aumentando. Incapaci di ottenere aiuti adeguati da Bisanzio, i vescovi furono costretti a cercare protezione altrove. Papa Stefano II si rivolse a Pipino il Breve, un re che aveva appena riunito gli Stati franchi. In cambio della ratifica delle sue conquiste da parte della chiesa, Pipino invase l'Italia e cacci&#242; i Longobardi dalle porte di Roma. Don&#242; anche gran parte dei territori catturati attorno a Roma al papa, aumentando di molto la dimensione dei possedimenti papali e creando lo Stato Pontificio.[PARAGRAPH:1]In un colpo solo il papa aveva cacciato gli invasori e trovato un potente alleato contro la lontana Bisanzio. L'alleanza tra la chiesa e i Carolingi sarebbe stata ulteriormente cementata nell'800 d.C., quando papa Leone III incoron&#242; il figlio di Pipino, Carlo Magno, primo imperatore del Sacro Romano Impero.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]El Papa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Obispo de Roma[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2:1]En el siglo VII d. C., Roma se encontraba nominalmente sometida a la autoridad del Imperio Romano de oriente, con capital en Constantinopla. Los bizantinos, ya sea por debilidad o por desidia, no pudieron proteger a la ciudad de la creciente amenaza lombarda procedente del norte y, de este modo, poco a poco, la ciudad fue cayendo bajo la autoridad de su obispo cat&#243;lico (quien m&#225;s tarde recibir&#237;a el t&#237;tulo de "Papa"), el hombre m&#225;s rico y poderoso de la regi&#243;n. [PARAGRAPH:1]Empleando una mezcla de soborno, poder pol&#237;tico y diplomacia, los obispos de Roma hab&#237;an logrado mantener a raya a los b&#225;rbaros, pero la presi&#243;n de los lombardos estaba aumentando. Al ver que los bizantinos no pod&#237;an o no quer&#237;an prestar la ayuda que la ciudad necesitaba, los obispos tuvieron que buscarla en otra parte. El Papa Esteban II recurri&#243; a Pipino el Breve, un franco que acababa de reunificar todas las tierras de este pueblo. A cambio de la sanci&#243;n de la Iglesia a sus conquistas, Pipino invadi&#243; Italia y alej&#243; a los lombardos de las puertas de Roma. A continuaci&#243;n don&#243; al Papa gran parte de las tierras capturadas en las proximidades de Roma, lo que, adem&#225;s de incrementar enormemente sus posesiones, le permiti&#243; fundar los Estados Pontificios.[PARAGRAPH:1]De un solo golpe, el Papa hab&#237;a expulsado a los invasores y encontrado un poderoso contrapeso frente a la lejana Bizancio. La alianza entre la Iglesia y los carolingios se reforzar&#237;a a&#250;n m&#225;s en el a&#241;o 800 d. C., cuando el Papa Le&#243;n III coronara al hijo de Pipino, Carlomagno, como primer emperador del Sacro Imperio Romano.</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_GEORGE_III</Tag>
		<English>George III</English>
		<French>George III</French>
		<German>Georg III.</German>
		<Italian>Giorgio III</Italian>
		<Spanish>Jorge III</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_GEORGE_III_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]George III[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Great Brittain, King of Ireland[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] June 4, 1738 - January 29, 1820 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>not yet</French>
		<German>not yet</German>
		<Italian>not yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>not yet</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HAAKON_IV</Tag>
		<English>Haakon Haakonson</English>
		<French>Haakon Haakonson</French>
		<German>Haakon Haakonson</German>
		<Italian>Haakon Haakonson</Italian>
		<Spanish>Haakon Haakonson</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HAAKON_IV_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Haakon Haakonson[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Norway[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1217 - 1263 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>not yet</French>
		<German>not yet</German>
		<Italian>not yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>not yet</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MARIA_II</Tag>
		<English>Maria II</English>
		<French>Marie II</French>
		<German>Maria II.</German>
		<Italian>Maria II</Italian>
		<Spanish>Maria II</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MARIA_II_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Maria II[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Queen regnant  of Portugal[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] April 4, 1819 - November 15, 1853 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>not yet</French>
		<German>not yet</German>
		<Italian>not yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>not yet</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ANDREA_DANDOLO</Tag>
		<English>Andrea Dandolo</English>
		<French>Andrea Dandolo</French>
		<German>Andrea Dandolo</German>
		<Italian>Andrea Dandolo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Andrea Dandolo</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ANDREA_DANDOLO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Andrea Dandolo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]54th Doge of Venice[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1306 - September 7, 1354 AD


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD]
	No background yet.</English>
		<French>not yet</French>
		<German>not yet</German>
		<Italian>not yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>not yet</Spanish>
		<Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_INDEPENDENT</Tag>
		<English>Independent Leader</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Dirigeant ind&#233;pendant</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Unabh&#228;ngigen-Staatsoberhaupt</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Leader indipendente</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>L&#237;der aut&#243;nomo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#203;&#232;&#228;&#229;&#240; &#205;&#229;&#231;&#224;&#226;&#232;&#241;&#232;&#236;&#251;&#245; </Russian>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
