<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit Upgrades for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWEDEN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Swedish</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Les Su&#233;dois</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Schweden:Die Schweden:den Schweden</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Male:Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1:1:1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>I Persiani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Los Persas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#216;&#226;&#229;&#228;&#251;</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWEDEN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Sweden</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Su&#232;de</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Schweden</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Persia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Persia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#216;&#226;&#229;&#246;&#232;&#255;</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWEDEN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Swedish</English>
		<French>
			<Text>su&#233;dois:su&#233;doise:su&#233;dois:su&#233;doises</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Schwedisch:schwedischen:schwedische</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>persiano:persiana:persiani:persiane</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>persa:persa:persas:persas</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
		<Russian>&#216;&#226;&#229;&#228;&#241;&#234;&#232;&#233;</Russian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE00</Tag>
		<English>Swedish Peoples</English>
		<French>Peuplade Su&#233;doise</French>
		<German>Schwedische Völker</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE01</Tag>
		<English>Kingdom of Sweden</English>
		<French>Royaume de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Königreich Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE02</Tag>
		<English>Swedish Empire</English>
		<French>Empire Su&#233;dois</French>
		<German>Schwedisches Reich</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE03</Tag>
		<English>Kingdom of Sweden</English>
		<French>Royaume de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Königreich Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE04</Tag>
		<English>Swedish Empire</English>
		<French>Empire Su&#233;dois</French>
		<German>Schwedisches Reich</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE05</Tag>
		<English>Republic of Sweden</English>
		<French>R&#233;publique de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Republik Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE06</Tag>
		<English>Placeholder Error</English>
		<French>Placeholder Error</French>
		<German>Placeholder Error</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE07</Tag>
		<English>Placeholder Error</English>
		<French>Placeholder Error</French>
		<German>Placeholder Error</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE08</Tag>
		<English>Sultanate of Sweden</English>
		<French>Sultanat de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Sultanat Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE09</Tag>
		<English>Islamic Republic of Sweden</English>
		<French>R&#233;publique Islamique de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Islamische Republik Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE10</Tag>
		<English>Exarchate of Suedia</English>
		<French>Exarchate de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Exarchat Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE11</Tag>
		<English>Duchy of Sweden</English>
		<French>Duch&#233; de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Herzogtum Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE12</Tag>
		<English>Emirate of Sweden</English>
		<French>Emirat de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Emirat Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE13</Tag>
		<English>Spanish Kingdom of Sweden</English>
		<French>Royaume Espagnol de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Spanisches Königreich Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE14</Tag>
		<English>Kalmar Sweden</English>
		<French>Su&#232;de Kalmar</French>
		<German>Kalmar Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE15</Tag>
		<English>Venetian Sweden</English>
		<French>Su&#232;de V&#233;nitienne</French>
		<German>Venezianisch-Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE16</Tag>
		<English>Russian Sweden</English>
		<French>Su&#232;de Russe</French>
		<German>Russisch-Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE17</Tag>
		<English>German Sweden</English>
		<French>Su&#232;de Allemande</French>
		<German>Deutsch-Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE18</Tag>
		<English>Counties of Sweden</English>
		<French>Comt&#233;s de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Counties Schwedens</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE19</Tag>
		<English>Habsburg Sweden</English>
		<French>Su&#232;de Habsbourg</French>
		<German>Habsburger Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE20</Tag>
		<English>Principality of Isves</English>
		<French>Principaut&#233; de Isves</French>
		<German>Fürstentum Isves</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DN_SWE21</Tag>
		<English>Province of Sweden</English>
		<French>Province de Su&#232;de</French>
		<German>Provinz Schweden</German>
		<Italian/><Spanish/><Russian/>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_GUSTAVUS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Gustav I Vasa[\H1]
[BOLD]King of Sweden, Father of the Swedish nation[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] May 12, 1496 - September 29, 1560


	[BOLD]Background:[\BOLD
	Gustav I, born Gustav Eriksson (Colloquial 15th century Upplandic, G&#246;sta Jerksson) and later known as Gustav Vasa, was King of Sweden from 1523 until his death. He was the first monarch of the House of Vasa, an influential noble family which came to be the royal house of Sweden for much of the 16th and 17th centuries. Gustav I was elected regent in 1521 after leading a rebellion against Christian II of Denmark, the leader of the Kalmar Union who controlled most of Sweden at the time.
[TAB]Gustav was an enigmatic person who has been referred to as both a liberator of the country and as a tyrannical ruler, which has made him the subject of many books. When he came to power in 1523, he was largely unknown, and he became the ruler of a still divided country without a central government. Though not as famous as most of his continental contemporaries, he became the first truly autocratic native Swedish sovereign and was a skilled propagandist and bureaucrat who laid the foundations for a more efficient centralized government. During his reign Protestantism was introduced in the country. In traditional Swedish history he has been labelled the founder of modern Sweden, and the "father of the nation". Gustav liked to compare himself to Moses, whom he believed to have also liberated his people and established a state. As a person, Gustav was known for ruthless methods and a bad temperament, but he also loved music, and had a certain sly wit.
[TAB]Gustav was born in Lindholmen, Sweden to a noble family, and was educated at the University of Uppsala. As a young man he entered the army, and from 1518 to 1519 he fought against Christian II, king of Denmark, who had invaded Sweden to regain the throne that the Danes had lost in 1501. Gustav was taken hostage but managed to escape. He was still a fugitive when he heard that Christian had massacred his father and other nationalist Swedish nobles in the Stockholm bloodbath of 1520. From 1521 to 1523, with an army of peasants, Gustav led a successful revolt and drove the Danes out of Sweden. His victory resulted in the dissolution of the Union of Kalmar, which in 1397 had placed Sweden and Norway under the Danish crown. Gustav was administrator of the kingdom from 1521 to 1523, when the Riksdag, or national assembly, elected him king. He strengthened his political hold and restored order by introducing the Reformation into Sweden. The Roman Catholic church had supported Christian II, and Gustav used this as an excuse for stripping the church of political power and confiscating its property. In 1527 he made Swedish bishops subject to royal power, and in 1529 he proclaimed Lutheranism the state religion. He joined with Norway in 1537 to defeat the German city of L&#220;beck, making Sweden economically independent of the Hanseatic League, a federation of German cities to enhance their commercial interests. Gustav created a strongly united state by introducing a sound financial administration, strengthening manufacturing, trade, and agricultural interests, and increasing the military forces. In 1544 he made the Swedish crown hereditary through his line, the house of Vasa. On his death, Gustav was succeeded by his son, Eric XIV.
[TAB]Gustav's heritage has been disputed. In 19th century Swedish history a folklore developed wherein Gustav was supposed to have had all kinds of adventures when he liberated Sweden from the Danes. The memory of Gustav has been honored greatly, resulting in embroidered history books, commemorative coins, and the annual ski event Vasaloppet (the largest ski event in the world with 15,000 participants). The city of Vaasa in Finland was named after the royal house of Vasa in 1606. Gustav is currently portrayed on the 1000 kronor note. Today most of these stories are considered to have no other foundation than legend and skilful propaganda by Gustav himself during his time. Gustav has been regarded by some as a power-hungry man who wished to control everything: the Church, the economy, the army and all foreign affairs. But in doing this, he also did manage to unite Sweden, a country that previously had no standardized language, and where individual provinces held a strong regional power. He also laid the foundation for Sweden's professional army that was to make Sweden into a regional superpower in the 17th century.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[H1]Gustav Wasa[\H1]
[BOLD]König von Schweden[\BOLD]
[BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 12. Mai 1496 - 29. September 1560


	[BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD]
	Gustav I. von Schweden wurde als Gustav Eriksson am 12. Mai 1496 geboren und ein Nachkomme einer edlen Familie. Während des schwedisch-dänischen Krieges führte Gustav die siegreiche Rebellion gegen die Dänen und wurde am 6. Juni 1523 zum König ernannt. Während seiner Regierung stand er vielen Aufständen in seinem Land gegenüber. Außerdem wurde der Protestantismus in diesem Zeitalter in Schweden eingeführt. Gustav I. starb am 29. September 1560, und wurde in der Kathedrale von Uppsala begraben. Ungeachtet der Tatsache, dass er autark und im Ausführen seiner Macht absolut war, ist es anerkannt, dass er der Gründer des modernen Schwedens war.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>	
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
