<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by XMLSPY 2004 Professional Ed. Release 2, Installed Multi + SMP for 3 users (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text Objects -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPEARMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Since a Medieval spear required only a small amount of steel along the sharpened edges, it was an economical weapon. Quick to manufacture, and needing less smithing skill than a sword, it became the common weapon of the peasantry in many parts of the world. With the rise of heavy cavalry, spear shafts began to be planted against the ground to deter charging cavalry. Spears morphed into different pole-arms as mounted knights became more important on the battlefields of Europe and a means to counter them was needed.</English>
		<French>Depuis le moyen-age, les lances exig&#233;es seulement une petite quantit&#233; d'acier le long des bords aiguis&#233;s, il s'agissait d'une arme &#233;conomique. Rapide &#224; fabriquer, et n&#233;cessitant moins d'habilet&#233; forge d'un sabre, il est devenu l'arme commune de la paysannerie dans de nombreuses r&#233;gions du monde. Avec la mont&#233;e de la cavalerie lourde, les lances ont commenc&#233; &#224; &#234;tre plant&#233;s sur le sol pour emp&#234;cher la cavalerie. Ces lances sont devenus de plus en plus important sur les champs de bataille d'Europe.</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Since a Medieval spear required only a small amount of steel along the sharpened edges, it was an economical weapon. Quick to manufacture, and needing less smithing skill than a sword, it became the common weapon of the peasantry in many parts of the world. With the rise of heavy cavalry, spear shafts began to be planted against the ground to deter charging cavalry. Spears morphed into different pole-arms as mounted knights became more important on the battlefields of Europe and a means to counter them was needed.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GUISARME_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A guisarme was a pole weapon used in Europe to dismount knights and horsemen, primarily between 1000-1400. Like most polearms it was developed by peasants by combining hand tools with long poles: in this case by putting a pruning hook onto a spear shaft. Later designs implemented a small reverse spike on the back of the blade, increasing the weapon's stopping power. Eventually hooks were incorporated into a variety of different polearms and guisarme became a catch-all for any weapon that included a hook on the blade.</English>
		<French>Un Guisarme &#233;tait une arme utilis&#233;es en Europe pour mettre pied &#224; terre les chevaliers et les cavaliers, surtout entre 1000-1400. Comme la plupart des armes d'hast il a &#233;t&#233; d&#233;velopp&#233; par des paysans en combinant des outils &#224; main avec de longues perches: dans ce cas en mettant une serpette sur un axe de lance. Derniers mod&#232;les mis en oeuvre, un petit clou sur le dos de la lame qui permit l'augmentation du pouvoir d'arr&#234;t de l'arme. </French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>A guisarme was a pole weapon used in Europe to dismount knights and horsemen, primarily between 1000-1400. Like most polearms it was developed by peasants by combining hand tools with long poles: in this case by putting a pruning hook onto a spear shaft. Later designs implemented a small reverse spike on the back of the blade, increasing the weapon's stopping power. Eventually hooks were incorporated into a variety of different polearms and guisarme became a catch-all for any weapon that included a hook on the blade.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PIKEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Early in the middle ages, the pike was only useful on defense; its length made it difficult for untrained soldiers to use in formation. The Swiss brought a renaissance to pike warfare in the 15th century, with strong training regimens and drummers to aid coordination. Now pike blocks could both rise to the attack and go into an impenetrable defensive formation when attacked by cavalry. The deep pike attack column remained an essential part of infantry combat for several hundred years.</English>
		<French>Au d&#233;but du Moyen Age, le piquier a &#233;t&#233; utile que sur la d&#233;fense, et sa longueur, il &#233;tait difficile pour les soldats non entraîn&#233;s &#224; utiliser en formation. Les suisses ont lanc&#233; une renaissance du piquier avec la guerre au 15&#232;me si&#232;cle, avec des sch&#233;mas de formation solide et des batteurs de coordination de l'aide. Les piquiers pouvait &#224; la fois &#234;tre utiliser &#224; l'attaque et aller dans une formation d&#233;fensive imp&#233;n&#233;trable quand on est attaqu&#233; par la cavalerie. En definitive les piquiers sont rest&#233;es un &#233;l&#233;ment essentiel du combat d'infanterie pour plusieurs centaines d'ann&#233;es.</French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Early in the middle ages, the pike was only useful on defense; its length made it difficult for untrained soldiers to use in formation. The Swiss brought a renaissance to pike warfare in the 15th century, with strong training regimens and drummers to aid coordination. Now pike blocks could both rise to the attack and go into an impenetrable defensive formation when attacked by cavalry. The deep pike attack column remained an essential part of infantry combat for several hundred years.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SWORDSMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Swords in antiquity and classical times tended to be relatively short, at first because they were made of bronze and later because they were rarely called upon to penetrate armor. The blade of the classic Roman stabbing sword, the gladius, was only some two feet long, though in the twilight years of the empire the gladius gave way to the spatha, the long slashing sword of the barbarians and forerunner of the great broadswords of medieval Europe. During the Early Middle Ages, European swords tended to be long and straight, with no crossguard to protect the wielder's hand.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Swords in antiquity and classical times tended to be relatively short, at first because they were made of bronze and later because they were rarely called upon to penetrate armor. The blade of the classic Roman stabbing sword, the gladius, was only some two feet long, though in the twilight years of the empire the gladius gave way to the spatha, the long slashing sword of the barbarians and forerunner of the great broadswords of medieval Europe. During the Early Middle Ages, European swords tended to be long and straight, with no crossguard to protect the wielder's hand.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LONG_SWORDSMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Longsword is a type of European sword used during the late medieval period. Made to counter the increasingly strong armor of the time, the longsword was commonly held in combat with both hands, though some may be used single-handed. A man-at-arms or dismounted knight fighting with a longsword would also have worn substantial other armor, such as a mail hauberk and helm. The terms "hand-and-a-half sword", "greatsword", and "bastard sword" are used colloquially to refer to longswords in general.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>The Longsword is a type of European sword used during the late medieval period. Made to counter the increasingly strong armor of the time, the longsword was commonly held in combat with both hands, though some may be used single-handed. A man-at-arms or dismounted knight fighting with a longsword would also have worn substantial other armor, such as a mail hauberk and helm. The terms "hand-and-a-half sword", "greatsword", and "bastard sword" are used colloquially to refer to longswords in general.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SCOUT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Light cavalry have been employed as scouts and skirmisher from ancient times. The only real requirement for these units is that they be able to cover great distances and escape from situations in which they would be killed. Specially trained or bred horses are not required, and the unit needs to be only minimally armored. Before the development of the stirrup and other equestrian technology, it took years to learn to fight from horseback effectively, not a worthwhile investment for scouting units.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Light cavalry have been employed as scouts and skirmisher from ancient times. The only real requirement for these units is that they be able to cover great distances and escape from situations in which they would be killed. Specially trained or bred horses are not required, and the unit needs to be only minimally armored. Before the development of the stirrup and other equestrian technology, it took years to learn to fight from horseback effectively, not a worthwhile investment for scouting units.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOUNTED_SEARGENT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A seargent, or serjeant, was a man of lesser rank and wealth to a knight, but with comparable equipment and training. Serjeants could fight either as heavy or light cavalry, and here fulfill that secondary role. Serjeants ranked above the common man-at-arms on the social scale. Although the social structure of the Norman society of England was generally static, the easiest manner for a man to attain social rank and improve his standing was through military service, as the Norman states, unlike the Germanic ones, believed in knighting men of common birth who demonstrated nobility and courage on the field. </English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>A seargent, or serjeant, was a man of lesser rank and wealth to a knight, but with comparable equipment and training. Serjeants could fight either as heavy or light cavalry, and here fulfill that secondary role. Serjeants ranked above the common man-at-arms on the social scale. Although the social structure of the Norman society of England was generally static, the easiest manner for a man to attain social rank and improve his standing was through military service, as the Norman states, unlike the Germanic ones, believed in knighting men of common birth who demonstrated nobility and courage on the field.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HORSE_ARCHER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A horse archer is a cavalryman armed with a bow. Because using a bow requires a horseman to let go of the reins with both hands, horse archers need superb equestrian skills and horse archery is typically associated with steppe nomads. The weapon of choice for horse archers was the recurve bow, which is compact enough to shoot from a horse yet retained sufficient range and penetrating power. Mounted archers needed little or no armor and could ride light, fast mounts.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>A horse archer is a cavalryman armed with a bow. Because using a bow requires a horseman to let go of the reins with both hands, horse archers need superb equestrian skills and horse archery is typically associated with steppe nomads. The weapon of choice for horse archers was the recurve bow, which is compact enough to shoot from a horse yet retained sufficient range and penetrating power. Mounted archers needed little or no armor and could ride light, fast mounts.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PISTOLIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Pistols were the first gunpowder weapons developed for cavalry, and the pistoliers was one of the new cavalry types to develop which signaled the end of the lance-charging heavy cavalry. Pistoliers were expected to be able to engage their opponents both with firearms and sword; they formed up in deep blocks and used their firearms in a caracole attack to disrupt enemy infantry formations before charging home and engaging in hand-to-hand combat. German mercenary cavalry called Reiters or "Black Riders" were some of the most prominent pistoliers.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Pistols were the first gunpowder weapons developed for cavalry, and the pistoliers was one of the new cavalry types to develop which signaled the end of the lance-charging heavy cavalry. Pistoliers were expected to be able to engage their opponents both with firearms and sword; they formed up in deep blocks and used their firearms in a caracole attack to disrupt enemy infantry formations before charging home and engaging in hand-to-hand combat. German mercenary cavalry called Reiters or "Black Riders" were some of the most prominent pistoliers.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUSSAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Frederick the Great was instrumental in spreading the irregular light cavalry of Hungary (huszars) to the battlefields of Europe. By dropping metal body armor, these light hussars became ideal for reconnaissance and raiding. In battle, they were used in such light cavalry roles as harassing enemy skirmishers, overrunning artillery positions, and pursuing fleeing troops. Following the Prussian example, hussar regiments were introduced across Europe, often maintaining the colorful uniforms a reputation for recklessness in battle of Frederick's original hussars.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Frederick the Great was instrumental in spreading the irregular light cavalry of Hungary (huszars) to the battlefields of Europe. By dropping metal body armor, these light hussars became ideal for reconnaissance and raiding. In battle, they were used in such light cavalry roles as harassing enemy skirmishers, overrunning artillery positions, and pursuing fleeing troops. Following the Prussian example, hussar regiments were introduced across Europe, often maintaining the colorful uniforms a reputation for recklessness in battle of Frederick's original hussars.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LANCER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Carolingians of early medieval France relied heavily on mounted warriors in their conquests. Inventions such as the stirrup and high-backed saddle are sometimes identified as the key element driving the shift from infantry to cavalry. Although these technologies were certainly useful in fighting from horseback, strategic considerations are just as likely to have driven the shift; the extended Carolingian empire required a mobile army. These early cavalry were protected with a byrnie (probably long scale armor) and fought primarily with lance and sword.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>The Carolingians of early medieval France relied heavily on mounted warriors in their conquests. Inventions such as the stirrup and high-backed saddle are sometimes identified as the key element driving the shift from infantry to cavalry. Although these technologies were certainly useful in fighting from horseback, strategic considerations are just as likely to have driven the shift; the extended Carolingian empire required a mobile army. These early cavalry were protected with a byrnie (probably long scale armor) and fought primarily with lance and sword.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEAVY_LANCER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Increasing armor weight required new breeds of heavier horses to carry mounted warriors. The most highly prized type of war-horse was the destrier, bred specifically for battles or jousts. In the wet climates of Europe, these new breeds required horseshoes to protect their hoofs. All of these developments required a fairly wealthy and advanced civilization, but the price was well worth it: few lighter units could hope to stand against the determined charge of a fully armored lancer.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>Increasing armor weight required new breeds of heavier horses to carry mounted warriors. The most highly prized type of war-horse was the destrier, bred specifically for battles or jousts. In the wet climates of Europe, these new breeds required horseshoes to protect their hoofs. All of these developments required a fairly wealthy and advanced civilization, but the price was well worth it: few lighter units could hope to stand against the determined charge of a fully armored lancer.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CUIRASSIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Cuirassier was the last step in the evolution of European armored cavalry. Drawing their name from their heavy, metal breastplates - or "cuirasses" - the Cuirassiers were the heaviest of the heavy cavalry. The earliest Cuirassiers, born in the 15th century, were armored head-to-toe and armed with heavy saber and pistols. As European warfare began to rely more on firearms, much of this heavy armor was shed to increase mobility, eventually adapting into what is now recognized as the standard Cuirassier uniform - a breastplate and helm.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>The Cuirassier was the last step in the evolution of European armored cavalry. Drawing their name from their heavy, metal breastplates - or "cuirasses" - the Cuirassiers were the heaviest of the heavy cavalry. The earliest Cuirassiers, born in the 15th century, were armored head-to-toe and armed with heavy saber and pistols. As European warfare began to rely more on firearms, much of this heavy armor was shed to increase mobility, eventually adapting into what is now recognized as the standard Cuirassier uniform - a breastplate and helm.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARBALEST_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The arbalest was a late variation of the medieval European crossbow. A larger weapon, the arbalest had a steel prod ("bow"). Since an arbalest was much larger than earlier crossbows, and because of the greater tensile strength of steel, it had a greater force and range. A skilled arbalestier could shoot two bolts per minute. Arbalests were sometimes considered inhumane or unfair weapons, since an inexperienced arbalestier could use one to kill a knight who had a lifetime of training.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>The arbalest was a late variation of the medieval European crossbow. A larger weapon, the arbalest had a steel prod ("bow"). Since an arbalest was much larger than earlier crossbows, and because of the greater tensile strength of steel, it had a greater force and range. A skilled arbalestier could shoot two bolts per minute. Arbalests were sometimes considered inhumane or unfair weapons, since an inexperienced arbalestier could use one to kill a knight who had a lifetime of training.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARQUEBUSIER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The arquebus is an early muzzle-loaded firearm. They were used against enemies that were often protected by steel-plate armor, which a bullet could pierce only at close range. The arquebus was unable to match the accuracy of a bow in the hands of a highly-skilled archer. However, it had a faster rate of fire than the most powerful crossbow, and a much shorter learning curve than a longbow. Once the methods were developed, powder and shot were relatively easy to mass-produce, while arrow making was a genuine craft requiring highly skilled labor.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>The arquebus is an early muzzle-loaded firearm. They were used against enemies that were often protected by steel-plate armor, which a bullet could pierce only at close range. The arquebus was unable to match the accuracy of a bow in the hands of a highly-skilled archer. However, it had a faster rate of fire than the most powerful crossbow, and a much shorter learning curve than a longbow. Once the methods were developed, powder and shot were relatively easy to mass-produce, while arrow making was a genuine craft requiring highly skilled labor.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MUSKETMAN2_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The arquebus is an early muzzle-loaded firearm. They were used against enemies that were often protected by steel-plate armor, which a bullet could pierce only at close range. The arquebus was unable to match the accuracy of a bow in the hands of a highly-skilled archer. However, it had a faster rate of fire than the most powerful crossbow, and a much shorter learning curve than a longbow. Once the methods were developed, powder and shot were relatively easy to mass-produce, while arrow making was a genuine craft requiring highly skilled labor.</English>
		<French></French><German/><Italian/><Spanish/><Russian>The arquebus is an early muzzle-loaded firearm. They were used against enemies that were often protected by steel-plate armor, which a bullet could pierce only at close range. The arquebus was unable to match the accuracy of a bow in the hands of a highly-skilled archer. However, it had a faster rate of fire than the most powerful crossbow, and a much shorter learning curve than a longbow. Once the methods were developed, powder and shot were relatively easy to mass-produce, while arrow making was a genuine craft requiring highly skilled labor.</Russian><Japanese/><Chinese/></TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BOMBARD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A bombard is a medieval cannon or mortar, used chiefly in sieges for throwing heavy stone balls. This weapon was usually used during sieges to hurl various forms of missile into enemy fortifications. Projectiles such as stone or metal balls, burning materials and weighted cloth soaked in quicklime or Greek fire are documented.</English>
		<French>[TAB]A bombard is a medieval cannon or mortar, used chiefly in sieges for throwing heavy stone balls. This weapon was usually used during sieges to hurl various forms of missile into enemy fortifications. Projectiles such as stone or metal balls, burning materials and weighted cloth soaked in quicklime or Greek fire are documented.</French>
		<German>[TAB]A bombard is a medieval cannon or mortar, used chiefly in sieges for throwing heavy stone balls. This weapon was usually used during sieges to hurl various forms of missile into enemy fortifications. Projectiles such as stone or metal balls, burning materials and weighted cloth soaked in quicklime or Greek fire are documented.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]A bombard is a medieval cannon or mortar, used chiefly in sieges for throwing heavy stone balls. This weapon was usually used during sieges to hurl various forms of missile into enemy fortifications. Projectiles such as stone or metal balls, burning materials and weighted cloth soaked in quicklime or Greek fire are documented.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]A bombard is a medieval cannon or mortar, used chiefly in sieges for throwing heavy stone balls. This weapon was usually used during sieges to hurl various forms of missile into enemy fortifications. Projectiles such as stone or metal balls, burning materials and weighted cloth soaked in quicklime or Greek fire are documented.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BURGUNDIAN_PALADIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Chevaliers are medieval knights who follow the code of knightly conduct. The particulars of the code varied, but codes would emphasize the virtues of courage, honor, and service. They were adept at the art of war, trained in fighting in armor, with horses, lances, swords and shields. Chevaliers were taught to excel in the arms, to show courage, to be gallant, loyal and to swear off cowardice and baseness.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The Chevaliers are medieval knights who follow the code of knightly conduct. The particulars of the code varied, but codes would emphasize the virtues of courage, honor, and service. They were adept at the art of war, trained in fighting in armor, with horses, lances, swords and shields. Chevaliers were taught to excel in the arms, to show courage, to be gallant, loyal and to swear off cowardice and baseness.</French>
		<German>[TAB]The Chevaliers are medieval knights who follow the code of knightly conduct. The particulars of the code varied, but codes would emphasize the virtues of courage, honor, and service. They were adept at the art of war, trained in fighting in armor, with horses, lances, swords and shields. Chevaliers were taught to excel in the arms, to show courage, to be gallant, loyal and to swear off cowardice and baseness.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The Chevaliers are medieval knights who follow the code of knightly conduct. The particulars of the code varied, but codes would emphasize the virtues of courage, honor, and service. They were adept at the art of war, trained in fighting in armor, with horses, lances, swords and shields. Chevaliers were taught to excel in the arms, to show courage, to be gallant, loyal and to swear off cowardice and baseness.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The Chevaliers are medieval knights who follow the code of knightly conduct. The particulars of the code varied, but codes would emphasize the virtues of courage, honor, and service. They were adept at the art of war, trained in fighting in armor, with horses, lances, swords and shields. Chevaliers were taught to excel in the arms, to show courage, to be gallant, loyal and to swear off cowardice and baseness.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CARRACK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]These four-masted sailing ships were the first European ships able to reliably navigate the open ocean. Although small by modern standards, the Carrack afforded enough space for crew, cargo and small cannons. Because the ship rose high out of the water it was near impossible for smaller ships to board a carrack. This size was a double edged sword, and due to its height Carracks were prone to capsize in strong winds. The Carrack was used most prominently by the Portuguese and Spanish during their explorations in the 15th and 16th centuries. The Santa Maria, the ship that carried Columbus to the New World, was a Carrack.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Ces navires &#224; quatre m&#226;ts sont les premiers bateaux europ&#233;ens capables de naviguer sur l'oc&#233;an. Bien que petite selon les crit&#232;res modernes, la caraque offre assez d'espace pour abriter un &#233;quipage, une cargaison et quelques petits canons. Ce bateau s'&#233;l&#232;ve bien au-dessus de la mer, il est donc presque impossible pour les plus petits navires de l'aborder. Cette taille ne pr&#233;sente pas que des avantages car les caraques sont enclines &#224; chavirer en cas de grand vent. La caraque est surtout utilis&#233;e par les Portugais et les Espagnols au cours de leurs explorations des 15&#232;me et 16&#232;me si&#232;cles. La Santa Maria, le vaisseau qui transporta Christophe Colomb jusqu'au Nouveau monde, &#233;tait une caraque.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Diese Vier-Mast-Segelschiffe waren die ersten europ&#228;ischen Schiffe, die in der Lage waren, zuverl&#228;ssig auf dem offenen Meer zu fahren. Obwohl sie nach modernen Ma&#223;st&#228;ben klein war, bot die Karacke genug Platz f&#252;r Mannschaft, Fracht und kleine Kanonen. Da das Schiff hoch aus dem Wasser ragte, war es f&#252;r kleinere Schiffe beinahe unm&#246;glich anzugreifen. Diese H&#246;he war ein zweischneidiges Schwert, da die Karacke daher auch bei starken Winden zum Kentern neigte. Die Karacke wurde vor allem von den Portugiesen und Spaniern bei ihren Entdeckungsreisen im 15. und 16. Jahrhundert genutzt. Die Santa Maria, das Schiff, das Kolumbus in die Neue Welt brachte, war eine Karacke.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Queste navi a quattro alberi furono le prime imbarcazioni europee in grado di navigare in sicurezza nell'oceano aperto. Anche se piccole, secondo gli standard moderni, le Caracche avevano abbastanza spazio da ospitare equipaggio, carico e piccoli cannoni. A causa dell'altezza delle murate era quasi impossibile, per navi pi&#249; piccole, abbordare una Caracca. Le dimensioni erano una spada a doppio taglio, per&#242;, proprio a causa dell'altezza, infatti, le Caracche tendevano a capovolgersi in caso di venti troppo forti. La Caracca venne usata principalmente da Portoghesi e Spagnoli durante le esplorazioni del 15&#176; e 16&#176; secolo. La Santa Maria, la nave che port&#242; Colombo nel Nuovo Mondo, era una Caracca.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Estas naves de cuatro m&#225;stiles fueron los primeros barcos europeos capaces de aventurarse sin peligro en mar abierta. Aunque peque&#241;as seg&#250;n los est&#225;ndares modernos, las carracas contaban con espacio suficiente para alojar a la tripulaci&#243;n, el cargamento y varios ca&#241;ones de peque&#241;o tama&#241;o. Ten&#237;an la borda tan elevada que para las dem&#225;s naves era casi imposible abordarlas. Sin embargo, esto resultaba ser un arma de doble filo, puesto que las hac&#237;a muy vulnerables a los vientos fuertes. Tanto los espa&#241;oles como los portugueses las utilizaron con frecuencia durante sus exploraciones en los siglos XV y XVI. La Santa Mar&#237;a, una de las naves que Col&#243;n llev&#243; al Nuevo Mundo, era una carraca.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOUNTED_INFANTRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Mounted Infantry soldiers use horses to get to the battlefield, but once there they dismount and fight on foot. They rarely take part in charges or other horseback maneuvers, and they tend to suffer badly when engaged in such against trained cavalry units. On the other hand, when fortified on a hill, Mounted Infantry can do serious damage to an attacking Horse Archer or Light Cavalry unit.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les soldats d'infanterie mont&#233;e se servent de chevaux pour atteindre le champ de bataille mais une fois sur place, ils se battent &#224; pied. Ils ne prennent que rarement part aux charges ou aux manoeuvres &#224; cheval et ont tendance &#224; subir des pertes importantes face &#224; des unit&#233;s de cavalerie entra&#238;n&#233;es. Cependant, si elle est plac&#233;e dans des fortifications sur une colline, l'infanterie mont&#233;e peut infliger de s&#233;rieux dommages &#224; une unit&#233; d'archers mont&#233;s ou de cavalerie l&#233;g&#232;re.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Soldaten der Berittenen Infanterie nutzen Pferde, um aufs Schlachtfeld zu gelangen. Sobald sie es erreicht haben, satteln sie jedoch ab und k&#228;mpfen zu Fu&#223;. Sie nehmen nur selten an Vorst&#246;&#223;en oder anderen Man&#246;vern zu Pferd teil, und wenn sie gegen ausgebildete Einheiten der Kavallerie eingesetzt werden, stecken sie meist viel Schaden ein. Wenn sie gefestigt auf einem H&#252;gel stationiert ist, kann die Berittene Infanterie anr&#252;ckenden Berittenen Bogensch&#252;tzen oder Einheiten der Leichten Kavallerie jedoch schweren Schaden zuf&#252;gen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]I soldati della fanteria a cavallo usano i cavalli per arrivare al campo di battaglia ma poi smontano e combattono a piedi. Di rado prendono parte a cariche o altre manovre a cavallo, e tendono a subire malamente gli attacchi delle unit&#224; di cavalleria. D'altro canto quando sono fortificate in collina, i fanti a cavallo possono infliggere seri danni ad arcieri a cavallo o cavalleria leggera.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Los soldados de la infanter&#237;a montada usan sus caballos para llegar al campo de batalla, pero una vez all&#237; desmontan y luchan a pie. Solo en raras ocasiones toman parte en cargas u otras maniobras t&#237;picas de caballer&#237;a y, cuando se enfrentan con escuadrones de caballer&#237;a profesional, normalmente llevan las de perder. Por otro lado, cuando est&#225; atrincherada en una colina, la infanter&#237;a montada puede ser muy peligrosa para los arqueros a caballo o la caballer&#237;a ligera.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PROSECUTOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]While Missionaries often focus on extolling the glories of their respective gods to spread their religion, the Prosecutors focuses instead on pointing out the fallacies of all religions but his own. Ardent in the belief that all other religions are wrong, the Prosecutor lives to destroy the beliefs of others. If the Prosecution convicted a person of heresy, the personal property of a condemned person was confiscated and places of worship were destroyed; based on medieval and feudal laws. Usually the confiscated property was divided three ways: by the Prosecution members, the church officials, and the state treasury. The Church and state kept strict accounts of the prisoner's incarceration, trial and execution costs. If the value of his confiscated property was not enough to cover these costs, then his heirs had to pay the difference. Records show many women and children were left penniless from such confiscation.  You may expend a Prosecutor inside a city to remove all religions from that city except your own.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les missionnaires se contentent souvent de glorifier leurs dieux respectifs pour propager leur religion, alors que l'inquisiteur s'efforce de d&#233;montrer les aberrations de toutes les autres religions. Convaincu que toutes les autres religions sont dans l'erreur, l'inquisiteur vit pour d&#233;truire les croyances des autres. Vous pouvez envoyer un inquisiteur dans une ville pour l'expurger de toutes les religions sauf la v&#244;tre.</French>
		<German>[TAB]W&#228;hrend Missionare sich oft darauf konzentrieren, die Tugenden ihrer jeweiligen G&#246;tter zu &#252;bertreiben, um ihre Religion zu verbreiten, konzentriert sich der Inquisitor stattdessen darauf, die Fehler aller anderen Religionen au&#223;er seiner eigenen aufzuzeigen. Der Inquisitor brennt vor &#220;berzeugung, dass alle anderen Religionen falsch sind, und lebt daf&#252;r, den Glauben aller anderen zu zerst&#246;ren. Sie k&#246;nnen einen Inquisitor in eine Stadt entsenden, um aus dieser Stadt alle Religionen au&#223;er Ihrer zu entfernen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Mentre i missionari si concentrano sulle lodi delle rispettive divinit&#224; per diffondere la propria religione, gli inquisitori mettono in risalto gli errori delle altre religioni. Credono ardentemente che le altre religioni si sbaglino e vivono per distruggere la fede degli altri. Puoi usare un Inquisitore in una citt&#224; per rimuoverne tutte le religioni tranne la tua.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Mientras que los misioneros suelen concentrarse en cantar las glorias de sus respectivos dioses para difundir su fe, los inquisidores se dedican a poner de manifiesto las falacias de todas las dem&#225;s religiones. Ferviente convencido de que todas las dem&#225;s religiones se equivocan, El inquisidor vive para socavar las creencias de los dem&#225;s. Puedes gastar un inquisidor dentro de una ciudad para eliminar todas las religiones salvo la tuya.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARABIA_GHAZI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Ghazi warriors were fierce Arabic light/medium cavalry armed with sword and lance, who raided deep into enemy territory to make war on unbelievers. Depending largely on plunder for their livelihood they were organized in bands similiar to mercenary companies which attracted religious zealots and adventurers of every kind. Within the context of Islamic jihad warfare, they struck fast and hard inside enemy borders to destroy war materials and morale, then withdrawing with all the loot they could carry. As flexible and highly mobile border defenders and raiders they often preceeded the deployment of much larger armies during the early Arab invasions of Persia, Egypt and North Africa.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOSCOW_BOYAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A boyar was a member of the highest rank of the feudal Bulgarian, Kievan Rus and Moscovian aristocracies, second only to the ruling dukes. Boyars weilded considerable power through their military support of the Moscovian princes and state, their traditions of family service and their ownership of land. Very similiar to Western knights, they were armed with swords and bows and equiped with chain or plate armour, and commanded their own personal armies of peasant levies and mercenaries. They continued to occupy the highest state offices, after repelling the Mongol invasions of the 13thC, throughout the 14th and 15th centuries until their power was eroded by the Czars, chiefly Ivan IV, during the 16C.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DRAGOON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The word "dragoon" is derived from the French Army designation dragon which was originally the name of a type of firearm (whose name means dragon) carried by French dragoons. In French, Portuguese and Spanish there is no distinction between the words dragoon and dragon.

Dragoons were originally infantrymen deployed by horse, but later became cavalry. They were therefore trained in horse riding as well as infantry fighting skills. Dragoon regiments were established in most European armies during the late 17th and early 18th centuries. Originally dragoons were considered as separate from regular cavalry, but during the 18th century they evolved into conventional mounted troops trained to fight from horseback.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TAGMATA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The tagma is a term for a military unit of battalion size. The best-known use of the term however refers to the elite regiments comprising the central imperial army of the middle and late Byzantine Empire.

In Byzantine usage, the term came to refer exclusively to the professional, standing troops, garrisoned in and around the capital of Constantinople. Most of them traced their origins to the Imperial guard units of the later Roman Empire. By the 7th century, these had declined to little more than parade troops, meaning that the emperors were hard put to face the frequent revolts of the new and powerful thematic formations, especially the Opsician theme, the Asian theme closest to the capital. Within the first sixty years since its creation, it was involved in five revolts, culminating in the rebellion and usurpation of the throne by its commander, the Count Artabasdos, in 741 - 743.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPANISH_TERCIO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Tercio ("one third"), also known as Tercio Español, was a Renaissance era military formation similar to and derivative of the Swiss pike square and was a term used to describe a mixed infantry formation of about 3,000 pikemen, swordsmen and arquebusiers in a mutually supportive formation; it was also sometimes referred to by other nations as a Spanish Square after its introduction by the Spanish army, and was widely adopted across international lines and dominated formalized field warfare for more than a century.

The Tercio Español was the product of the Italian Wars in which the Spanish general, Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba, would reorganize the Spanish army throughout a series of conflicts at the end of the 15th and early 16th centuries, into a tactically unique combination of modern and medieval combined arms centered around armored infantry. This emphasis on the infantry was the result of Spain's great dependence on mules in daily life, which in turn resulted in an inability to raise large cavalry forces. It marked the transformation of medieval military institutions into the early modern combined-arms[3] army. (See: Pike and Shot for an excellent description of the eventual formation.) Gonzalo Fernández, developed the Tercio to further increase the effectiveness of Spanish infantry against every manner of opposing infantry while remaining impervious to the dangers of a cavalry charge.
At first the army consisted of units of around 6000 men, called coronelias, which by 1534 had been reduced into the Tercios of 3000 for increased mobility on the offensive.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VENICE_GALLEAS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The galleass or "galliass" developed from large merchant galleys converted for military use they were higher and larger than regular ("light") galleys. They had up to 32 oars, each worked by up to 5 men. They usually had three masts and a forecastle and aftcastle. Much effort was made in Venice to make these galleasses as fast as possible to compete with regular galleys. The gun-deck usually ran over the rowers' heads, but there are also pictures showing the opposite arrangement.

Galleasses usually carried more sails than true galleys, and were far deadlier; a galley caught broadside lay all but helpless, but coming broadside to a galleass, as with a ship of the line, exposed an attacker to her gunfire. The galleass exemplified an intermediate type between the galley and the true man-of-war. Relatively few galleasses were built - one disadvantage was that, being more reliant on sails, their position at the front of the galley line at the start of a battle could not be guaranteed - but they were used at the Battle of Lepanto (7 October 1571), their firepower helping to win victory for the Christian fleet, and some sufficiently seaworthy galleasses accompanied the Spanish Armada in 1588 (e.g. La Girona). In the 15th century a type of light galleass, called the frigate, was built in southern European countries to answer the increasing challenge posed by the north African based Barbary pirates in their fast galleys.

In the Mediterranean, with its shallower waters, less dangerous weather and fickle winds, both galleasses and galleys continued in use, particularly in Venice and Turkey, long after they became obsolete elsewhere. Later, "round ships" and galleasses were replaced by galleons and ships of the line which originated in Atlantic Europe. The first Venetian ship of the line was built in 1660.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KIEV_DRUZHINA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The name is derived from the Slavic word drug with the meaning of "companion, friend". It is a cognate of the Germanic drottin meaning "war band".

Druzhina was in the history of early East Slavs a detachment of select troops in personal service of a Knyaz (A Slavic title). It's main functions were bodyguarding, raising tribute from conquered territories and serving as the core of the army during war campaigns. Equipped as heavy cavalry wearing padded and mail armour and armed with lance and sword, the "Druzinniks" served freely and could leave one knyaz and join another. Druzyna varied in size, but usually numbered several hundred. They served as the nucleus of the army which was otherwise largely recruited as peasant levies. Druznya were paid by the knyaz and were able to share a portion of any military loot while on campaign.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CORDOBAN_BERBER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Following the Muslim conquest of North Africa in the 7thC., the Berber peoples of the Maghreb and Morocco largely adopted Islam and became the mainstay of Arab armies in the West. Skilled with bow and javelin and mounted on camels, they soon mastered the horse and became adept as scouting and raiding light cavalry. The Arab conquest of Iberia initiated by the Berber general, Tarik ibn-Zihad consisted of about 300 elite Arabian cavalry and a mixed Berber army of about 1800-2000 bowmen, spearmen and light cavalry. Later Andalusian armies were largely comprised of a core of Arabian noble horsemen and a majority of Berber voluteers and mercenaries who fought both on foot and on horseback.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GENOA_BALESTRIERI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Genoese crossbowmen were a famous military formation both in the defence of Genoa and as mercenaries for other Italian and European powers during the Middle Ages. Fighting on both land and in naval battles, they were outfitted with a dagger, light metal helmet, gorget and a large shield called a "pavese" which protected them while loading the crossbow. The presence of balestieri companies on the battlefield was highly feared due to the efficiency of their weapons and their organization, and even often enough to lead an opponent to alter his battle plans. The balestrieri remained feared and respected military formations into the late 16thC. even after the introduction of black powder weapons into Europe.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_COGGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The cog (or cogge) was a type of ship which first appeared in Northern Europe and was widely used from the 12thC. onwards. Cogs were generally made of oak, an abundant timber in the Baltic region, and were fitted with a single mast and square-rigged sail. Even though this rigging prevented them sailing into the wind, cogs between associated with sea going trade in the northern waters of Medieval Europe. They were generally flat-bottomed and employed a stern-mounted rudder with fore and stern castles as defense against pirates, enabling them to often used as warships. By the late 15thC. they were replaced by the carrack which was more sea-worthy and suitable for sailing in the open ocean over longer distances.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ENGLISH_LONGBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Longbows were tall, powerful bows employed to penetrate all but the best of Medieval armour.Their use by English armies reached a peak during the Hundred Years War when the use of massed longbowmen was highly effective against the French at the battles of Crecy (1346), Poitiers (1356) and at Agincourt in 1415. The longbow combined long range and high accuracy but not both at the same time. Most longbow shooting involved launching volleys of arrows at enemy armies at long range from protected positions. The longbow was the machine gun of the Middle Ages, accurate, deadly and more rapid-firing than the crossbow or even early firearms though with the development of the latter the longbow gradually fell into disuse.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WELSH_LONGBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Following the Norman conquest of Wales in the 13thC., during which Welsh bowmen caused heavy casualties to the invader, Kings of England increasingly began to used longbowmen, including Welsh bowmen in their armies. Originally the Welsh employed a much shorter, rougher bow made of elm technically distinct from the classic English yew longbows. But as soon as the Welsh
campaign was successfully over, Welsh conscripts began to be incorporated in large numbers into English armies. The valuable lessons the English learned in Wales of the tactic of massed formations of skilled archers using powerful bows was later used with great effect by English and Welsh mercenary longbowmen on the battlefields of Scotland and France. </English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT> <!--merijn_v1 Text-->
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUNGARIAN_LANCER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A type of irregular light horsemen was already well established by the 15th century in medieval Hungary. Etymologists are divided over the derivation of the word 'hussar'. Many scholars believe the word that was passed into Hungarian by way of the Croatians originates from the Latin word 'cursus' meaning 'raid'. According to Webster's the word hussar stems from the Hungarian huszár, which in turn originates from the Serbian husar or gusar, meaning pirate, from the Medieval Latin cursarius (cf. the English word corsair). A variant of this theory is offered by Byzantinist scholars, who argue the term originated in Roman military practice, and the cursarius--a group of fast moving horsemen used for scouting or raiding-came to be called tsanarioi in Greek or the Armenian Chosarioi.  Through Byzantine Army operations in the Balkans in the 10th and 11th centuries, the word was thus reintroduced to Western European military practice after its original usage had been lost with the collapse of Rome in the west. According to another theory, the word is derived from the Hungarian word of húsz meaning twenty, suggesting that hussar regiments were originally composed of twenty men. Or the term huszár probably signified 'one in twenty' as selected for service by ballot.

The hussars reportedly originated in bands of Hungarian and Serbian warriors crossing into southern Hungary after the Turkish invasion of Serbia at the end of the 14th century. The Governor of Hungary, Hunyadi János - John Hunyadi, created mounted units inspired by his enemy the Ottoman Turks. His son, Hunyadi Mátyás Matthias Corvinus, later king of Hungary, is unanimously accepted as the creator of these troops. Initially they fought in small bands, but were reorganized into larger, trained, formations during the reign of King Matthias I Corvinus of Hungary. So the first Hussar regiments were the light cavalry of the Black Army of Hungary. Under his command the hussars took part in the war against the Ottoman Empire in 1485 and proved successful against the Turkish Spahis as well as against Bohemians and Poles. After the king's death in 1490, hussars remained the preferred form of cavalry in Hungary. The Habsburg emperors hired Hungarian hussars as mercenaries to serve against the Ottoman Empire and on various battlefields throughout Europe. The "father" of the US cavalry in 1777 was a Hungarian hussar named Kováts Mihály - Michael de Kovats.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
