<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- RFCE Dawn of Man -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RHYES_DAWN_OF_MAN_TEXT</Tag>
		<English>The sun rises on the year %s1_year. The %s2_civ people are ready to settle down and found your first city.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, your people have vested absolute power in you, trusting that you can build a Civilization to stand the test of time!</English>
		<French>Le soleil se l&#232;ve sur l'an %s1_year. Les %s2_civ sont pr&#234;ts &#224; s'installer et &#224; fonder votre premi&#232;re ville.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, votre peuple vous a confi&#233; le pouvoir absolu et s'en remet &#224; vous pour b&#226;tir une civilisation qui r&#233;sistera &#224; l'&#233;preuve du temps !</French>
		<German>Die Sonne erhellt das Jahr %s1_year. Das %s2:3_civ Volk ist bereit, sich niederzulassen und Eure erste Stadt zu gr&#252;nden.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, Euer Volk hat Euch absolute Macht verliehen und vertraut darauf, dass Ihr eine Zivilisation errichtet, welche die Zeit &#252;berdauern wird!</German>
		<Italian>Il sole sorge nell'anno %s1_year. La popolazione %s2:2_civ &#232; infine pronta a stabilirsi e a fondare la tua prima citt&#224;.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, il tuo popolo ti ha conferito potere assoluto, credendo che tu possa sviluppare una civilt&#224; in grado di resistere alle prove del tempo!</Italian>
		<Spanish>El sol se alza en el a&#241;o %s1_year. Las gentes del %s2_civ est&#225;n listas para asentarse y fundar vuestra primera ciudad.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]%s3_leader, vuestro pueblo os ha conferido poder absoluto, confiando en que pod&#225;is desarrollar una civilizaci&#243;n que supere los retos del tiempo.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>O sol nasce no ano de %s1_year. </Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_SCREEN_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</English>
		<French>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</French>
		<German>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</German>
		<Italian>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</Italian>
		<Spanish>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPE</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>RHYE'S AND FALL OF CIVILIZATIONS: EUROPA</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BYZANTIUM</Tag>
		<English>After many glorious centuries under Rome, the great Constantine saw fit to split the mighty empire into two parts.[NEWLINE]It is now the year 500 AD, and the Western Roman Empire has fallen. While Rome will always have a place in your people's hearts, Constantinople is now the heart of the most glorious nation on Earth![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Justinian, you are now the sole ruler, THE Roman Emperor. Your nation is rich and strong, but be aware: vast riches attract many enemies, and some of the barbarians may be even stronger than we are.[NEWLINE]Your people have faith that you can lead their mighty nation through the coming storm. Will you prevail and lead the Byzantine Empire through another 1,000 years of glory?</English>
		<French>After many glorious centuries under Rome, the great Constantine saw fit to split the mighty empire into two parts.[NEWLINE]It is now the year 500 AD, and the Western Roman Empire has fallen. While Rome will always have a place in your people's hearts, Constantinople is now the heart of the most glorious nation on Earth![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Justinian, you are now the sole ruler, THE Roman Emperor. Your nation is rich and strong, but be aware: vast riches attract many enemies, and some of the barbarians may be even stronger than we are.[NEWLINE]Your people have faith that you can lead their mighty nation through the coming storm. Will you prevail and lead the Byzantine Empire through another 1,000 years of glory?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BYZANTIUM_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>Basileus. Though we have endured many hardships over the last several centuries, the Roman Empire still stands strong, and Constantinople, the Queen of Cities, remains the crown jewel of Europe. However, we are but a shell of our former glory. Much of the work of the Komnenian Restoration has already been undone; corruption plagues the empire, usurpers rise left and right, the Bulgarians have revolted once more, and the dream of recovering Anatolia is now more distant than ever.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Now we fear we may have our greatest challenge yet. It appears that the schismatic Catholics are preparing for yet another Crusade. But we fear this one will be different. Our former vassals, the Venetians, are still furious over the Massacre of the Latins several years ago. Should the Venetians choose to give the order, rather than attacking the infidels in the Holy Land, the Crusaders may instead set sail for our beating heart, the great city of Constantinople.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Our walls have never been breached, though many have tried. But this may prove too much. And if the Venetians can bring them down, how will we fend off invasions from the heathens in Anatolia in the years to come?</English>
		<French>Basileus. Though we have endured many hardships over the last several centuries, the Roman Empire still stands strong, and Constantinople, the Queen of Cities, remains the crown jewel of Europe. However, we are but a shell of our former glory. Much of the work of the Komnenian Restoration has already been undone; corruption plagues the empire, usurpers rise left and right, the Bulgarians have revolted once more, and the dream of recovering Anatolia is now more distant than ever.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Now we fear we may have our greatest challenge yet. It appears that the schismatic Catholics are preparing for yet another Crusade. But we fear this one will be different. Our former vassals, the Venetians, are still furious over the Massacre of the Latins several years ago. Should the Venetians choose to give the order, rather than attacking the infidels in the Holy Land, the Crusaders may instead set sail for our beating heart, the great city of Constantinople.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Our walls have never been breached, though many have tried. But this may prove too much. And if the Venetians can bring them down, how will we fend off invasions from the heathens in Anatolia in the years to come?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_FRANCE</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 500 AD. As king of the Frankish people, you have lead their way in becoming the first barbarian tribe to embrace Catholicism instead of Arianism, which will be our guiding principle in building a glorious civilization.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Your lands are vast and fertile, but the Burgundians in the Rhone valley will not always stay subdued, and the coasts may provide access to dangerous raiders from the north. Will you bear through these struggles, unify the realm, and establish the most powerful kingdom in Europe for generations to come?</English>
		<French>It is the year 500 AD. As king of the Frankish people, you have lead their way in becoming the first barbarian tribe to embrace Catholicism instead of Arianism, which will be our guiding principle in building a glorious civilization.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Your lands are vast and fertile, but the Burgundians in the Rhone valley will not always stay subdued, and the coasts may provide access to dangerous raiders from the north. Will you bear through these struggles, unify the realm, and establish the most powerful kingdom in Europe for generations to come?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_FRANCE_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>The year is 1200 AD, and the Kingdom of France is in the midst of a complex web of alliances and rivalries with its neighboring nations. To the west lies the Kingdom of England, ruled by King John Lackland, who seeks to expand his dominion over the French territories.[NEWLINE]To the south, the Duchy of Aquitaine, controlled by Eleanor of Aquitaine, is a key ally of France. However, her sons, Richard the Lionheart and King John of England, have been at odds with each other for years, threatening the stability of the region.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You have been chosen to drive back the English invaders and secure key territories for the French crown. The winds of war are blowing strongly, and your decisions will shape the course of history in this tumultuous era. Will you seek to drive back the English invaders, forge alliances with other nations, or pursue a more cautious strategy? The fate of France rests in your hands.</English>
		<French>The year is 1200 AD, and the Kingdom of France is in the midst of a complex web of alliances and rivalries with its neighboring nations. To the west lies the Kingdom of England, ruled by King John Lackland, who seeks to expand his dominion over the French territories.[NEWLINE]To the south, the Duchy of Aquitaine, controlled by Eleanor of Aquitaine, is a key ally of France. However, her sons, Richard the Lionheart and King John of England, have been at odds with each other for years, threatening the stability of the region.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You have been chosen to drive back the English invaders and secure key territories for the French crown. The winds of war are blowing strongly, and your decisions will shape the course of history in this tumultuous era. Will you seek to drive back the English invaders, forge alliances with other nations, or pursue a more cautious strategy? The fate of France rests in your hands.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ARABIA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 632 AD The prophet Muhammed, peace be upon him, accomplished what no one thought was possible - uniting the tribes of Arabia. You, Abu Bakr, has been chosen to succeed him as Caliph and expand the House of Islam.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]After a devastating war with Sassanid Persia and raging religious controversies between Chalcedonians and Monophysities, the lands of the Byzantine Empire are ripe for conquest. You know you cannot miss this opportunity, and there will be many centuries to build up your forces before the western crusaders cast their gaze towards the holy city of al-Quds.</English>
		<French>It is the year 632 AD The prophet Muhammed, peace be upon him, accomplished what no one thought was possible - uniting the tribes of Arabia. You, Abu Bakr, has been chosen to succeed him as Caliph and expand the House of Islam.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]After a devastating war with Sassanid Persia and raging religious controversies between Chalcedonians and Monophysities, the lands of the Byzantine Empire are ripe for conquest. You know you cannot miss this opportunity, and there will be many centuries to build up your forces before the western crusaders cast their gaze towards the holy city of al-Quds.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ARABIA_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>The great Saladin has gone to Paradise, after rolling back a century of Christian gains in the Blessed Land. The holy city of al-Quds is now back in Arabian hands, and the infidel "Crusader States" that butchered Muslims by the thousands have been all but eradicated.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You have been chosen as the new ruler of the Ayyubid Sultanate, and it is your duty to finish off the last of the Frankish invaders. There may be more Crusades to come, though we have reason to believe that we will be spared, at least for now. With the Christians nearly finished off and stability restored to Egypt and the Levant for the first time in centuries, it is time for a great flourishing of culture and science in the Arab World once more. We should not become too complacent, however; while we may be dominant in the Middle East for now, we should recall the example of the Abbasids and be wary of the Turks to the north...</English>
		<French>The great Saladin has gone to Paradise, after rolling back a century of Christian gains in the Blessed Land. The holy city of al-Quds is now back in Arabian hands, and the infidel "Crusader States" that butchered Muslims by the thousands have been all but eradicated.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You have been chosen as the new ruler of the Ayyubid Sultanate, and it is your duty to finish off the last of the Frankish invaders. There may be more Crusades to come, though we have reason to believe that we will be spared, at least for now. With the Christians nearly finished off and stability restored to Egypt and the Levant for the first time in centuries, it is time for a great flourishing of culture and science in the Arab World once more. We should not become too complacent, however; while we may be dominant in the Middle East for now, we should recall the example of the Abbasids and be wary of the Turks to the north...</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BULGARIA</Tag>
		<English>Many years ago, your father had finally managed to unite the warring Bulgar clans and form the powerful state of Great Bulgaria north of the Black Sea. Following his death, however, pushed by the Khazar hordes, you and your brothers had to divide the Bulgarians once more and leave your old home, migrating in different directions.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is now the year 680 AD. After years of travel across the steppe braving snow and heat, across mountains and through swamps, you and your followers have finally reached the northern borders of the Eastern Roman Empire. Tired of traveling with no home, you gather your people for one last push, to cross the Danube river and to challenge the mighty Empire itself; to claim this lustful land as yours forever.</English>
		<French>Many years ago, your father had finally managed to unite the warring Bulgar clans and form the powerful state of Great Bulgaria north of the Black Sea. Following his death, however, pushed by the Khazar hordes, you and your brothers had to divide the Bulgarians once more and leave your old home, migrating in different directions.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is now the year 680 AD. After years of travel across the steppe braving snow and heat, across mountains and through swamps, you and your followers have finally reached the northern borders of the Eastern Roman Empire. Tired of traveling with no home, you gather your people for one last push, to cross the Danube river and to challenge the mighty Empire itself; to claim this lustful land as yours forever.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BULGARIA_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>The year is 1200 AD, and the Second Bulgarian Empire is at the height of its power under the rule of Tsar Kaloyan. The Bulgarians have recently defeated the Byzantines in several key battles, and their influence extends from the Black Sea to the Adriatic coast. To the north lies the Kingdom of Hungary, ruled by King B&#233;la III, who seeks to expand his dominion over the Balkans and secure trade routes with the Western world. The Hungarian army is known for its heavy cavalry and skilled archers.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Your mission is to secure key trade routes and expand the Bulgarian Empire at the expense of your rivals.</English>
		<French>The year is 1200 AD, and the Second Bulgarian Empire is at the height of its power under the rule of Tsar Kaloyan. The Bulgarians have recently defeated the Byzantines in several key battles, and their influence extends from the Black Sea to the Adriatic coast. To the north lies the Kingdom of Hungary, ruled by King B&#233;la III, who seeks to expand his dominion over the Balkans and secure trade routes with the Western world. The Hungarian army is known for its heavy cavalry and skilled archers.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Your mission is to secure key trade routes and expand the Bulgarian Empire at the expense of your rivals.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CORDOBA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 711 AD After the long struggle, the seemingly endless flight from the upstart Abbasids in the east, many thought your Umayyad line to be extinct.[NEWLINE]Not so! You, Abd-ar-Rahman III, have led your people to a new place you now call "Al-Andalus", where you and your people may finally find a new home.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]These new lands may easily be the richest you have ever seen, so with Allah's will you might be able to build a rich and happy Caliphate - full of poetry, art and religious tolerance - to rival even that of the prophet Muhammed![NEWLINE]You only have to worry about those fanatical Christians to the north...</English>
		<French>It is the year 711 AD After the long struggle, the seemingly endless flight from the upstart Abbasids in the east, many thought your Umayyad line to be extinct.[NEWLINE]Not so! You, Abd-ar-Rahman III, have led your people to a new place you now call "Al-Andalus", where you and your people may finally find a new home.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]These new lands may easily be the richest you have ever seen, so with Allah's will you might be able to build a rich and happy Caliphate - full of poetry, art and religious tolerance - to rival even that of the prophet Muhammed![NEWLINE]You only have to worry about those fanatical Christians to the north...</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- CORDOBA is not playable in this scenario -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CORDOBA_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_VENEZIA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 810 AD. Fleeing the onslaught of the barbarian Lombards, your people and the remnants of the Byzantine Exarchate of Ravenna have settled on the inaccessible islands in the lagoon. The recent agreement between Charlemagne of the Franks and emperor Nicephorus in Constantinople means that you will be left alone for the time being. There has never been a better opportunity to build a rich trading empire that will dominate the seas!</English>
		<French>It is the year 810 AD. Fleeing the onslaught of the barbarian Lombards, your people and the remnants of the Byzantine Exarchate of Ravenna have settled on the inaccessible islands in the lagoon. The recent agreement between Charlemagne of the Franks and emperor Nicephorus in Constantinople means that you will be left alone for the time being. There has never been a better opportunity to build a rich trading empire that will dominate the seas!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_VENEZIA_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>Enrico Dandolo, you are poised on the doorstep of a pivotal moment in the history of your Republic. For centuries, your Venetians have used maritime skill and control of trade routes to become the richest nation in Europe. They continued to build on this as three great Crusades left for the Holy Land, largely sailing on fleets that you provided. Now a Fourth Crusade is gathering - but this time, they aren't able to pay their way.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Now is your chance to become the greatest Doge in Venetian history. The Crusaders have agreed to buy their passage by doing Venice a small favor. They can return rebellious Zara to Venetian control - but your plans are much grander than that. The former colony is about to triumph over their master...</English>
		<French>Enrico Dandolo, you are poised on the doorstep of a pivotal moment in the history of your Republic. For centuries, your Venetians have used maritime skill and control of trade routes to become the richest nation in Europe. They continued to build on this as three great Crusades left for the Holy Land, largely sailing on fleets that you provided. Now a Fourth Crusade is gathering - but this time, they aren't able to pay their way.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Now is your chance to become the greatest Doge in Venetian history. The Crusaders have agreed to buy their passage by doing Venice a small favor. They can return rebellious Zara to Venetian control - but your plans are much grander than that. The former colony is about to triumph over their master...</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BURGUNDY</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 843 AD. After your defeat at the hands of your brothers, you have signed the treaty of Verdun, accepting that the inheritance of Charlemagne's great empire will be split into three, with you taking the middle portion. Your exposed position - wedged between the powerful French and German kingdoms - will require great diplomatic skill, but your knights shall be the envy of all of Europe!</English>
		<French>It is the year 843 AD. After your defeat at the hands of your brothers, you have signed the treaty of Verdun, accepting that the inheritance of Charlemagne's great empire will be split into three, with you taking the middle portion. Your exposed position - wedged between the powerful French and German kingdoms - will require great diplomatic skill, but your knights shall be the envy of all of Europe!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- CORDOBA is not playable in this scenario -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BURGUNDY_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_GERMANY</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 856 AD. The great Frankish inheritance has irrevocably been split into three, with the eastern portion going to you. As the Byzantine Empress Irene rejected Charlemagne's marriage proposal, you should instead build a Holy Roman Empire for yourself!</English>
		<French>It is the year 856 AD. The great Frankish inheritance has irrevocably been split into three, with the eastern portion going to you. As the Byzantine Empress Irene rejected Charlemagne's marriage proposal, you should instead build a Holy Roman Empire for yourself!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_GERMANY_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>As Frederick I, the mighty Holy Roman Emperor, you face a delicate balance of power in a tumultuous Europe. The once-peaceful kingdom is now beset by external threats and internal strife. To the north, the mighty Kingdom of Denmark looms, its Viking warriors ever-ready to raid and pillage the Empire's borders. To the east, the Byzantine Empire teeters on the brink of collapse, its capital city Constantinople a tempting prize for any would-be conqueror. Meanwhile, the papacy in Rome wields significant influence over the Holy Roman Church, but its authority is often challenged by the growing power of the German states and the imperial nobility. As Emperor, you must navigate these treacherous waters to secure your legacy and protect the Empire's borders from foreign invaders.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you answer the call to greatness, or will your empire crumble beneath the weight of its own ambition?</English>
		<French>As Frederick I, the mighty Holy Roman Emperor, you face a delicate balance of power in a tumultuous Europe. The once-peaceful kingdom is now beset by external threats and internal strife. To the north, the mighty Kingdom of Denmark looms, its Viking warriors ever-ready to raid and pillage the Empire's borders. To the east, the Byzantine Empire teeters on the brink of collapse, its capital city Constantinople a tempting prize for any would-be conqueror. Meanwhile, the papacy in Rome wields significant influence over the Holy Roman Church, but its authority is often challenged by the growing power of the German states and the imperial nobility. As Emperor, you must navigate these treacherous waters to secure your legacy and protect the Empire's borders from foreign invaders.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you answer the call to greatness, or will your empire crumble beneath the weight of its own ambition?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_NOVGOROD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 864 AD. You, Rurik, have been invited by the warring local tribes to reestablish order; to rule over them. Novgorod the Great has the potential to grow into a fabulously wealthy city, the envy of both West and East.[NEWLINE]But can you hold the fledgling principality together when both West and East come for you?</English>
		<French>It is the year 864 AD. You, Rurik, have been invited by the warring local tribes to reestablish order; to rule over them. Novgorod the Great has the potential to grow into a fabulously wealthy city, the envy of both West and East.[NEWLINE]But can you hold the fledgling principality together when both West and East come for you?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_NOVGOROD_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>As the leader of the Republic of Novgorod, you stand at the crossroads of medieval Europe. The city's bustling markets and trade routes connect you to the vast expanse of the Baltic Sea, while your strong walls and skilled warriors protect you from the constant threat of Mongol invasions from the east. The Grand Prince of Kiev to the south seeks to expand his dominion over the region, but Novgorod's independence is not easily swayed. To the west, the Teutonic Knights and the Hanseatic League vie for influence in the Baltic region, while the mighty Kingdom of Sweden threatens your northern borders.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]As Novgorod's leader, you must navigate these complex relationships to maintain your city's autonomy and prosperity. </English>
		<French>As the leader of the Republic of Novgorod, you stand at the crossroads of medieval Europe. The city's bustling markets and trade routes connect you to the vast expanse of the Baltic Sea, while your strong walls and skilled warriors protect you from the constant threat of Mongol invasions from the east. The Grand Prince of Kiev to the south seeks to expand his dominion over the region, but Novgorod's independence is not easily swayed. To the west, the Teutonic Knights and the Hanseatic League vie for influence in the Baltic region, while the mighty Kingdom of Sweden threatens your northern borders.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]As Novgorod's leader, you must navigate these complex relationships to maintain your city's autonomy and prosperity. </French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_NORWAY</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 872 AD. The various petty kingdoms of Norway have been united by Harald Fairhair, who once vowed not to cut his hair until he was king of all of Norway.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Norway is, given its location, a surprisingly wealthy land with a large population of skilled seafarers. Skills you will have to utilize in order to keep ahead of your neighbors!</English>
		<French>It is the year 872 AD. The various petty kingdoms of Norway have been united by Harald Fairhair, who once vowed not to cut his hair until he was king of all of Norway.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Norway is, given its location, a surprisingly wealthy land with a large population of skilled seafarers. Skills you will have to utilize in order to keep ahead of your neighbors!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_NORWAY_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>As Haakon IV, you rule over a kingdom fragmented by petty feuds and rival clans. The harsh fjords and snow-capped mountains of the north are home to your loyal warriors, while the fertile valleys and bustling trading centers of the south hold the key to prosperity.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You must navigate the treacherous waters of medieval politics to unite the warring clans, expand your trade networks, and defend against external threats.</English>
		<French>As Haakon IV, you rule over a kingdom fragmented by petty feuds and rival clans. The harsh fjords and snow-capped mountains of the north are home to your loyal warriors, while the fertile valleys and bustling trading centers of the south hold the key to prosperity.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You must navigate the treacherous waters of medieval politics to unite the warring clans, expand your trade networks, and defend against external threats.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_KIEVAN_RUS</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 882 AD. After the mighty walls of Constantinople foiled your brazen attack in 866, you have decided to settle down with some of your loyal Varangians. This rich land you have just set foot on seems perfect.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The local Slavic people accept you as their leader, while your fellow Swedes, the feared Viking warriors establish themselves as the local elite. Life is good, the land is fertile, you and your descendants will surely lead your new nation, the Kievan Rus, into glory.[NEWLINE]If only you weren't having those dreams about savage hordes rising in the east...</English>
		<French>It is the year 882 AD. After the mighty walls of Constantinople foiled your brazen attack in 866, you have decided to settle down with some of your loyal Varangians. This rich land you have just set foot on seems perfect.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The local Slavic people accept you as their leader, while your fellow Swedes, the feared Viking warriors establish themselves as the local elite. Life is good, the land is fertile, you and your descendants will surely lead your new nation, the Kievan Rus, into glory.[NEWLINE]If only you weren't having those dreams about savage hordes rising in the east...</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_KIEVAN_RUS_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>Your capital city Kiev shines with golden domes and vibrant markets, while your armies of Varangian guardsmen and Slavic warriors are feared by all who know their name. The Byzantine Empire to the south seeks to exert its influence over Kievan Rus, but your Orthodox Church and your people remain fiercely loyal to your rule.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you forge strong ties with Byzantium, expand your trade networks through the Baltic ports, or launch raids on foreign shores to secure your legacy? The fate of Kievan Rus hangs in the balance.</English>
		<French>Your capital city Kiev shines with golden domes and vibrant markets, while your armies of Varangian guardsmen and Slavic warriors are feared by all who know their name. The Byzantine Empire to the south seeks to exert its influence over Kievan Rus, but your Orthodox Church and your people remain fiercely loyal to your rule.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you forge strong ties with Byzantium, expand your trade networks through the Baltic ports, or launch raids on foreign shores to secure your legacy? The fate of Kievan Rus hangs in the balance.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_HUNGARY</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 895 AD. While your glorious armies warred with the Byzantines and Bulgarians, the traitorous Pechenegs attacked your families and the remaining tribes in the homeland, Etelkoz. Without defences they had to flee, and you know you cannot lead them back to their previous home.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]After taking your nation further to the west you finally reach the Carpathian Basin, which is everything your people have ever needed: wealthy, fertile, and most importantly, easily defendable. Immediately falling in love with it, you claim these lands as yours forever.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]One thing is clear to you though: all the previous empires and civilizations that once held these lands have faded away throughout the centuries. You will have to accept some of the more developed Western European ways if you are to establish a long-living and successful nation in the middle of Europe.</English>
		<French>It is the year 895 AD. While your glorious armies warred with the Byzantines and Bulgarians, the traitorous Pechenegs attacked your families and the remaining tribes in the homeland, Etelkoz. Without defences they had to flee, and you know you cannot lead them back to their previous home.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]After taking your nation further to the west you finally reach the Carpathian Basin, which is everything your people have ever needed: wealthy, fertile, and most importantly, easily defendable. Immediately falling in love with it, you claim these lands as yours forever.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]One thing is clear to you though: all the previous empires and civilizations that once held these lands have faded away throughout the centuries. You will have to accept some of the more developed Western European ways if you are to establish a long-living and successful nation in the middle of Europe.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_HUNGARY_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>As Bela III, the King of Hungary, you sit upon the throne of the Golden Bull, surrounded by the rolling hills and fertile plains of the Carpathian Basin. Your kingdom is a crossroads of Europe, where the Latin West meets the Orthodox East, and the Mongol Horde looms in the east.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]One thing is clear to you though: all the previous empires and civilizations that once held these lands have faded away throughout the centuries. You will have to accept some of the more developed Western European ways if you are to establish a long-living and successful nation in the middle of Europe.</English>
		<French>As Bela III, the King of Hungary, you sit upon the throne of the Golden Bull, surrounded by the rolling hills and fertile plains of the Carpathian Basin. Your kingdom is a crossroads of Europe, where the Latin West meets the Orthodox East, and the Mongol Horde looms in the east.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]One thing is clear to you though: all the previous empires and civilizations that once held these lands have faded away throughout the centuries. You will have to accept some of the more developed Western European ways if you are to establish a long-living and successful nation in the middle of Europe.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SPAIN</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 910 AD. While the Moors never really held sway over your northern parts of Spain, the Caliphate of Cordoba under Abd-ar-Rahman III is stronger than ever. Christians are tolerated there, but lower taxes drive them towards conversion and eternal damnation. You must launch the Reconquista and liberate them before it is too late!</English>
		<French>It is the year 910 AD. While the Moors never really held sway over your northern parts of Spain, the Caliphate of Cordoba under Abd-ar-Rahman III is stronger than ever. Christians are tolerated there, but lower taxes drive them towards conversion and eternal damnation. You must launch the Reconquista and liberate them before it is too late!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SPAIN_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>As Isabella, you rule over a kingdom that spans the Iberian Peninsula, from the snow-capped Pyrenees to the sun-baked lands of Andalusia. The mighty Kingdom of Le&#243;n to the north seeks to expand its borders at Castile's expense, while the Muslim taifas of Andalusia offer a tantalizing prize for any would-be conqueror. Meanwhile, the Crown of Aragon to the east plots its own expansion into the Mediterranean, its fleets and armies poised to strike.[NEWLINE]As you navigate the complex web of alliances and rivalries, you must also contend with the growing power of the nobility within your own kingdom. </English>
		<French>As Isabella, you rule over a kingdom that spans the Iberian Peninsula, from the snow-capped Pyrenees to the sun-baked lands of Andalusia. The mighty Kingdom of Le&#243;n to the north seeks to expand its borders at Castile's expense, while the Muslim taifas of Andalusia offer a tantalizing prize for any would-be conqueror. Meanwhile, the Crown of Aragon to the east plots its own expansion into the Mediterranean, its fleets and armies poised to strike.[NEWLINE]As you navigate the complex web of alliances and rivalries, you must also contend with the growing power of the nobility within your own kingdom. </French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_DENMARK</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 936 AD. Denmark, once a collection of petty kingdoms, has been united under Gorm the Old, and forged into a centralized state.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Your country now stands at a crossroads of sorts, with Viking influences and craftmanship from the North and Christian influences and statesmanship from the South. Take advantage of both for as long as you can, but eventually you will have to choose!</English>
		<French>It is the year 936 AD. Denmark, once a collection of petty kingdoms, has been united under Gorm the Old, and forged into a centralized state.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Your country now stands at a crossroads of sorts, with Viking influences and craftmanship from the North and Christian influences and statesmanship from the South. Take advantage of both for as long as you can, but eventually you will have to choose!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_DENMARK_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1200 AD. You rule over a kingdom that stretches from the frozen tundras of Greenland to the fertile plains of Jutland. Your capital city Roskilde shines with the grandeur of the Viking Age, while your armies of huscarls and housecarls are feared by all who know their name.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you forge strong ties with the Holy Roman Empire, expand your trade networks through the Baltic ports, or launch raids on foreign shores to secure your legacy? The fate of Denmark hangs in the balance.</English>
		<French>It is the year 1200 AD. You rule over a kingdom that stretches from the frozen tundras of Greenland to the fertile plains of Jutland. Your capital city Roskilde shines with the grandeur of the Viking Age, while your armies of huscarls and housecarls are feared by all who know their name.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you forge strong ties with the Holy Roman Empire, expand your trade networks through the Baltic ports, or launch raids on foreign shores to secure your legacy? The fate of Denmark hangs in the balance.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SCOTLAND</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 960 AD. While you are the sole ruler over some loyal subjects, most Scottish men still remember the shadows of the past. Your goal is to unite all the tribes and clans of Scotland and establish the "last free kingdom".[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You can choose to pass the old walls of Hadrian or stay behind it, but it would be wise to gather some mighty allies on the Continent. Whatever path you choose, it is clear to you: your nation is destined to survive the storms of centuries to come, and be bright forever. Make the Highlanders proud and show the world: Scotland, be foe or ally, solid as a rock!</English>
		<French>It is the year 960 AD. While you are the sole ruler over some loyal subjects, most Scottish men still remember the shadows of the past. Your goal is to unite all the tribes and clans of Scotland and establish the "last free kingdom".[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You can choose to pass the old walls of Hadrian or stay behind it, but it would be wise to gather some mighty allies on the Continent. Whatever path you choose, it is clear to you: your nation is destined to survive the storms of centuries to come, and be bright forever. Make the Highlanders proud and show the world: Scotland, be foe or ally, solid as a rock!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SCOTLAND_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>As the King of Scotland, you rule over a land of rugged beauty and fierce pride. From the misty mountains of the Highlands to the fertile Lowlands, your kingdom stretches from sea to sea. The English crown seeks to exert its influence over your kingdom, and the Norman Conquest of 1066 has left a lasting legacy of rivalries and alliances. But your kingdom is not isolated from the rest of Europe. The Kingdom of France, to the south, has long been friendly for a long time.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you rise to the occasion and build a prosperous and powerful kingdom, or will you succumb to the pressures of rival kingdoms and internal conflicts?</English>
		<French>As the King of Scotland, you rule over a land of rugged beauty and fierce pride. From the misty mountains of the Highlands to the fertile Lowlands, your kingdom stretches from sea to sea. The English crown seeks to exert its influence over your kingdom, and the Norman Conquest of 1066 has left a lasting legacy of rivalries and alliances. But your kingdom is not isolated from the rest of Europe. The Kingdom of France, to the south, has long been friendly for a long time.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you rise to the occasion and build a prosperous and powerful kingdom, or will you succumb to the pressures of rival kingdoms and internal conflicts?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_POLAND</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 966 AD. Worried by the threat of a unified German Empire, you have accepted Christianity to protect your land against foreign aggression. With knowing your people are safe - at least for now - you can start to strengthen your position in Central Europe.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]If all your plans goes well, your nation will be a shining example of liberty and toleration for the rest of Europe - no inquisition will be needed, and the Szlactha will curb any autocratic tendencies!</English>
		<French>It is the year 966 AD. Worried by the threat of a unified German Empire, you have accepted Christianity to protect your land against foreign aggression. With knowing your people are safe - at least for now - you can start to strengthen your position in Central Europe.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]If all your plans goes well, your nation will be a shining example of liberty and toleration for the rest of Europe - no inquisition will be needed, and the Szlactha will curb any autocratic tendencies!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_POLAND_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>.</English>
		<French>In the distant lands of Eastern Europe, the Kingdom of Poland struggles to maintain its independence in the face of Teutonic expansion.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The fate of Poland hangs in the balance, and it is up to you to determine its destiny. </French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_GENOA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1016 AD. Together with the Pisans, you have just defeated the Muslim pirates, assuring Christian dominance of Sardinia and blocking Muslim expansion. The need for security forces the republic you serve to assert an ever greater responsibility: the protection of the whole Italian peninsula.[NEWLINE]This is your chance to build a magnificent merchant republic! With enough resources, even the fabled cities of the eastern Mediterranean will lay at your hands.</English>
		<French>It is the year 1016 AD. Together with the Pisans, you have just defeated the Muslim pirates, assuring Christian dominance of Sardinia and blocking Muslim expansion. The need for security forces the republic you serve to assert an ever greater responsibility: the protection of the whole Italian peninsula.[NEWLINE]This is your chance to build a magnificent merchant republic! With enough resources, even the fabled cities of the eastern Mediterranean will lay at your hands.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_GENOA_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>You are the Doge of Genoa, ruler of a powerful maritime republic that has long dominated the Mediterranean. As you sit upon your throne in Palazzo Ducale, you gaze out upon the bustling ports and merchant vessels that line the city's waterfront.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you rise to the challenge and lead Genoa to a new era of greatness, or will the forces of decline and decay tear your city apart?</English>
		<French>You are the Doge of Genoa, ruler of a powerful maritime republic that has long dominated the Mediterranean. As you sit upon your throne in Palazzo Ducale, you gaze out upon the bustling ports and merchant vessels that line the city's waterfront.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you rise to the challenge and lead Genoa to a new era of greatness, or will the forces of decline and decay tear your city apart?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MOROCCO</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1041 AD, and the Almoravid dynasty is on the rise. You are the rightful ruler of the Berbers, destined to establish a great, long-lasting empire in the Maghreb. With Allah's help, you will follow the path of the Idrisids, and the great cities of Morocco are waiting to be filled with art and faith.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The rich, fertile coastline is also yours to claim, though it will not be easy. You will have to deal not only with the Spanish and the Portuguese, for the whole Christian world will come to their aid. Are you up to the task, with the help of your loyal Black Guards? Will you be able to protect your brothers in Al-Andalus? The Christian filth shall pay dearly for their atrocities; make your ancestors proud!</English>
		<French>It is the year 1041 AD, and the Almoravid dynasty is on the rise. You are the rightful ruler of the Berbers, destined to establish a great, long-lasting empire in the Maghreb. With Allah's help, you will follow the path of the Idrisids, and the great cities of Morocco are waiting to be filled with art and faith.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The rich, fertile coastline is also yours to claim, though it will not be easy. You will have to deal not only with the Spanish and the Portuguese, for the whole Christian world will come to their aid. Are you up to the task, with the help of your loyal Black Guards? Will you be able to protect your brothers in Al-Andalus? The Christian filth shall pay dearly for their atrocities; make your ancestors proud!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MOROCCO_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>The Almohad Caliphate is a powerful force in North Africa, with its capital at Marrakech serving as a hub of trade, culture, and learning. The city is a melting pot of cultures, with merchants and scholars from across the Mediterranean coming to trade goods and exchange ideas.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The fate of Morocco hangs in the balance, as you navigate the complexities of politics, diplomacy, and warfare.</English>
		<French>The Almohad Caliphate is a powerful force in North Africa, with its capital at Marrakech serving as a hub of trade, culture, and learning. The city is a melting pot of cultures, with merchants and scholars from across the Mediterranean coming to trade goods and exchange ideas.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The fate of Morocco hangs in the balance, as you navigate the complexities of politics, diplomacy, and warfare.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ENGLAND</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1066 AD. The battlefield of Hastings lays quiet. Harold Godwinson is dead, but not before he took care of the Norwegians for you. Though Scotland may be the source of trouble sometimes, the rich estates of England will fund the defense of your ancestral possessions back in France. No longer William the Bastard, henceforth you will be known as William the Conqueror!</English>
		<French>It is the year 1066 AD. The battlefield of Hastings lays quiet. Harold Godwinson is dead, but not before he took care of the Norwegians for you. Though Scotland may be the source of trouble sometimes, the rich estates of England will fund the defense of your ancestral possessions back in France. No longer William the Bastard, henceforth you will be known as William the Conqueror!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ENGLAND_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>The 13th Century dawns over an England in turmoil. The great Lionheart lies dead, and his soldiers returning from the Third Crusade are dejected that they never reached the Holy City despite the Crusade's general success. The once-mighty Angevin Empire now faces growing threats from a rebellious Scotland in the north, a resurgent France keen to reclaim its western lands, and dissension amongst the English barons who resent the king's despotic rule.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You must lead the English people through the looming civil wars and foreign invasions and emerge stronger than ever. The French will soon be looking to conquer your ancestral lands on the continent, but if you play your cards correctly you may be able to turn the tables and claim the French crown for yourself. With technological prowess, industrial might, and your strong leadership, you will turn this island nation into an empire on which the sun never sets!</English>
		<French>The 13th Century dawns over an England in turmoil. The great Lionheart lies dead, and his soldiers returning from the Third Crusade are dejected that they never reached the Holy City despite the Crusade's general success. The once-mighty Angevin Empire now faces growing threats from a rebellious Scotland in the north, a resurgent France keen to reclaim its western lands, and dissension amongst the English barons who resent the king's despotic rule.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You must lead the English people through the looming civil wars and foreign invasions and emerge stronger than ever. The French will soon be looking to conquer your ancestral lands on the continent, but if you play your cards correctly you may be able to turn the tables and claim the French crown for yourself. With technological prowess, industrial might, and your strong leadership, you will turn this island nation into an empire on which the sun never sets!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PORTUGAL</Tag>
		<English>Your small county of Portugal has just decided to break its familial ties with the Kingdom of Le&#243;n and declare its independence, creating the Kingdom of Portugal. It is 1139 AD, and you, Afonso Henriques, are the king of this newly formed kingdom.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is time to strengthen your position by advancing to the south and continuing the Reconquista, but you should also prepare for your ultimate goal: to expand beyond the Iberian Peninsula. Your position makes it ideal to claim the riches of North Africa and the Atlantic islands - and who knows, maybe even much further lands than those.</English>
		<French>Your small county of Portugal has just decided to break its familial ties with the Kingdom of Le&#243;n and declare its independence, creating the Kingdom of Portugal. It is 1139 AD, and you, Afonso Henriques, are the king of this newly formed kingdom.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is time to strengthen your position by advancing to the south and continuing the Reconquista, but you should also prepare for your ultimate goal: to expand beyond the Iberian Peninsula. Your position makes it ideal to claim the riches of North Africa and the Atlantic islands - and who knows, maybe even much further lands than those.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PORTUGAL_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1200 AD. You are King Afonso III of Portugal, ruler of a small yet resolute nation nestled between the Atlantic Ocean and the Iberian Peninsula. Your kingdom's rugged coastline and fertile interior offer endless opportunities for exploration, trade, and expansion - but so too do the threats of Castile, Aragon, and the Almohad Caliphate.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you rise to the challenge and lead your nation to greatness?</English>
		<French>It is the year 1200 AD. You are King Afonso III of Portugal, ruler of a small yet resolute nation nestled between the Atlantic Ocean and the Iberian Peninsula. Your kingdom's rugged coastline and fertile interior offer endless opportunities for exploration, trade, and expansion - but so too do the threats of Castile, Aragon, and the Almohad Caliphate.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Will you rise to the challenge and lead your nation to greatness?</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ARAGON</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, my lord! It is the blessed year of 1164 AD, under your new rule these lands will finally have the possibility for strong, centralized rule. And the people of Aragon are in dire need of our guidance, as the situation is very tense; the various Principalities, Duchies and Kingdoms in the region have many diverse interests pulling in every which way, putting a heavy toll on the local populace. Religious differences are also leading to harsh tensions and conflict with the Muslims to the south.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Crown of Aragon shall rule over many dominions, but your hands are also tied by the Aragonese Law. You must decide where and how to expand to make your people calm and happy.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Surrounded by stronger and more united states, you must fight with both sword and pen. You can choose to expand by joining the Reconquista, but the power vacuum in the vast Mediterranean is also very tempting. Small but rich kingdoms could be yours if you play your cards well, an empire to span across the sea.</English>
		<French>Greetings, my lord! It is the blessed year of 1164 AD, under your new rule these lands will finally have the possibility for strong, centralized rule. And the people of Aragon are in dire need of our guidance, as the situation is very tense; the various Principalities, Duchies and Kingdoms in the region have many diverse interests pulling in every which way, putting a heavy toll on the local populace. Religious differences are also leading to harsh tensions and conflict with the Muslims to the south.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Crown of Aragon shall rule over many dominions, but your hands are also tied by the Aragonese Law. You must decide where and how to expand to make your people calm and happy.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Surrounded by stronger and more united states, you must fight with both sword and pen. You can choose to expand by joining the Reconquista, but the power vacuum in the vast Mediterranean is also very tempting. Small but rich kingdoms could be yours if you play your cards well, an empire to span across the sea.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ARAGON_1200AD</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, my lord! It is the blessed year of 1200 AD, under your new rule these lands will finally have the possibility for strong, centralized rule. And the people of Aragon are in dire need of our guidance, as the situation is very tense; the various Principalities, Duchies and Kingdoms in the region have many diverse interests pulling in every which way, putting a heavy toll on the local populace. Religious differences are also leading to harsh tensions and conflict with the Muslims to the south.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Crown of Aragon shall rule over many dominions, but your hands are also tied by the Aragonese Law. You must decide where and how to expand to make your people calm and happy.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Surrounded by stronger and more united states, you must fight with both sword and pen. You can choose to expand by joining the Reconquista, but the power vacuum in the vast Mediterranean is also very tempting. Small but rich kingdoms could be yours if you play your cards well, an empire to span across the sea.</English>
		<French>Greetings, my lord! It is the blessed year of 1200 AD, under your new rule these lands will finally have the possibility for strong, centralized rule. And the people of Aragon are in dire need of our guidance, as the situation is very tense; the various Principalities, Duchies and Kingdoms in the region have many diverse interests pulling in every which way, putting a heavy toll on the local populace. Religious differences are also leading to harsh tensions and conflict with the Muslims to the south.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Crown of Aragon shall rule over many dominions, but your hands are also tied by the Aragonese Law. You must decide where and how to expand to make your people calm and happy.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Surrounded by stronger and more united states, you must fight with both sword and pen. You can choose to expand by joining the Reconquista, but the power vacuum in the vast Mediterranean is also very tempting. Small but rich kingdoms could be yours if you play your cards well, an empire to span across the sea.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SWEDEN</Tag>
		<English>For the last few hundred years, Sweden has in some ways been the least developed of the Scandinavian nations. Though several rulers at Uppsala have claimed kingship over Sweden, few have had any power outside Uppland. Christianisation has been slow as well. Southern Sweden was even the target of a crusade less than a century ago, yet pagan beliefs are still important in much of the country.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is now the year 1210 AD, and this year things are to change. Eric the Survivor has managed to destroy his rivals in a bloody civil war and become the first ever Swedish King to be crowned by the Church. The separatists are rapidly losing power and the people of Uppland are about to lose their ancient privileges. The stage is set for the consolidation of Sweden.</English>
		<French>For the last few hundred years, Sweden has in some ways been the least developed of the Scandinavian nations. Though several rulers at Uppsala have claimed kingship over Sweden, few have had any power outside Uppland. Christianisation has been slow as well. Southern Sweden was even the target of a crusade less than a century ago, yet pagan beliefs are still important in much of the country.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]It is now the year 1210 AD, and this year things are to change. Eric the Survivor has managed to destroy his rivals in a bloody civil war and become the first ever Swedish King to be crowned by the Church. The separatists are rapidly losing power and the people of Uppland are about to lose their ancient privileges. The stage is set for the consolidation of Sweden.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PRUSSIA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1224 AD. The Northern Crusades have been raging since 1193 and the Livonian Brothers of the Sword - the Sword Brethren - are making slow progress in Livonia. Konrad I of Masovia, a Polish Duke, has now invited the Teutonic Order to conquer and Christianise the pagan Prussian tribes.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Teutonic Order has experience from defending both the Holy Land and the borderlands of Hungary, and is able to call on the finest knights of Europe. A speedy subjugation of Prussia might not only decide the war in the Crusaders' favor, but provide the foundations of an empire.</English>
		<French>It is the year 1224 AD. The Northern Crusades have been raging since 1193 and the Livonian Brothers of the Sword - the Sword Brethren - are making slow progress in Livonia. Konrad I of Masovia, a Polish Duke, has now invited the Teutonic Order to conquer and Christianise the pagan Prussian tribes.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Teutonic Order has experience from defending both the Holy Land and the borderlands of Hungary, and is able to call on the finest knights of Europe. A speedy subjugation of Prussia might not only decide the war in the Crusaders' favor, but provide the foundations of an empire.</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_LITHUANIA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1236 AD. Strange invaders - calling themselves Teutonic Knights and worshiping a man on a cross - have disturbed the tranquility of the land. However, they are not invincible. You, Mindaugas, have shown that they bleed and die, just like other men.[NEWLINE]It is high time to drive them out, as the ancient religion of your ancestors is surely also the best for you. Make them proud!</English>
		<French>It is the year 1236 AD. Strange invaders - calling themselves Teutonic Knights and worshiping a man on a cross - have disturbed the tranquility of the land. However, they are not invincible. You, Mindaugas, have shown that they bleed and die, just like other men.[NEWLINE]It is high time to drive them out, as the ancient religion of your ancestors is surely also the best for you. Make them proud!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_AUSTRIA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1282 AD. In the last few decades your dynasty, the Habsburgs, have been quickly gaining strength in the Holy Roman Empire through your ever-growing estates.[NEWLINE]Now King of the Romans and having just acquired the rich Duchy of Austria, you are much more powerful than you had ever dreamt of. Still, your ambitions are forcing you to climb much higher, and who knows where will be the end?[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Leave the waging of wars to others! You, happy Austria, marry; for the realms which Mars awards to others, Venus transfers to you. Navigate carefully through the intricate diplomacy of central Europe, and your dynasty will still stand proudly many hundreds of years from now!</English>
		<French>It is the year 1282 AD. In the last few decades your dynasty, the Habsburgs, have been quickly gaining strength in the Holy Roman Empire through your ever-growing estates.[NEWLINE]Now King of the Romans and having just acquired the rich Duchy of Austria, you are much more powerful than you had ever dreamt of. Still, your ambitions are forcing you to climb much higher, and who knows where will be the end?[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Leave the waging of wars to others! You, happy Austria, marry; for the realms which Mars awards to others, Venus transfers to you. Navigate carefully through the intricate diplomacy of central Europe, and your dynasty will still stand proudly many hundreds of years from now!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_TURKEY</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1356 AD. Allah has truly shown his favour towards you. Firstly, the Black Death decimated the Byzantines in the cities, but largely spared the countryside of the Turks. Secondly, the earthquake in 1354 leveled all the walls of Gallipoli, leaving the strategic fortress ripe for conquest. The way to Europe is open, and you only need to reach out and grasp it![NEWLINE]If you play your cards right, your Ottoman Empire will surely be unstoppable!</English>
		<French>It is the year 1356 AD. Allah has truly shown his favour towards you. Firstly, the Black Death decimated the Byzantines in the cities, but largely spared the countryside of the Turks. Secondly, the earthquake in 1354 leveled all the walls of Gallipoli, leaving the strategic fortress ripe for conquest. The way to Europe is open, and you only need to reach out and grasp it![NEWLINE]If you play your cards right, your Ottoman Empire will surely be unstoppable!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MOSCOVY</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1380 AD. The shadow of the Mongol Golden Horde has loomed over the land for more than a hundred years. With the people chafing under their oppression, fear has prevented effective resistance.[NEWLINE]All has changed now on the fields of Kulikovo, where you led your coalition to victory. The road ahead is long and arduous, but in the end, Mother Russia will prevail!</English>
		<French>It is the year 1380 AD. The shadow of the Mongol Golden Horde has loomed over the land for more than a hundred years. With the people chafing under their oppression, fear has prevented effective resistance.[NEWLINE]All has changed now on the fields of Kulikovo, where you led your coalition to victory. The road ahead is long and arduous, but in the end, Mother Russia will prevail!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_NETHERLANDS</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1581 AD. The Low Countries have been under foreign rule - German, Burgundian, Austrian, and now Spanish - for a long time.[NEWLINE]This is your chance, though! The Act of Abjuration was signed on July 22nd of this year, absolving the provinces of the Union of Utrecht of their oath of allegiance to Philip II of Spain and finally declaring the independence of your beloved Dutch nation.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]While it will be many years before our independence is finally accepted, this will be the start of an empire that will become one of the wealthiest civilizations in the world!</English>
		<French>It is the year 1581 AD. The Low Countries have been under foreign rule - German, Burgundian, Austrian, and now Spanish - for a long time.[NEWLINE]This is your chance, though! The Act of Abjuration was signed on July 22nd of this year, absolving the provinces of the Union of Utrecht of their oath of allegiance to Philip II of Spain and finally declaring the independence of your beloved Dutch nation.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]While it will be many years before our independence is finally accepted, this will be the start of an empire that will become one of the wealthiest civilizations in the world!</French>
		<German>.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
