<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- RFCE Techs Pedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_ALCHEMY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A philosophy and attempt to achieve ultimate wisdom, alchemy began in Classical Greece but developed in Persia and later Europe during the Middle Ages. The goals of the alchemist were the "transmutation" of common metals into gold or silver, the creation of an elixir of life and the search for a universal solvent, and the quest to find the "philosophers stone" in the pursuit of these goals. Alchemists like Paracelsus and Issac Newton enjoyed great prestige and made contributions to early chemical processes like ore-testing and refining, metallurgy and the production of gunpowder, dyes, ceramics and glass. And the Islamic alchemists like Geber and al Kindi also laid the important foundations of modern scientific chemistry.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die &#228;ltesten bekannten Aufzeichnungen &#252;ber die Alchemie, insbesondere die Tabula Smaragdina, stammen aus dem alten &#196;gypten und dem hellenistischen Griechenland. Da diese zun&#228;chst ausschlie&#223;lich &#252;ber die arabische Welt nach Europa gelangten, stammt das Wort Alchemie vermutlich von arabisch ?al-?imiya oder ?al-kimiya und &#228;gyptisch k(he)m f&#252;r "schwarz" ab, das wiederum seinen Ursprung im Griechischen (eventuell chymia bzw. chemeia f&#252;r "Metallguss" oder auch chymos f&#252;r "Fl&#252;ssigkeit") zu haben scheint. Die Bedeutung des Wortes ist bislang nicht sicher gekl&#228;rt und die m&#246;glichen Auslegungen sind vielf&#228;ltig. Paracelsus und Georg Agricola verwendeten die Worte chymia bzw. chymista f&#252;r die Alchemie. Beispielsweise l&#228;sst sich Alchemie mit "Kunst der &#196;gypter", in einer anderen Lesart dagegen als "Lehre des Gie&#223;ens" &#252;bersetzen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Ein Ziel der Alchemisten war die Transmutation von unedlen Metallen zu Gold und Silber. Bei der Umwandlung der Metalle gab es einen praktischen Teil, der den sorgf&#228;ltigen Umgang mit den Destillations-, Extraktions-, Sublimationsapparaturen voraussetzte, sowie eine theoretische, religi&#246;se Komponente. W&#228;hrend dieser Umwandlungen sollte sich auch die Seele des Alchemisten l&#228;utern und den Mikrokosmos im Makrokosmos widerspiegeln.[PARAGRAPH:2]In der griechisch arabischen Alchemie waren die Urelemente Erde, Wasser, Luft und Feuer nach Empedokles bekannt, die f&#252;r alle Umwandlung verantwortlich waren. Ebenso gab es nach Aristoteles vier Ureigenschaften (warm - kalt, trocken - feucht) die auch eine Entsprechung in der Alchemie hatten.[PARAGRAPH:2]Wir verdanken der experimentellen Anwendung der Alchemie unter anderem die (Wieder-)Erfindung des Porzellans und Schwarzpulvers in Europa. Das Porzellan zum Beispiel ist ein Abfallprodukt der Suche nach Gold. Ein Alchemist am s&#228;chsischen Hof, Johann Friedrich B&#246;ttger, rettete sein Leben, indem er seinem Arbeitgeber wenigstens "Wei&#223;es Gold" liefern konnte. Ber&#252;hmte Alchemisten waren z. B. Vincenzo Casciarolo aus Bologna, der 1604 erstmals einen Phosphoreszenz-Farbstoff herstellte, den sogenannten "Bologneser Leuchtstein" oder "Lapis Solaris". Diese Entdeckung bef&#246;rderte Diskussionen &#252;ber die Natur des Lichtes und f&#252;hrte bereits 1652 zu ersten spektroskopischen Untersuchungen. Der Hamburger Hennig Brand war ein weiterer wichtiger Alchemist. Er entdeckte 1669 den wei&#223;en Phosphor und dessen Chemilumineszenz ("Phosphorus mirabilis") und damit die erste Chemilumineszenzreaktion &#252;berhaupt. Diese Chemilumineszenzreaktion fand als Mitscherlich-Probe Eingang in die forensische Chemie und ist auch heute noch ein beeindruckendes Experiment.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_ARABIC_KNOWLEDGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Islamic world from the 9thC experienced a Golden Age of science and learning in which scholars translated all the world's knowledge into Arabic. Thousands of works from Greece, Rome and India were preserved and studied by Muslim scholars who developed from them even greater scientific, mathematical and astronomical achievements. For over 500 years Islamic knowledge in every field surpassed anything else in the world, including the astronomical advances of Al Biruni; the introduction of numerals and invention of algebra by Al Khwarizmi; the optical breakthroughs of al Haytham and the development of modern chemistry by Geber, of whom Issac Newton may have referred when he said, "I have stood upon the shoulders of giants".</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Im Haus der Weisheit arbeiteten 90 Menschen an wissenschaftlichen &#220;bersetzungen vor allem aus dem Griechischen in die Arabische Sprache. al-Ma?mun schickte daf&#252;r einen Gelehrten seines Hofs nach Byzanz und bat den griechischen Kaiser, ihm mathematische Werke (u. a. die des Euklid) zu &#252;bergeben. Im Haus wurden alle Werke der Antike &#252;bersetzt, die aufzufinden waren, unter anderem von Galen, Hippokrates, Platon, Aristoteles, Ptolem&#228;us oder Archimedes. Unter der Leitung des Christen Hunayn ibn Ishaq entwickelten sie ebenso eine Technik des konzeptionellen anstelle des w&#246;rtlichen &#220;bersetzens.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Bagdad arbeiten nach Aussagen des Historikers al-Qufiti in der Epoche des Aufbau des Hauses 37 Christen, 8 Sab&#228;er und 9 Juden. Sie waren aufgrund ihrer Fachkenntnisse sowie Sprachkenntnisse wichtig f&#252;r den Aufbau des Hauses. Unter den Mitarbeitern waren der Arzt Hunayn ibn Ishaq, der Astronom Thabit ibn Qurra und der Mathematiker al-Chwarizmi.[PARAGRAPH:2]Neben dem &#220;bersetzungszentrum z&#228;hlt man zum Haus der Weisheit auch ein Observatorium, eine Akademie und eine reichhaltige Bibliothek sowie ein Krankenhaus. Nach dem Vorbild der Institution wurden &#228;hnliche Einrichtungen in C&#243;rdoba und Sevilla geschaffen. Der Kalif al-Hakim lie&#223; um 1000 ein Haus der Weisheit in Kairo einrichten.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_ARABIC_MEDICINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The prophet Muhammad himself recognized the infectious nature of disease and that for every disease there was always a cause and a cure. Islamic medicine translated Greek and Indian sources into Arabic greatly expanding medical knowledge and the practices found in the work of Galen and Hippocrates. Muslim physicians set up the first hospitals, medical schools, clinics and operating theatres, pioneering thousands of new remedies and procedures, many unmatched even in the 19thC. But it was the contributions of scientists like Albucasis, considered the father of modern surgery, and Avicenna, still regarded as the father of all modern medicine, that make them some of the greatest medical scholars and innovators of history.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die arabische Medizin baute direkt auf den antiken Vorl&#228;ufern auf. Die griechischen und lateinischen Texte wurden teils im Original tradiert, teils ins Arabische &#252;bersetzt. Im arabischen Raum erfuhr die Antike Medizin noch einmal eine Bl&#252;te, da arabische Mediziner auf ihr aufbauend auch zu neuen Erkenntnissen kamen. Die Araber entwickelten Spezialistentum und z. B. auch Krankenh&#228;user von einer Qualit&#228;t, wie sie im Westen erst im 19. Jahrhundert wiederzufinden waren. Ein Teil des heute vorhandenen Wissens &#252;ber die griechische Medizin wurde auf Arabisch festgehalten und sp&#228;ter wieder ins Griechische &#252;bersetzt. Einer der bedeutendsten &#196;rzte dieser Zeit war der Perser Avicenna, seine Schrift Qanun galt seit dem 12. Jahrhundert als ein Standardwerk der Medizin. Ebenfalls von Bedeutung war der auch aus Persien stammende Rhazes, der einer der ersten Vertreter einer auf Experimenten beruhenden Medizin war.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_ARCHITECTURE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As a process, architecture involves the designing and constructing buildings which first evolved to address the human needs of shelter, security and worship. Texts on architecture first appeared in Classical Greece and Rome and continued throughout the Middle Ages in Europe. With the Renaissance, buildings were constructed by individual designers and master builders like Brunelleschi, Michelangelo and Inigo Jones, combining the functions of artist, architect and engineer. As scientific knowledge advanced with the use of new materials and technologies, architecture and civil engineering began to diverge, allowing the architects like Bernini, Palladio and Christopher Wren to concentrate on the more aesthetic aspects of building design.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]W&#228;hrend sich die Bauten in der Fr&#252;hgeschichte der Menschheit zumeist nur an die unmittelbaren Bed&#252;rfnisse der Bewohner - also an Wohnen, Lagerung und Viehhaltung - orientieren, entwickelte sich die Architektur der westlichen Welt in Europa und sp&#228;ter dann in anderen Kontinenten in mehreren "doppelten Zyklen", von einem eher einfacheren Stil hin zur verst&#228;rkten Verwendung des Ornaments und der Plastizit&#228;t sowie von einer eher horizontalen Gliederung hin zur verst&#228;rkten Betonung der Vertikalen.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_ARISTOCRACY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Aristocracy refers to a form of government where the most prominent citizens rule, or as the highest class in society which holds the bulk of land, money and power. In Europe during the Middle Ages, a hereditary class of arbitrary rulers became known as the "nobility". In the feudal system, these nobles normally held a "fief" under "vassalage",ie. property and wealth in exchange for allegiance and military service to the Monarch or Lord and became a ruling caste holding a hereditary title, enjoying fiscal, political and other privileges. The military power of the aristocracy gradually declined as Kings began to organize cohesive national armies and their economic power declined with the rise of the urban merchant classes.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Begriff Aristokratie bezeichnet in der ideengeschichtlichen Forschung die Herrschaft einer Gruppe weniger Auserw&#228;hlter, das hei&#223;t dass eine relativ kleine Zahl besonders bef&#228;higter Individuen politische Leitungsfunktionen wahrnimmt, wobei die Art der Bef&#228;higung nicht n&#228;her bestimmt ist. Die urspr&#252;ngliche Wortbedeutung ist "Herrschaft der Besten". In der politischen Wirklichkeit wurde die Eigenschaft zu "den Besten" zu geh&#246;ren meist mit der Zugeh&#246;rigkeit zu einer adligen Oberschicht gleichgesetzt, weshalb man unter Aristokratie seit der Antike die Herrschaft des Adels verstand.[PARAGRAPH:2]In der historischen Literatur wird der Begriff Aristokratie oft synonym zu Adel als der Gesamtheit aller Adligen in einem bestimmten geografischen Bereich verwendet. Im Mittelalter werden darunter zumeist keine merklichen Vorz&#252;ge, sondern die famili&#228;re Abstammung und die Zugeh&#246;rigkeit zu einer festen sozialen Gruppe verstanden. Ob soziale Qualit&#228;t (etwa durch Tugend oder Arbeitsleistung) machbar sei, ist ein Hauptproblem der Neuzeit. Damit verbindet sich die Anerkennung oder &#220;berwindung von Standesgrenzen.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_ASTROLABE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An astronomical instrument, the astrolabe was used by classical astronomers, navigators and astrologers to plot the position of the Sun, the Moon, the planets and the stars, and determining latitude, surveying and triangulation. In the Islamic world they were used for astronomical studies as well as astrology, navigation, surveying and timekeeping and determining the direction of prayer. Astrologers in medieval Europe mostly used astrolabes to construct horoscopes and the "mariners astrolabe" was later developed to cope with conditions at sea on ships and was still in use well into the 17thC. The first mechanical astronomical clocks developed from the astrolabe until they were replaced by advanced clock-making techniques.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Astrolabium (auch: Astrolab, griech. "Stern-Nehmer") oder Planisph&#228;rum ist ein scheibenf&#246;rmiges astronomisches Instrument.[PARAGRAPH:2]Auf einer festen Scheibe (Tympanon) sind der Horizont und Kreise des horizontalen Koordinatensystems abgebildet. Dar&#252;ber liegt die drehbare Rete, die als Himmelsk&#246;rper einige Sterne und die Jahresbahn (Ekliptik) der Sonne enth&#228;lt. Einige von vielen Anwendungsm&#246;glichkeiten sind folgende: Wird die Rete auf Datum und Uhrzeit eingestellt, so lassen sich die Positionen der Sterne ablesen. Umgekehrt lassen sich aus dem Datum und der Position eines Sterns oder der Sonne die Uhrzeit oder die Himmelsrichtungen bestimmen. Allgemein kann mit einem Astrolabium der drehende Himmel, wie er von der Erde aus sichtbar ist, dargestellt werden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die R&#252;ckseite des Astrolabiums tr&#228;gt einen Diopter, mit der der H&#246;henwinkel eines Objekts auf der Erde oder am Himmel (zum Beispiel Stern oder Sonne) &#252;ber dem Horizont gemessen werden kann.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_BLAST_FURNACE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Used in smelting iron and steel for making farm implements and weapons, blast furnaces existed in China in the 5thC. B.C. In Europe, the Celts, Romans and Greeks used the inferior "bloom" method until early blast furnaces developed in Germany and Sweden in the 12thC. Used primarily in the production of cast iron, the Cistercian monasteries in France became the leading iron producers in Europe. While in the Muslim East, Indian "bloom"-cast iron was imported for the forging of the greatly superior "Damascus" steel sword blades. Iron and steel blast smelting reached its peak in 17thC England and Belgium in the production of precision machinery and weapons until it was replaced by more advanced coke-burning blast processes.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die moderne Hochofentechnik entwickelte sich im Laufe von rund 5.000 Jahren von den Anf&#228;ngen der Nutzung einfacher, mit Holzkohle betriebener und Kaltluft angefachter Rennfeuer ca. 3.000 v. Chr. &#252;ber Rennofen, St&#252;ckofen und Flo&#223;ofen bis hin zum Hochofen, der ab Anfang des 18. Jahrhunderts mit Koks und ab 1828 mit Hei&#223;wind betrieben und angefacht wird.[PARAGRAPH:2]Anfang des 13. Jahrhunderts begann man leistungsf&#228;higere &#214;fen zu entwickeln. Als eine Bindeglied zur Entwicklung der heutigen Hoch&#246;fen kann der "St&#252;ckofen" angesehen werden, welcher nach dem Eisenst&#252;ck benannt wurde, welches man aus dem Ofen herausgeholte. Der Ofen war ein viereckig gemauerter, oben offener Schachtofen dessen Gr&#246;&#223;e von etwas vier Meter H&#246;he im Mittelalter bis auf zu zehn Meter H&#246;he im 17. Jahrhundert anwuchs, wie zum Beispiel die St&#252;ck&#246;fen in Vordernberg in der Steiermark, einem damaligen Zentrum der Roheisenerzeugung in Mitteleuropa. Die Blaseb&#228;lge der &#214;fen wurden durch Wasserr&#228;der angetrieben und die Anlagen wurden daher auch als Radwerk bezeichnet. Sie erreichten Temperaturen von bis zu 1600 &#176;C, wobei das Gemenge aus Eisenerz und Holzkohle dabei teilweise zum Schmelzen gebracht wurde. Eine Weiterentwicklung war der Blauofen, dessen Name aus einer Verballhornung des englischen Wortes blow (= blasen) entstand. Er entspricht im Prinzip dem St&#252;ckofen, besitzt aber eine geschlossene Ofenbrust.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_BRONZE_CASTING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A metal alloy of copper with an additive of tin, bronze was important from pre-Classical times as the first important alloy used by man. Used for the mould-casting of tools, weapons and jewelry, it was much harder and more durable than stone or copper. Tin and copper ores are rarely found together, making Cornwall in Britain the major ancient source for both and a source of much early trade with Europe. Though bronze is harder than wrought iron, iron is much easier to find. So the Bronze Age gave way to the Iron Age in Europe and as iron-working became cheaper, bronze was increasingly confined to artistic uses, and cultures learned to make iron into steel which is much harder than bronze and holds a much sharper cutting edge.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Bronzeguss ist ein Urformverfahren, bei dem fl&#252;ssige Bronze, eine Legierung aus Kupfer und Zinn, in eine Form gegossen wird, um einen gew&#252;nschten Gegenstand aus Bronze herzustellen. Typische Produkte waren und sind u. a. Glocken, Epitaphien, Plastiken, Werkzeuge, Kanonen, Spiegel und Schmuck.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Bronzeguss genie&#223;t eine lange Tradition, die in ihren Wurzeln bis in das Neolithikum zur&#252;ckreicht. Im 4. vorchristlichen Jahrtausend haben Menschen begonnen, Kupfer zu schmelzen und zu gie&#223;en. Erste Nachweise f&#252;r gegossenes Kupfer in Mitteleuropa sind Tiegelfunde aus der Pfyner Kultur, Schweiz. Ab etwa 2200 v. Chr. taucht Zinn-Bronze regelm&#228;&#223;ig in Mitteleuropa auf.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Bronzeguss ist neben der Kaltbearbeitung der Bronze der wichtigste Produktionsprozess der Bronzezeit, da er nach und nach die Produktion der Steinger&#228;te ersetzt. Von gro&#223;em Vorteil ist die Wiederverwendbarkeit des Metalls, das sich beliebig oft wieder einschmelzen l&#228;sst.[PARAGRAPH:2]Im Verlauf der Menschheitsgeschichte haben sich mehrere Form-Verfahren herausgebildet, einmal das Gie&#223;en in Dauerformen und das Gie&#223;en in Verlorenen Formen.[PARAGRAPH:2]F&#252;r Kupferwerkstoffe lassen sich Dauerformen aus Stein und Metall herstellen. Metallformen werden auch als Kokillen bezeichnet. Heutzutage werden Stahlkokillen in der Industrie eingesetzt. F&#252;r das Handwerk ist lediglich Gie&#223;en in Verlorenen Formen rentabel. Der Bronzeguss spielt in der modernen Welt in erster Linie f&#252;r K&#252;nstler eine Rolle, da andere Werkstoffe belastbarer und wirtschaftlicher als Bronze sind.[PARAGRAPH:2]In der Literatur wird das Wachsausschmelzverfahren oft mit dem Verfahren der Verlorenen Form gleichgesetzt. Dies ist technisch nicht richtig, da auch Sandformen zu den verlorenen Formen z&#228;hlen, die nach dem Guss zerst&#246;rt werden. Beim Wachsausschmelzverfahren sollte also eher vom Verfahren mit Verlorenem Modell gesprochen werden. Anforderungen an den Formstoff sind die Bildsamkeit, Gasdurchl&#228;ssigkeit, mechanische Belastbarkeit vor dem Guss und guter Zerfall nach dem Guss, um nur die wichtigsten zu nennen. Der Guss erfolgt meist in kalte Formen, die zun&#228;chst unbedingt trocken gebrannt werden m&#252;ssen. Hierbei ist auch darauf zu achten, s&#228;mtliches chemisch gebundene Kristallwasser zu entfernen.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_CHAIN_MAIL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Known as "mail" or "maille", chain mail consists of small metal rings linked together in a pattern to form a mesh. Worn as a shirt, it is known as a "hauberk", normally knee-length but often shorter. It also take the form of leggings, hoods, mittens or collars. Mail seems to have emerged in both East Asia and Europe around 400BC and featured prominently throughout the Dark Ages and into the Middle Ages, reaching its apex in Europe during the 13thC were mail often covered the whole body. Plate armour, however, gradually began to replace mail in the 14th.C as it offered more effective protection against archery, pikes and early firearms. Mail did continue much longer however as a protective clothing for foot soldiers as late as the 18thC.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Als Kettenr&#252;stung oder Kettenpanzer bezeichnet man eine R&#252;stung, die aus zahlreichen ineinander verflochtenen und vernieteten kleinen Metallringen besteht. Aufgabe des Kettenhemds war es Schnittverletzungen zu vermeiden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Nach dem Zusammenbruch des Westr&#246;mischen Reichs gab es lange Zeit keine nennenswerte R&#252;stungsindustrie auf europ&#228;ischem Boden (au&#223;er in Byzanz), was den Wert einer Kettenr&#252;stung noch erh&#246;hte. Die Kettenr&#252;stung war im Fr&#252;hmittelalter im Gro&#223;teil Europas deshalb weniger verbreitet. Man kennt sie zur Zeit der V&#246;lkerwanderungen vor allem aus den Gr&#228;bern hochrangiger F&#252;rsten, etwa aus Planig und Gammertingen. Dar&#252;ber hinaus waren die Spangenhelme dieser Zeit zum Teil mit einem Nackenschutz aus Kettengeflecht versehen. Neben Kettenr&#252;stungen existierten im Fr&#252;hmittelalter diverse Arten von g&#252;nstigeren Textil- und Lederr&#252;stungen, Lamellenr&#252;stungen zudem Schuppenpanzer. Letzterer bot au&#223;erdem besseren Schutz gegen Wuchtattacken, da er etwas starrer war, insgesamt war er jedoch dem Kettenhemd unterlegen. Im Gegensatz zur r&#246;mischen Kettenr&#252;stung bedeckte die Kettenr&#252;stung des Mittelalters immer gr&#246;&#223;ere Teile des K&#246;rpers. Im 12. und 13. Jahrhundert wurde das Kettenhemd zu einer wichtigen R&#252;stungsform der Ritter. Neben dem Kettenpanzer trug man Kettenhandschuhe, den Topfhelm und die Helmbr&#252;nne.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_CHIVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As an expression of the medieval institution of knighthood, chivalry embodied the ideals of knightly virtue, duty, honour and courtly love. The term originated in 10th.C France from the word "chevalier" for knight, a powerful warrior with military training, a horse and equipment with sufficient wealth and prestige to support him. Chivalry was mainly associated with the occupation, duties and social class of the knight but from the 12thC, chivalry was also seen as a moral, religious and social code of knightly conduct, esp. with the development of knightly orders like the Templars and Hospitallers during the Crusades, and with the practice of heraldry and its elaborate rules of displaying personal and family coats of arms.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ritterlichkeit umfasst einen Katalog von tugendhaftem Verhalten oder bestimmten Tugenden; manchmal sogar einen Ethos. Es stammt vom mittelhochdeutschen Adjektiv bzw. Adverb r&#238;tterlich oder r&#238;terlich, das Nomen Ritterlichkeit ist also sp&#228;teren Ursprungs. Dort bezeichnet es das einem Ritter geziemende Verhalten.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die ritterlichen Tugenden bestanden aus pers&#246;nlichen wie sozialen Normen, die zum einen das Ansehen des Rittertums und damit des Adels &#252;berhaupt erhalten und begr&#252;nden (&#234;re, zuht), aber auch die Ordnung der sozialen Beziehungen der Menschen festigen und garantieren sollten. Sie dienten damit auch der Legitimation des Adels als des vornehmsten Standes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Nat&#252;rlich fu&#223;ten sie auf den milit&#228;rischen Tugenden von Treue und Tapferkeit (denn Ritter waren zun&#228;chst nichts anderes als die Soldaten eines Lehnsherren), &#252;berstiegen diese jedoch weit. Wichtig dabei ist zu beachten, dass es sich dabei um Idealisierungen handelt, die vornehmlich der so genannten h&#246;fischen Dichtung wie Erec, Parzival oder Iwein sowie dem Minnesang entlehnt sind und die sich dort in ritualisierten Handlungen niederschlagen. Die h&#246;veschkeit, aus dessen Begriff der neuhochdeutsche Begriff der H&#246;flichkeit sich noch speist, bezeichnet die Umgangsformen am Hof, welcher ein gesittetes wie musisch gebildetes Verhalten nahelegt.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_CIVIL_ENGINEERING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The engineering discipline that deals with the design, construction and maintenance of works like bridges, roads, canals, dams and buildings, civil engineering can be traced as far back as about 3000BC in Egypt and Mesopotamia in projects like the Great Pyramids of Egypt and the Hanging Gardens of Babylon. The Romans built civil structures throughout their empire including aqueducts, harbours, bridges and roads. In Europe during the Middle Ages, rulers commissioned huge cathedrals and palaces built by armies of labourers and guilds of skilled building masons and other craftsmen. Until the 18thC there was no distinction between civil engineering and architecture and only described works not specifically for military purposes.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Begriff Bauwesen bezeichnet &#252;bergreifend das Fachgebiet, das sich mit allen Aspekten des Bauens im Sinne der Errichtung von Baulichen Anlagen bzw. Bauwerken besch&#228;ftigt.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Begriff umfasst alle Themen, Arbeitsbereiche und Fachdisziplinen, die mit dem Bauen im o.g. Sinne zu tun haben, sowohl die Beteiligten des Bauprozesses als auch die gesamte Bauwirtschaft, Baukunst und Bautechnik.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die einzelnen Fachdisziplinen dagegen betrachten das Bauen in der Regel unter bestimmten Blickwinkeln. So stehen im Bauingenieurswesen eher technische Fragen im Mittelpunkt, w&#228;hrend die Architektur st&#228;rker gestalterische und Nutzungsaspekte bearbeitet.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Akteure des Bauwesens sind "die am Bau Beteiligten" (&#252;bliche zusammenfassende Bezeichnung): Der Bauherr, die Planer (Architekten und Fachingenieure), die ausf&#252;hrenden Unternehmen, der (sp&#228;tere) Nutzer, die Bauleitung und Bau&#252;berwachung sowie die Baugenehmigungsbeh&#246;rden.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_CLASSICAL_KNOWLEDGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Classical antiquity refers broadly to the period of cultural history of the Ancient Greeks and Romans from the poetry of Homer (8th-7thC BC), through the rise of Christianity until the decline of the Roman Empire (5thC AD). Classical Greek civilization was hugely influential in the language, politics, education, philosophy, science, art and architecture of Western Europe esp. during its revival in Renaissance Italy. The Hellenistic tradition carried on throughout the Roman republic and empire with important advances by Roman authors and scientists like Virgil and Galen and the followers of Plato and Aristotle, until gradually being replaced by the theology of the Christian Church in the early Middle Ages.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Antike Traditionen hatten starke und pr&#228;gende Auswirkungen auf den weiteren Verlauf der Weltgeschichte, insbesondere auf die Entwicklung der westlichen Welt, die in der Antike ihre Wurzeln hat. Neuzeitliche Aufkl&#228;rer, Philosophen, Staatstheoretiker, Wissenschaftler, K&#252;nstler u.a. kn&#252;pften immer wieder an die Ionische Naturphilosophie, die attische Demokratie, das r&#246;mische Recht, den religi&#246;sen Pluralismus, das antike Sch&#246;nheitsideal und andere Hinterlassenschaften der Antike an.[PARAGRAPH:2]Antike Traditionen gerieten auch im Mittelalter nie v&#246;llig in Vergessenheit. In den Kl&#246;stern des Abendlandes wurde umfangreiches antikes Schriftgut bewahrt. Auch die Romidee blieb im Heiligen R&#246;mischen Reich lebendig. Im 8. Jahrhundert kam es zur ersten, sogenannten Karolingischen Renaissance. Auch byzantinische und arabische Gelehrte st&#252;tzten sich auf antikes Wissen und gaben es indirekt an das mittelalterliche Europa weiter.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_CLOCKMAKING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As a device for measuring time less than a day or month, early types of clocks include the sundial, the measured candle and the hour glass. Many types of water clock were known in China, Babylon and Egypt though these were refined by the Greeks and Romans and developed further in the Byzantine and Islamic period. In the Middle Ages as religious institutions sought to regulate the hours of prayer and work, came the development of "escapement" or weight-driven clocks and the use of the astrolabe in astronomical clocks. A further refinement arose in Calileo's invention of the pendulum clock and early attempts in spring-driven clocks which culminated in the invention of the marine chronometer by John Harrison in 1761.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die ersten Uhrmacher waren Schlosser und Schmiede. Auch nachdem Mitte des 16. Jahrhunderts Uhrmacherz&#252;nfte in Deutschland entstanden waren, hatten Schlosser das Recht, Uhren zu bauen. Die ersten Uhrmachervereinigungen finden sich 1540 in Dresden, noch vereinigt mit der Innung der Kleinschmiede und ohne Zwang zum Meisterst&#252;ck, 1544 in Paris und 1631 in London mit der Worshipful Company of Clockmakers. Die Uhrmacherei z&#228;hlte zun&#228;chst zu den K&#252;nsten, sp&#228;ter zum Kunsthandwerk. Die Uhrmacher waren die Pioniere der Feinmechanik.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_COMBINED_ARMS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The integration of different military units to achieve mutually complimentary effects is known as "combined arms" and dates back to antiquity. Roman legions were traditionally heavy infantry but were used in combination with skirmishers and light cavalry to form an integrated unit. The "Strategikon" written by Emperor Maurice of Byzantium in the 6thC described and refined this principle. The Engish effectively combined massed longbowmen with heavy men-at-arms against superior French mtd. forces at Crecy, Poiters and Agincourt. The weakness of early firearms led the Spanish to adopt the "tercio" pike and musket formations protected by swordsmen. Finally as firearms improved, pikes were gradually replaced by the bayonet.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Milit&#228;rischer Verband ist eine gr&#246;&#223;ere Gliederung von Truppen. Mit dem Niedergang der klassischen Feudalheere und der zunehmenden Kommerzialisierung der Kriegsf&#252;hrung entwickelte sich zum Ende des 16. Jahrhunderts das Regiment als ein neuer Verbandstyp. Das Regiment war urspr&#252;nglich, wie die Kompanie, eine Verwaltungseinheit und kein taktischer Truppenk&#246;rper. Diese wurden damals deutsch mit Gewalthaufen oder Gevierthaufen, ab der Mitte des 17. Jahrhunderts auch international als Bataillon bezeichnet.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_EXPLOSIVES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first explosives came in the form of gunpowder, a mixture of sulphur, charcoal and saltpetre, in China in the 9thC. Often used in the production of fireworks it soon was employed in incendiary grenades and as a propellant for early bombards and cannons. In the 13thC it had spread to the Middle East where the Ottomans and Arabs developed bombard cannons of great power. The use of gunpowder spread in Europe leading to the fielding of early cannon and the increasing reliance on firearms. A key advancement was corned gunpowder in which powder was mixed with a solvent making it more stable and reliable. Black powder was also used in the mining industry and civil engineering before the invention of chemical explosives in the early 19thC.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die erste verb&#252;rgte Darstellung vom Gebrauch von Explosivstoffen stammt aus China im Jahre 1232. Um die Mitte des 13. Jahrhunderts wird von Roger Bacon und Albertus Magnus &#252;ber schwarzpulver&#228;hnliche Mischungen berichtet. Die Wiedererfindung des Schwarzpulvers wird dem legend&#228;ren M&#246;nch Berthold Schwarz zugeschrieben, es wurde in der 2. H&#228;lfte des 13. Jahrhunderts erstmalig zum Verschie&#223;en noch pfeilf&#246;rmiger Geschosse aus geschlossenen Rohren verwendet. Die Geschichte der Explosivstoffe in der Folgezeit ist eng verbunden mit der Entwicklung von Schie&#223;rohren und Kanonen ab dem 14. Jahrhundert. Bis weit in das 19. Jahrhundert hinein blieb das Schwarzpulver das einzige Treibmittel f&#252;r Schusswaffen. Die Verwendung von Schwarzpulver f&#252;r gewerbliche Zwecke begann um 1620 mit Sprengungen in Steinbr&#252;chen und Erzbergwerken. Das Zeitalter des technischen Fortschritts auf dem Gebiet der Explosivstoffe begann mit der Entdeckung der Nitrozellulose sowie des Nitroglycerins Mitte des 19. Jh. Ihre sichere Handhabung lernte man erst ab ca. 1885. Wichtige Erfindungen auf diesem Gebiet stammen von Alfred Nobel. In der Folgezeit wurden weitere Explosivstoffe auf Nitroaromatenbasis entwickelt. Nach dem Zweiten Weltkrieg wurden in den USA die besonders sicheren und preiswerten ANFO-Sprengstoffe sowie die wasserhaltigen Sprengschlamm erfunden. Neueste Entwicklung auf diesem Gebiet sind Emulsionen von Mineral&#246;l in konzentrierter w&#228;ssrigen Ammoniumnitrat-L&#246;sung.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_FARRIERS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A farrier is a specialist of equine hoofcare, fabricating, adapting, and placing of iron shoes to the horses' foot. The practice of shoeing horses followed the domestication of the horse as it was realized that the feet of working horses needed the additional protection of fitted covers. The Romans used wooden or hide coverings on the shoes of their cavalry horses but the making of iron shoes seems to have become common in Byzantine and Arab armies at the time of the Crusades. But in Europe it was only with the heavy war horse and the armoured knight that specially crafted iron horse shoes became common practice. The early farriers art derived from that of the blacksmith and the two remained synonymous until at least the 18thC.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der traditionelle Aufgabenbereich des Hufschmieds ist der Beschlag mit Hufeisen, sowie das K&#252;rzen und Korrigieren bei Barhufg&#228;ngern. Dazu geh&#246;rt auch die Zubereitung des Hufes f&#252;r den Beschlag durch Ausschneiden und Raspeln des Horns. Bei Stellungsfehlern, Hufkrankheiten wie Hufrehe oder Hohle Wand usw. wird der Schmied auch therapeutisch t&#228;tig, indem er durch das Anbringen spezieller Beschl&#228;ge den Heilungsprozess unterst&#252;tzt.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_MATCHLOCK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The flintlock firing mechanism in early firearms, invented in France about 1630, gradually replaced the more primitive matchlock and wheel-lock mechanisms. Flintlocks could be small-arm long guns or pistols, rifled or smoothbore, muzzle-loading or breech-loading. Flintlock muskets became the mainstay of European armies between 1660 and 1840 and were generally muzzle-loading, smoothbore long guns firing a round lead ball. Flintlock pistols were most often self-defense weapons, employed in dueling and as a cavalry arm in conjunction with swords and cutlasses. It was only with the invention of paper and metal cartridges and the development of multi-shot revolvers and rifles in the mid 19thC that flintlocks became obsolete.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Steinschloss (franz&#246;sisches Schloss) ist ein Ausl&#246;semechanismus f&#252;r Vorderladerfeuerwaffen, welches mit einem Feuerstein z&#252;ndet. Erste Vorformen gab es bereits im 16. Jahrhundert (Schnappschloss), allerdings funktionierten diese sehr schlecht. Im 17. Jahrhundert wurde das System verbessert und setzte sich allm&#228;hlich durch, da es nicht ganz so wetterabh&#228;ngig war wie das Luntenschloss, und weil man immer feuerbereit sein konnte, ohne Lunte zu verbrauchen. Ab 1704 hatte es sich bei allen Armeen durchgesetzt und das Luntenschloss fast vollst&#228;ndig verdr&#228;ngt. Lediglich die Kavallerie verwendete noch l&#228;nger das Radschloss. Sp&#228;ter wurde es auch bei der Kavallerie eingef&#252;hrt, da es billiger und pflegeleichter als das Radschloss war.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_FREE_MARKET_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In theory, a market free of government regulation apart from a legal system and protection of property rights, a free market is characterized by open pricing and competition in a free marketplace. Many argue that a free market is a natural form of social organization that arises in any society when not obstructed. Historically, the free market economy seems to have emerged in late medieval and early modern Europe with the development of capitalism and the theory of "laissez-faire". It is unclear whether such a pure form could have existed in the era of mercantilism and colonialism with their competing systems of tariffs and other trade restrictions. In fact a truly free market may instead be more of an aspiration than a reality.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Im Modell der Freien Marktwirtschaft wird allein durch den Markt bestimmt, was produziert und konsumiert wird, in welcher Menge und zu welchem ??Preis.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_GOTHIC_ARCHITECTURE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Gothic architecture evolved from earlier Romanesque architecture and was succeeded by the Renaissance style. Originating in 12thC France and lasting until the 16thC, and generally known as "The French style", its characteristic features were the pointed arch, elevated spires. the ribbed vault and the flying buttress. Gothic architecture is most typified in the great cathedrals, abbeys and parish churches in Europe but also in many castles, palaces, town-halls, guildhalls and universities. But it is especially the great cathedrals like Rheims, Notre Dame, Cologne and York which most exemplify this distinctive architectural design which so much appeals to the emotions and humbles the soul by its sheer monumental power.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Gotik ist eine Epoche der europ&#228;ischen Architektur und Kunst des Mittelalters. Sie entstand um 1140 in der &#206;le-de-France (Gegend um Paris) und w&#228;hrte n&#246;rdlich der Alpen bis etwa 1500-1550. Der zuvor vorherrschende Bau- und Kunststil ist als Romanik, der nachfolgende als Renaissance bekannt. In der Nachgotik lebte der gotische Baustil auch au&#223;erhalb seiner Epoche bis in die Barockzeit weiter fort und fand in der Neugotik als Spielart des Historismus neues Interesse. Der gotische Stil ist nur in der Architektur genau abzugrenzen, w&#228;hrend dies auf den Gebieten der Plastik und Malerei nicht in gleicher Klarheit m&#246;glich ist.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Gotik war eine Epoche der Verbildlichung der christlichen Ideenwelt und bediente sich dabei in gro&#223;em Umfang der Symbolik und Allegorie. Herausragende Kunstsch&#246;pfung ist die gotische Kathedrale, die als Gesamtkunstwerk Architektur, Plastik und (Glas-)Malerei des Mittelalters vereint. In der Architektur unterscheidet man weiterhin die Phasen der Fr&#252;h-, Hoch- und Sp&#228;tgotik, die in den verschiedenen europ&#228;ischen Kunstlandschaften zu unterschiedlichen Zeitpunkten &#252;bernommen wurden und sich dann teilweise auch voneinander unabh&#228;ngig weiterentwickelten.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_HERBAL_MEDICINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Herbalism is the traditional practice of folk medicine based on the use of plants and plant extracts as well as fungal, apiary and even animal products which was well-documented in the works of Hippocrates and Galen and faithfully copied and studied in monasteries in early medieval Europe. Monasteries became the local centres of medical practice and kept extensive herb gardens for medicinal use. There was also a rise in traveling herbalists including many "wise women" whose use of spells would open them to charges of witchcraft in later centuries. The Arabs expanded greatly on Greek and Roman methods and from their trading networks introduced hundreds of new plants and preparations to European medical practice.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Nutzung von Pflanzen mit der Absicht der Heilung l&#228;sst sich bereits in fr&#252;hesten Schichten babylonischer, alt&#228;gyptischer, indischer (Hymnen des Rig Veda) oder chinesischer Texte nachweisen, aber auch der ausdr&#252;ckliche Anbau von Heilkr&#228;utern. Das bekannteste Zeugnis dieser &#228;ltesten Aufzeichnungen medizinischer Bem&#252;hungen mit zahlreichen Beispielen f&#252;r Heilpflanzen und deren Anwendung ist das Papyrus Ebers das im letzten Viertel des sechzehnten Jahrhunderts vor Christus des alten &#196;gypten verfasst wurde.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_INDUSTRIAL_TECH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Industrial Revolution which saw major changes in agriculture, mining, manufacturing and transportation occurred initially in Britain but spread rapidly to Europe, America and the World, transforming socio-economic and cultural conditions. From the 1780's there was a profound shift from a mainly rural economy using on manual labour to one based increasingly on machine-based manufacturing. The enclosure of agricultural land, mechanization of the textile industry, the refinement of iron and steel-making and the introduction of steam power brought with it the improvement of canals, roads and railroads. And the refinement of all-metal machine tools greatly increased production capacity and output in manufacturing industry.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Als Industrielle Revolution wird die tiefgreifende und dauerhafte Umgestaltung der wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Verh&#228;ltnisse, der Arbeitsbedingungen und Lebensumst&#228;nde bezeichnet, die in der zweiten H&#228;lfte des 18. Jahrhunderts begann und verst&#228;rkt im 19. Jahrhundert, zun&#228;chst in England, dann in ganz Westeuropa und den USA, seit dem sp&#228;ten 19. Jahrhundert auch in Japan und weiteren Teilen Europas und Asiens zum &#220;bergang von der Agrar- zur Industriegesellschaft gef&#252;hrt hat. Als wichtigste an dieser Umw&#228;lzung beteiligte Gesellschaftsklassen standen sich kapitalistische Unternehmer und lohnabh&#228;ngige Proletarier gegen&#252;ber.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_LATEEN_SAILS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A lateen or latin-rig is a triangular sail set on a large yard mounted at an angle to the mast in a fore to aft direction. First used in Arabian waters and the Indian Ocean as early as the 4thC BC, it again became standard in the rigging of Roman vessels from the 3rd.C. Until the 14thC its use was confined to the Mediterranean Sea while Atlantic and Balkan vessels relied on the square sail. But it was the Portugese who first used large lateen sails in ocean-going caravels and the larger carrick with its mixed arrangement of both lateen and square rigging which became the mainstay of Atlantic voyages by the early European discoverers. Lateen sails have continued today mainly on the Nile, Mediterranean and Indian Oceans.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Lateinersegel ist ein Schratsegel bestehend aus einem Tuch in der Form eines Dreiecks, das mit dem Rutenliek an der Rute oder lateinische Rah genannten Spiere angeschlagen ist. Die Rute ist zumeist ann&#228;hernd mittig am Mast befestigt. Zum Segeln wird die Rute schr&#228;g gestellt, etwa so, dass eine Seite des Segels horizontal verl&#228;uft und mit dem Tau an der Spitze gespannt wird. Je nach Windrichtung kann das Segel auf beide Seiten geschwenkt werden, wozu die gesamte Rute neu ausgerichtet werden muss.[PARAGRAPH:2]Das Lateinersegel kam im 2.-4. Jahrhundert n. Chr. in der r&#246;mischen Mittelmeerschiffahrt auf, zun&#228;chst vor allem auf kleineren und K&#252;stenfahrzeugen.[ Dem belgischen Marinehistoriker Lucien Basch zufolge lassen sich in der hellenistischen Seefahrt echte Lateinersegel sogar bis in das erste vorchristliche Jahrhundert zur&#252;ckverfolgen. Die Hochzeit des Lateinersegels begann im Fr&#252;hmittelalter: bis zum 6. Jahrhundert hatte es das bis dahin vorherrschende Rahsegel derart vollst&#228;ndig abgel&#246;st, dass Letzteres bis zum Sp&#228;tmittelalter fast v&#246;llig aus dem Mittelmeerraum verschwand. Das Lateinersegel erlaubte, h&#246;her am Wind zu segeln, wodurch das Kreuzen vereinfacht und die Fahrtzeit gegen den Wind erheblich verk&#252;rzt wurden.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_MACHINE_TOOLS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A machine tool is a powerful mechanical device used to shape or fabricate metal objects by "machining" or the selective removal of metals. Machine tools typically used a source of power other than human movement but could employ human action only is set up as such. But true machine tools only arose with the employment of water wheels as in the earliest forms which involved direct mechanical control of the cutting tool. Early examples include the first screw-cutting lathes in the 15thC as well as simple drill presses and milling machines. But it was only in the 18thC with the development of the steam engine that reliable machine tools began to develop, contributing to the great advances of the Industrial Revolution.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]In der Renaissance entwickelte sich ein genaueres Konzept &#252;ber Mechanismen: Mechanismen sind Komplexe von Bauteilen, bei denen die Bewegung eines Elements zwangsl&#228;ufig die Bewegung anderer Elemente bewirkt. Sie haben in der Regel bewegliche Komponenten und sind im Vergleich zum apparatus (dem ,Werkzeug') erheblich komplexer.[PARGRAPH:2]In dieser Zeit war ein Mechanismus prim&#228;r ein Werk, eine Form von Getrieben, die Kr&#228;fte &#252;bertragen. Zu den kompliziertesten Mechanismen geh&#246;rte die Grande Complication (Gro&#223;e Komplikation) in mechanisch-automatischen Uhrwerken. In diesem Sinne ist auch der Mechanismus von Antikythera zu verstehen, ein antikes Artefakt, das die Himmelsmechanik nachbildete.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_MANORIALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As the organizing principle of rural economy and society in early medieval Europe, "manorialism" was characterized by the vesting of legal and economic power in a lord (French, "seigneur") supported economically from his direct landholding ( or "manor"), and from the obligatory contributions of a legally-bound peasant population under his control. The lord held this position as part of his obligations of loyalty and military service to a higher lord or king and exercised local justice through his manor court governed by public law and local custom. Although usually secular, seigneurs could also be bishops or abbots who controlled manors and lands by religious authority but enjoyed similar local rights and obligations.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Bei der herrschaftlichen Organisationsform der Grundherrschaft (in &#214;sterreich-Ungarn auch als Patrimonialherrschaft bezeichnet) handelte es sich um die vom Mittelalter bis zur Fr&#252;hneuzeit vorherrschende rechtliche, wirtschaftliche und soziale Besitzstruktur des l&#228;ndlichen Raums.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Grundherr (in der Regel Adlige, die Kirche, Kl&#246;ster oder der K&#246;nig) war dabei nicht nur Grundeigent&#252;mer oder Inhaber eines Lehens mit Verf&#252;gungsgewalt &#252;ber das Land, sondern er &#252;bte zumeist auch weitreichende weitere Verwaltungs- und Gerichtsfunktionen aus. Dem Grundherrn oblag sowohl die rechtliche Verwaltung und Nutzungsvergabe von land- oder forstwirtschaftlich genutzten Fl&#228;chen als auch die Aus&#252;bung &#246;ffentlich-rechtlicher Befugnisse, wie der Polizeigewalt und der niederen Gerichtsbarkeit (Hofgericht), mit dem Recht, geistlich oder weltlich &#252;ber seine Untertanen zu richten. Gleichzeitig hatte der Grundherr aber seinen Grundholden (Untertanen) "Schutz und Schirm" zu gew&#228;hren. Die Grundherrschaft umfasste somit nicht nur eine eng mit dem Feudalismus zusammenh&#228;ngende agrarische Wirtschaftsform, sondern eine Herrschafts- und Besitzstruktur, die alle Bereiche des mittelalterlichen Lebens umfasste und Formen wie Leibherrschaft, Schutzherrschaft, Gerichtsherrschaft, Zehntherrschaft, Vogteigewalt und Dorfobrigkeit betreffen konnte. Kriegschaft setzte aber nicht zwingend die Leibherrschaft voraus.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_MAP_MAKING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Cartography, or map making, is the practice of making geographical maps which developed in ancient Greece and Rome in the 6thC. BC. An early example was Ptolemy's map of the known world in the 2ndC. AD. Arab geographers began to translate the works of Greek geographers into Arabic and many "mappa mundi" were produced in early medieval Europe, but the first accurate atlas of maps was produced by the Arab geographer al-Idrisi in 1154, incorporating knowledge of Europe, Africa, the Indian Ocean and the Far East. Later European geographers relied heavily on previous maps and the observations of explorers but were aided by the introduction of the magnetic compass, telescope and sextant which improved the accuracy of map making greatly.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Kartografie (auch Kartographie) ist die Wissenschaft und Technik zur Darstellung der Erdoberfl&#228;che in topografischen und thematischen Karten, im einfachsten Fall Landkarten.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die &#228;ltesten Karten stammen bereits aus dem Neolithikum. Eine Wandmalerei zeigt eine zentralanatolische Siedlung um 6200 v. Chr. mit ihren H&#228;usern und dem Doppelgipfel des Vulkans Hasan Dagi (3.270 m). Bedeutende fr&#252;he Zeugnisse stammen aus der babylonischen Zeit (geritzte Tontafeln). Den ersten ernsthaften Versuch eine brauchbare Karte unter mathematischen und geometrischen Aspekten anzufertigen unternahm Anaximander von Milet (ein Sch&#252;ler des Thales) um 541 v. Chr.[PARAGRAPH:2]Im Mittelalter entstanden die ersten Kartenwerke von muslimischen Geographen, die auf der Grundlage neuerer Beobachtungen, Messungen und Entdeckungen das im 8. Jahrhundert ins Arabische &#252;bersetzte Werk des Ptolem&#228;us korrigierten und erheblichen Einfluss auf die europ&#228;ische Kartografie aus&#252;bten. Hervorzuheben sind hier al-Istakhris Karten aus dem 10. Jahrhundert, und die im Auftrag K&#246;nig Rogers II. von Sizilien 1154 angefertigte Weltkarte Charta Rogeriana von Abu Abdallah al-Idrisi (auch Weltkarte des Idrisi genannt).[PARAGRAPH:2]Im sp&#228;ten Mittelalter entstanden die mappae mundi mit ihren bekanntesten Vertretern, der Ebstorfer Weltkarte (ca. 1235) und der Hereforder Weltkarte (ca. 1270). Parallel gab es bereits recht genaue Karten des Mittelmeeres, die sog. Portolankarten. Das Bild am Ende des Mittelalters zeigt der Globus des N&#252;rnberger Gelehrten Martin Behaim von 1492.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_MILITARY_TACTICS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The art of organizing an army and techniques for the use of weapons and military units to engage the enemy in battle, military tactics have changed greatly over time with changes in philosophy and technology. Before the 19th.C, most military tactics were confined to the concerns of the battlefield, such as how to maneuver units during combat in open terrain. Typical practices in early warfare included ambushes, seeking and turning flanks, reconnaissance, creating and using obstacles and defences. An essential element of tactics was the use of ground to advantage, such as rivers, swamps, passes, choke points and natural cover, which might be used by a commander to create or enhance an advantage over his opponent.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die milit&#228;rischen Taktiken des Mittelalters wurden in Europa von zwei Faktoren bestimmt: Das Fehlen umw&#228;lzender technischer Neuerungen (bis zur Erfindung des Schie&#223;pulvers) und eine stete Verfestigung (bis hin zu einer Erstarrung) der gesellschaftlichen Strukturen. Grunds&#228;tzlich wurden die r&#246;mischen Taktiken fortgef&#252;hrt. Steigende, mit der Zeit entscheidende Bedeutung erlangte dabei der Einsatz gepanzerter Ritter. Die Ritter wurden zu autarken, im direkten Kampf der Infanterie haushoch &#252;berlegenen Berufskriegern mit zentraler gesellschaftlicher Bedeutung und polizeilicher Befugnis, jedoch ohne gro&#223;e milit&#228;rische Bedeutung. Eine Ver&#228;nderung im hohen und sp&#228;ten Mittelalter ist allerdings in der breiten Einf&#252;hrung von spezialisierten Fernkampfeinheiten (Langbogen- und Armbrustsch&#252;tzen) zu sehen. Die Zunahme der Bedrohung "aus der Luft" konnte die Entscheidung in einer Schlacht ma&#223;geblich (zum Beispiel Schlacht von Azincourt) ver&#228;ndern. Hierdurch gewannen Heeresaufstellung und -einsatz an Bedeutung. Besonderen Einfluss auf die europ&#228;ische Taktik hatten die Erfahrungen der Kreuzz&#252;ge in Bezug auf die Kavallerie, als der Steigb&#252;gel von den eurasischen Steppenv&#246;lkern &#252;bernommen wurde.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_MONASTICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Monasticism is the religious practice in which individuals renounce worldly pursuits in favour of more spiritual work. The practice developed early in Christianity and monasteries were founded throughout early Europe to organize their followers in orders based on the rules laid down by St. Benedict, St. Dominic and others. Monasteries were communities whose members engaged in prayer, study and contemplation but also cooperated in the production of books and manuscripts, metallurgy, agriculture, textiles and brewing. Monasteries often became very powerful and wealthy communities whose influence could challenge the more secular authorities such as the landed nobility, the military and the king or even the Church itself.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Begriff M&#246;nchtum bezeichnet die Gesamtheit der von M&#246;nchen und Nonnen praktizierten religi&#246;s gepr&#228;gten Lebensformen. Das M&#246;nchtum ist eine von asketischen Idealen bestimmte Lebensweise, um in Abkehr von der Welt den weltlichen Zielen zu entsagen und das eigene Leben einem spirituellen Ziel zu widmen. Das M&#246;nchtum existiert in verschiedenen Religionen, so vor allem im Buddhismus und im Christentum, ferner im Hinduismus und im Daoismus.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_MONUMENT_BUILDING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A monument is a structure built to commemorate a person or event, or a remembrance of past events, the word being derived from the Latin "monere" meaning to remind or warn. Monuments have been created for thousands of years and have become the most durable symbols of past civilizations. In the Middle Ages, wealthy patrons financed the building of statues, tombs and memorials to famous people, esp. military leaders, national heroes or notable politicians. Triumphal arches and decorative fountains often commemorated military victories or famous generals. During the Renaissance, the Church commissioned great statues and sculptures by artists like Michelangelo and Bernini to celebrate Christianity and the glory of God.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Unter Monumentalkunst versteht man gro&#223;formatige Kunst, die deutlich in der Absicht konzipiert wurde, ein auff&#228;lliges Zeichen oder sogar Machtsymbol zu setzen. Monumentalkunst findet man vor allem im &#246;ffentlichen Raum, z. B. bei Denkm&#228;lern, Geb&#228;uden und Wandbildern. Ma&#223;stab f&#252;r die Gr&#246;&#223;e ist das &#220;berschreiten einer menschlichen Proportion: Als monumental wird ein Bauwerk empfunden, das dem es betrachtenden Menschen aus der N&#228;he durch seine Gr&#246;&#223;e wenig &#220;berschaubarkeit bietet und damit die &#220;berlegenheit des Erbauers, (bei Denkm&#228;lern) Widmungstr&#228;gers oder (bei sakralen Bauten) Gottes demonstriert.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_NAVAL_ARCHITECTURE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The engineering discipline dealing with the design, construction and repair of marine vehicles, naval architecture involves research, design, development and calculation in all stages of the life of a marine vehicle. Traditionally, naval architecture has been more craft than science, the shape of a vessel being judged by the use of scale models or prototypes. In Europe, Viking longships were developed from the use of "clinker" or overlapped planking though later European vessels favoured more rounded hulls with a broad beam and heavily curved at both ends. Later innovations included a straight steerpost enabling the mounting of a moveable rudder and a mixed array of both lateen and square-rigged sails on ocean-going vessels.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Trockendock wurde in Europa 1495 in Portsmouth zum ersten Mal seit der europ&#228;ischen Antike wieder angewandt. Es dauerte jedoch noch mehrere hundert Jahre, bis sich das Trockendock f&#252;r den Schiffbau im 19. Jahrhundert allgemein durchsetzte. Drei Jahrtausende war Holz das dominierende Baumaterial f&#252;r Schiffe.[PARAGRAPH:2]Zu Beginn der Industrialisierung begannen die Schiffbauer vor allem in Gro&#223;britannien verst&#228;rkt Eisen einzusetzen, um das rar gewordene Krummholz zu ersetzen. Damit entstand die Kompositbauweise mit Kielschwein und Spanten aus Eisenprofilen und Beplankung aus Holz. Das Unterwasserschiff wurde zum Schutz gegen Bewuchs mit Kupferblech beschlagen.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_PATRONAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Patronage is the support, encouragement, privilege and financial aid that an organization or individual bestows on another. In the history of art, patronage refers to the support kings, popes or the wealthy provided to musicians, painters and sculptors, acting as sponsors of individual artists to enhance their prestige, political ambitions or social position. Some patrons like the Medici family of Florence and the Papacy supported the the creation of religious art and architecture by their commissioning of churches, cathedrals, paintings and sculpture. Artists and writers such as Michelangelo, Raphael, Da Vinci, Shakespeare and Ben Jonson all enjoyed the direct support of wealthy noble or ecclesiastical patrons.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Begriff Kunstpatronage bezeichnet das Auftragsverh&#228;ltnis zwischen einem K&#252;nstler und seinem Auftraggeber, bei dem der Patron die finanziellen und sozialen Voraussetzungen zur Umsetzung des Kunstwerkes schafft. F&#252;r gew&#246;hnlich wird die Bezeichnung Kunstpatronage f&#252;r die Kunstf&#246;rderung des sp&#228;ten Mittelalters und der Fr&#252;hen Neuzeit verwendet.[PARAGRAPH:2]Als Auftraggeber traten meist wohlhabende Pr&#228;laten, F&#252;rsten, Kaufleute oder Privatpersonen, aber auch Personengruppen wie Ordensgemeinschaften, Gremien, Z&#252;nften oder Bruderschaften auf. Die Kunstpatronage fand auf dem Gebiet der bildenden und der angewandten Kunst statt. Malerei und Bildhauerei, Architektur und Kunsthandwerk sowie Musik, Theater und Literatur wurden durch dieses System gef&#246;rdert und in gewisser Weise auch gesteuert. Eine enge Beziehung zwischen K&#252;nstler und Auftraggeber auf pers&#246;nlicher Ebene war bei einer kontinuierlichen, langj&#228;hrigen Kunstpatronage nicht ungew&#246;hnlich.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_PLATE_ARMOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A personal armour made from large metal plates, worn on the chest and sometimes the whole body, plate armour was first used by the Greeks and Romans but fell into disuse until its revival in the 13thC in Byzantium and Europe. Single plates of metal armour were used to protect joints and shins but worn over a full mail "haubergeon" or shirt although by the end of the 14thC larger and more complete full sets of plate armour were developed. The best armour was produced in Germany, Northern Italy, Serbia and at Greenwich in England, each with its own distinctive style. Full plate armour continued in use until the 18thC but became more decorative than militarily useful due to advances in weaponry like the adoption of rifled muskets.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Als Plattenpanzer wird eine aus k&#246;rpergerecht geformten Metallplatten bestehende R&#252;stung bezeichnet. Er stellt eine Form von Schutzkleidung dar, die im Kampfeinsatz z. B. vor Stichwaffen sch&#252;tzen soll. Plattenpanzer, die einen Gro&#223;teil des K&#246;rpers sch&#252;tzten, kamen gegen Ende des 14. Jahrhunderts in Westeuropa auf und fanden bis in das 17. Jahrhundert hinein Verwendung. Dabei wurden sie st&#228;ndig weiter entwickelt, den Plattenpanzer gibt es so gesehen nicht. W&#228;hrend die wichtigsten Teile derartiger R&#252;stungen meist nur aus einer oder wenigen Stahlplatten bestanden, mussten bestimmte K&#246;rperteile durch zahlreiche Metallschienen (Gesch&#252;be) oder durch Kettengeflecht gesch&#252;tzt werden, um dem Tr&#228;ger eine m&#246;glichst hohe Beweglichkeit zu gew&#228;hrleisten.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_POLYGONAL_FORT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A polygonal fort is a type of fortification which was designed in the early 19thC.in response to the effects of powerful explosive shells. It replaced the earlier complex designs of the "star fort" which developed in 16thC. Italy to replace more traditional fortifications. In order to counter the effect of cannons and bombards, defensive walls were made lower and thicker and made of brick rather than stone as it was not shattered so easily by the impact of cannonballs. Bastions were placed at every angle or corner to provide overlapping covering fire, producing the characteristic star or multiple star patterns. These "star forts" prevailed in Europe until replaced by the geometrically simpler but more durable polygonal form.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Eine Bastion oder Bollwerk, s&#252;ddeutsch-&#246;sterreichisch auch Bastei genannt, ist eine Anlage, die aus der Linie eines Festungswalls vorspringt und deren Aufgabe es war, den Raum unmittelbar vor dem Wall, den die Verteidiger von der Brustwehr aus nicht unmittelbar einsehen k&#246;nnen, seitlich bestreichen zu k&#246;nnen. Bastionen haben in einer neuzeitlichen Festung die gleiche Funktion wie die T&#252;rme einer antiken oder mittelalterlichen Stadtmauer. Sowohl der Turm als auch die Bastion stellen unabh&#228;ngig von ihrer &#228;u&#223;eren Form den flankierenden Teil eines Festungswalls dar.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_PROFESSIONAL_ARMY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A "standing" or professional army is comprised of full-time soldiers who "stand over" or do not disband in peacetime. Standing armies were better trained, equipped and prepared for battle, as defined in the "Marian" reforms which transformed the earlier property-based citizen army of the Roman Republic into a full-time professional Roman Army based on a period of service. Early European armies tended to be temporary levees raised by the King but standing armies emerged in Hungary under Matthias Corvinus, France under Henry VII and the "janissary" armies of the Ottoman Empire in the 15thC. James II of England raised the first professional British Army which saw action throughout the expanding British Empire of the 17th and 18th centuries.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die S&#246;ldnerheere des sp&#228;ten Mittelalters und der Neuzeit k&#246;nnen teilweise als Berufsarmeen angesehen werden, teilweise sind sie jedoch durch Zwangsrekrutierungen aufgestockt worden. Gleiches gilt f&#252;r die Armeen im Dienste der F&#252;rsten, Grafen und Herz&#246;ge im 17. und 18. Jahrhundert. Aufgrund der fehlenden Finanzmittel waren hier nur die Offiziere und Unteroffiziere Berufssoldaten, Mannschaften wurden generell zwangsverpflichtet. Die Repressionen und teilweise grausame Durchsetzung von Disziplin und Gehorsam hatte ung&#252;nstige Auswirkungen auf die Kampfkraft der Truppen im Vergleich mit aus Freiwilligen bestehenden Verb&#228;nden. Dies trat besonders im Aufeinandertreffen von Napoleonischen Truppen und preu&#223;ischer Armee in der Schlacht von Jena und Auerstedt zu Tage, die mit der Zerschlagung der zahlenm&#228;&#223;ig &#252;berlegenen preu&#223;ischen Armee endete. Ein gutes Beispiel f&#252;r die Unterschiedlichkeit in der Kampfmoral zwischen den als Stehendes Heer zu bezeichnenden Heeres und einer aus Freiwilligen bestehenden Truppe bildet die unter dem damaligen Kommandanten der Festung Kolberg (heute polnisch Kolobrzeg) Hauptmann Gneisenau, dessen Truppe aus zahlreich frisch rekrutierten Freiwilligen bestand. Diese Festung wurde noch lange nach der Schlacht von Jena und Auerstedt gehalten und musste erst als die Verpflegung und Munition aufgebraucht war, im Jahre 1807 aufgegeben werden.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_PUBLIC_WORKS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Public works are construction or engineering projects carried out by the state on behalf of the community which might include roads, canals, dams, harbours or city walls. Many great public projects were carried out by the Roman emperors to enhance their power and prestige and secure favour with the public like arenas, stadiums, public baths, theatres and libraries. In Europe during the Middle Ages, powerful kings, wealthy families and the Christian monasteries all supplied the wealth to finance the building of churches, cathedrals, castles, schools and transportation networks. As governments grew in power and influence and were able to raise tax revenues the building of public works became increasingly collective and national.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der St&#228;dtebau befasst sich mit der Gestaltung von Geb&#228;udegruppen, Siedlungen, Stadtteilen und insbesondere mit &#246;ffentlichen R&#228;umen. St&#228;dtebau kann als Bezeichnung f&#252;r die sichtbaren und gestalterischen Aspekte der Stadtplanung verstanden werden. Nach einem erweiterten Verst&#228;ndnis umfasst der Begriff des St&#228;dtebaues die "Gesamtheit der planenden, ordnenden und baulichen Ma&#223;nahmen zur r&#228;umlichen Gestaltung in Stadt und Land, die darauf gerichtet sind, in Durchsetzung gesellschaftspolitischer Ziele die Voraussetzungen f&#252;r das Zusammenleben der Menschen in einer ihnen gem&#228;&#223;en Umwelt zu schaffen"</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_RELIGIOUS_ART_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Sacred or religious art was intended to uplift the mind to the spiritual as an object venerated not for what it was but what it represented. The use of art in religion was essential in symbolizing concepts or feelings that words alone could not express. Christian art was usually allusive, or built on familiar images, like the Virgin Mary holding the baby Jesus, or Christ on the cross. As most people could not read, an elaborate iconograghic style in depicting religious themes was developed with Biblical events representing parables or lessons for the audience. Islamic art, however, forbade natural images but used geometric or calligraphic devices which emphasized the spiritual essence rather than the physical form.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Religi&#246;se Kunst umfasst im allgemeinen Sinn alle Bereiche k&#252;nstlerischen Schaffens, die religi&#246;se Inhalte zum Thema haben, welche in verschiedenen Medien zum Ausdruck kommen - von der Musik &#252;ber alle Bereich der Bildenden Kunst (insbesondere Malerei und Skulptur) und Architektur bis hin zur Kleinkunst (kirchliche Preziosen, Ger&#228;tschaften und Gew&#228;nder).</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_RENAISSANCE_ART_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The most distinguishing feature of Renaissance art which developed in 14thC. Europe was its highly realistic and linear perspective, first demonstrated in the writings of the architect Leon Battista Alberti. Painters like Leonardo Da Vinci, Michelangelo and Raphael studied the effects of light, shadow, colour and anatomy in their aesthetic attempt to depict the beauty of Nature. Paintings by Botticelli, Donatello and Titian were generally Classical or religious in theme though a vibrant artistic culture with more natural and rustic themes developed in the Netherlands in works by Van Eyck, Vermeer and Breughel and the German artists Durer and Holbein who themselves influenced the further development of the Italian style.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Begriff Renaissance (franz&#246;sisch Wiedergeburt) beschreibt die Kunstepoche der mit ihr beginnenden Neuzeit, vor allem im 15. (Quattrocento) und 16. Jahrhundert (Cinquecento). Die Bezeichnung wurde im 19. Jahrhundert gepr&#228;gt und gibt die Vorstellung wieder, nach dem Mittelalter habe die europ&#228;ische Kultur sich erneut an der griechischen und r&#246;mischen Antike orientiert. Typisch f&#252;r die Renaissance ist der Gedanke an den Menschen als Einzelperson, als sch&#246;pferisches Individuum.[PARAGRAPH:2]Bereits im Mittelalter schaute Europa auf die Antike zur&#252;ck, doch in den ein, zwei Jahrhunderten danach wurden unter anderem antike Texte wiederentdeckt und im Humanismus das antike Staatswesen studiert. Als der Renaissance gem&#228;&#223; gelten ferner die vielen Erfindungen und Entdeckungen, die man als Folge des geistigen Erwachens beschreiben kann.[PARAGRAPH:2]Als Kernzeitraum der Renaissance wird das 15. (Quattrocento) und 16. Jahrhundert (Cinquecento) angesehen. Das Ende der Epoche vollzieht sich im beginnenden 17. Jahrhundert in Italien durch den neu hervortretenden Stil des Barock. Im Norden Europas kam die Renaissance sp&#228;ter an und wurde auch erst sp&#228;ter von der neuen Kunstepoche des Barocks abgel&#246;st. Im protestantischen Nordeuropa wird der Epochenbegriff der Renaissance von dem der Reformation &#252;berlagert.[PARAGRAPH:2]Bei K&#252;nstlern der Renaissance denkt man in erster Linie an Italiener wie Leonardo da Vinci, Tizian und Donatello sowie an den Deutschen Albrecht D&#252;rer. Zu dieser Epoche geh&#246;ren aber auch bedeutende Schriftsteller von Dante Alighieri bis William Shakespeare. Der Staatsphilosoph Niccol&#242; Machiavelli gilt als Vertreter einer selbstbewussten Machtpolitik, Erasmus von Rotterdam wiederum steht f&#252;r Moral und Selbstreflexion. In der Musik verbindet man die Epoche vor allem mit verst&#228;rkter Mehrstimmigkeit und neuer Harmonie etwa bei Orlando di Lasso.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_RIGHTS_OF_MAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]"The Rights of Man", published by Thomas Paine in 1791, suggested that popular political revolution was permissible where a government had failed to safeguard its people, their natural rights and their interests. Defending both the French and American Revolutions from critics like Edmund Burke and others, Paine's ideas followed logically from those of Jean Jacques Rousseau in "The Social Contract" (1762) where he outlined the basis of legitimate political order in a republican context with sovereignty lying in the hands of the people based on definable laws. Paine also opposed the continuation of hereditary government, preferring a natural progression to representative democracy based on an agreed and written constitution.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Idee der Menschenrechte und deren staatlicher Umsetzung wurde in der Aufkl&#228;rung besonders von den Philosophen Thomas Hobbes, John Locke, Jean-Jacques Rousseau und Immanuel Kant gepr&#228;gt.[PARAGRAPH:2]Bereits der Dominikanerm&#246;nch Bartholom&#233; de Las Casas verwendet den Ausdruck 1552 in einem Schreiben zur Verteidigung der peruanischen Ureinwohner an den mit der Sklavenfrage befassten "Indienrat". Er spricht von den "Prinzipien der Rechte der Menschen" ("las reglas de los derechos humanos").[PARAGRAPH:2]Thomas Hobbes (1588-1679) ist zu erw&#228;hnen, obwohl er eigentlich kein Philosoph der Aufkl&#228;rung ist. Es gibt bei ihm keine direkten Menschenrechtsformulierungen, vielmehr ist nicht einmal ansatzweise von gleichen, unver&#228;u&#223;erlichen Rechten f&#252;r alle die Rede. Dennoch ist er aufgrund seiner Staatsphilosophie ein Vordenker der Menschenrechte. Nach dieser hat jeder Mensch im Naturzustand das Selbsterhaltungsrecht. Doch aufgrund der Unsicherheit und Gefahren des Naturzustandes verzichtet der Mensch auf diesen und seine damit verbundenen Naturrechte und gibt sie an den Staat ab. So gibt er dem Staat uneingeschr&#228;nkte Macht und ordnet das Menschenrecht dem Staat unter. Trotz der schwachen Stellung des Menschenrechts bei Thomas Hobbes hat die Tatsache, dass es &#252;berhaupt ein solches Recht geben kann, viele Philosophen beeinflusst.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_SHIPBUILDING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The construction of ships or vessels of all types traces its roots to well before recorded history. The early Egyptians and Phoenicians fashioned large ships whose hulls were formed from wooden planking fixed with sinews or reeds. Greek ships were equipped with multiple masts and sails and powered by several banks of oars. Viking longships were traditional "clinker" built with overlapping planks and large square sails. Later European vessels were more rounded,with broader beam, heavily curved at each end and equipped with vertical steerposts and a moveable rudder. Lateen sails were gradually combined with square-rigged types in the 15thC. to produce the caravels and carracks were the mainstay of the European navigators and explorers.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Geschichte des Schiffbaus l&#228;sst sich nach Epochen gliedern, es k&#246;nnen aber auch grundlegende Konstruktionsprinzipien unterschieden werden, die sich im auf &#252;berliefertem Erfahrungswissen basierenden Schiffbau oft &#252;ber Jahrhunderte hinweg weitgehend unver&#228;ndert gehalten haben.[PARAGRAPH:2]Zu Unterscheiden sind der Einbaum, seine Erweiterung zu prahmartigen Booten und solchen mit Setzbord sowie die bis ins 20. Jahrhundert &#252;bliche Schalenbauweise, bei der eine zun&#228;chst erstellte Holzschale durch nachtr&#228;glich eingesetzte Spanten stabilisiert wurde und die seit dem 15. Jahrhundert &#252;bliche Skelettbauweise, bei der zun&#228;chst der Kiel gelegt und Spanten aufgesetzt wurden und anschlie&#223;end verplankt wurde.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_SIEGE_ENGINES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A device designed to break or circumvent city walls and other fortifications in siege warfare, the earliest type of siege engines were probably the battering ram developed by the Assyrians and siege towers used by the Carthaginians against Greek colonies in Sicily. Greek inventions like those of Archimedes, were further refined by the Romans in their use of catapults, the onager, the ballista, the tortoise and the testudo. European devices like the mangonel and the traction trebuchet were replaced by the more advanced counterweight trebuchet first used by the Arabs during the Crusades. Siege warfare was at its apex in the European Middle Ages where protracted sieges against cities were often preferred to open field warfare.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Belagerungsger&#228;te, im historischen Sprachgebrauch auch mit dem Sammelbegriff Antwerk bezeichnet, umfassen Hilfsmittel zur Erst&#252;rmung und Maschinen zur Zerst&#246;rung oder Schw&#228;chung einer Befestigung.[PARAGRAPH:2]Solange Menschen sich in Befestigungen versteckten oder sich daraus verteidigten, mussten Angreifer Mittel und Wege finden, die Befestigung des Verteidigers zu zerst&#246;ren oder zu &#252;berwinden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Belagerungsmaschinen reichten von primitiven Konstruktionen wie Leitern und Rammen, die vor Ort hergestellt wurden und oft nur Belagerungsger&#228;tschaften waren, bis hin zu komplizierten Apparaten und Maschinen, die von den Belagerern mitgef&#252;hrt wurden.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_STEAM_ENGINES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As an engine that performs mechanical work using steam as its working fluid, machines using boiling water to produce motion date back nearly 2000 years but were not practical power producers. It was not until the 18thC. that designs which produced usable power were developed, initially vacuum engines for the removal of mine-water as invented by Thomas Newcomen in 1712. In the 1760s, James Watt greatly improved these engines, making them more fuel-efficient and cheaper to run, and introduced a rotary motion which made them suitable for driving factory machinery. But it was the invention of the more powerful high pressure steam engine by Richard Trevithick in 1800 that made steam the dominant power source of the Industrial Revolution.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Geschichte der Dampfmaschine reicht zur&#252;ck bis ins erste nachchristliche Jahrhundert - der erste Bericht &#252;ber eine technische, rudiment&#228;r als "Dampfmaschine" zu bezeichnende Apparatur, die Aeolipile (auch Heronsball genannt), stammt aus der Feder des griechischen Mathematikers Heron von Alexandria. In den Jahrhunderten, die den ersten neuzeitlichen Dampfmaschinen vorangingen, wurden dampfgetriebene "Maschinen" haupts&#228;chlich zu Demonstrationszwecken gebaut, um das Prinzip der Dampfkraft zu illustrieren. Die ersten Versuche einer Dampfmaschine kamen unter anderem von Blasco de Garay 1543, Denis Papin 1690 und Thomas Savery 1698 in Kassel. Sie alle waren aber ohne Erfolg.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die erste verwendbare Dampfmaschine wurde 1712 von Thomas Newcomen konstruiert und diente zum Abpumpen des Wassers in einem Bergwerk. Diese so genannte atmosph&#228;rische Dampfmaschine erzeugte durch Einspritzen von Wasser in einen mit Dampf gef&#252;llten Zylinder einen Unterdruck gegen&#252;ber der Atmosph&#228;re. Mit diesem Druckunterschied wurde der Kolben im Arbeitstakt vom atmosph&#228;rischen Luftdruck nach unten gedr&#252;ckt und anschlie&#223;end durch das Eigengewicht der anzutreibenden Pumpenstange wieder nach oben in die Ausgangsposition gezogen. Die Kraft&#252;bertragung zwischen Kolbenstange und Balancier erfolgte mittels einer Kette. Der Wirkungsgrad der newcomenschen Maschine lag bei 0,5 Prozent.[PARAGRAPH:2]James Watt, dem oft f&#228;lschlicherweise die Erfindung der Dampfmaschine zugeschrieben wird, verbesserte den Wirkungsgrad der Newcomenschen Dampfmaschine erheblich. Er verlagerte mit seiner 1769 patentierten Konstruktion einerseits den Abk&#252;hlvorgang aus dem Zylinder heraus in einen separaten Kondensator, andererseits belieferte er den Kolben abwechselnd von der einen und der anderen Seite mit Dampf. Auf der jeweils gegen&#252;berliegenden Seite &#246;ffnete er den Auslass zum Kondensator. So konnte Watt auf das mechanische R&#252;ckf&#252;hren des Kolbens verzichten, und die Maschine bei beiden Kolbenh&#252;ben Arbeit verrichten lassen. Zusammen mit der Erfindung des Wattschen Parallelogramms war es m&#246;glich, die Maschine ein Schwungrad drehen zu lassen. James Watt bezeichnete diese Erfindung als seine bedeutendste; sie gilt auch heute noch als Musterbeispiel f&#252;r die L&#246;sung der Aufgabe, eine geradlinige Bewegung in eine kreisf&#246;rmige nur mit Hilfe von Drehgelenken umzuwandeln.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_STIRRUP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The stirrup is a flat-bottomed ring fixed to a leather strap hanging on either side of a saddle to create a footrest for a person riding a horse, both as a support and an aid in mounting. Greatly improving the rider's ability to stay in the saddle and controlling his mount, it increased the animal's usefulness in communication, transportation and warfare. As a key factor in the creating and spreading of civilization, it may be just as important as the wheel and the printing press. Originating in China about 200AD it spread into Europe by the 7thC. and was widely adopted in the Middle Ages. With the rise of the armoured mounted knight and his retainers, it may also have helped initiate the development of the European feudal system.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Steigb&#252;gel in Form von ledernen Schlaufen f&#252;r die F&#252;&#223;e wurden etwa im 3. Jahrhundert v. Chr. von den Skythen erstmals benutzt und erst sehr viel sp&#228;ter von anderen europ&#228;ischen V&#246;lkern. Griechen und Karthager kannten sie nicht, die R&#246;mer lernten sie erst in der ausgehenden Sp&#228;tantike kennen (s. u.). W&#228;hrend die Hunnen noch keinen Sattel mit Steigb&#252;gel kannten, war dieser den sp&#228;teren eurasischen Reiternomaden wie den Awaren bekannt.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Weiterentwicklungen der Steigb&#252;gel, die von gepanzerten Reitern (Ritter) im Mittelalter verwendet wurden, machten die Steigb&#252;gel zum Bestandteil der Schutzwaffen der Ritter. Wie bei allen Schutzwaffen wurde die Gestaltung dieser Steigb&#252;gel gem&#228;&#223; dem Einsatztzweck und "der zu erwartenden Bedrohung" jeweils angepasst, was zu zahlreichen Formen dieser historischen Steigb&#252;gel f&#252;hrte.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_TRADING_COMPANIES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As a type of public or joint-stock company, trading companies generally put their shares for sale on the open market and were "listed" on the stock exchange. An early example was the Virginia Company, combining the overseas interests of the London Company and the Plymouth Company which established the colonies of Jamestown and Popham on the east coast of America. Also about 1600, the Dutch East India Company and the Honourable East India Company of England were established to develop favourable trade contacts and advantages in India and the East Indies. Similar companies were established in South America and the West Indies by Spain, Portugal, Britain, Holland and Denmark to exploit their trade interests in those regions.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Handelskompanien gab es in Italien seit dem 14. Jahrhundert. Diese operierten in der Levante. Zu den italienischen Staaten mit den wichtigsten Handelskompanien in dieser Zeit z&#228;hlten Pisa, Genua, Venedig und Florenz. Die Hochzeit der Handelskompanien lag vor allem im Zeitalter des Merkantilismus. Anfangs des 16. Jahrhunderts dominierte die Republik Venedig das Mittelmeer und dank ihrer Verbindungen in den mittleren Osten den Handel, insbesondere den Seeweg nach Indien, die Levante sowie den Indischen Ozean. Dies erm&#246;glichte Venedig die Kontrolle der Produkte aus dem Fernen Osten und dadurch auch die Kontrolle der europ&#228;ischen Wirtschaft. Trotzdem gelang es Antwerpen Zolllager f&#252;r den von Portugal importierten Pfeffer zu werden.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_VASSALAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A vassal, as developed during the rise of feudalism in Europe, was someone who enjoyed mutual rights and obligations with a lord or monarch, usually of military support and protection in exchange for guarantees which might entitle him to a certain terrain or "fief". Vassalage might involve an elaborate ceremony composed of declarations of homage and fealty backed by the Christian sacraments which formalized the concepts of lordship or "seigneurship" in a recognized pattern of individual social standing in the European Middle Ages. Increasingly society began to be organized around an elaborate pattern of overlapping hierarchies where each individual was bound by mutual rights, duties, honour and his own clearly defined obligations.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Vasall (Keltisch gwas, lat. vassus: Knecht) war im fr&#252;hen Mittelalter (6.?7. Jahrhundert) ein Herr, der sich freiwillig als Gefolgsmann in den Dienst eines anderen Herrn stellte und sich diesem f&#252;r bestimmte milit&#228;rische oder diplomatische Dienstleistungen verpflichtete. Der Vasall musste eine bestimmte Anzahl an Soldaten zur Verf&#252;gung stellen, um somit den Dienstherrn in dessen Krieg zu unterst&#252;tzen. Die Lehnspflicht bestand aber auch aus Abgaben, zum Beispiel f&#252;r die herrschaftlichen Kriegsdienste, oder aus &#228;hnlichen Leistungen. Der Vasall genoss im Gegenzug den Schutz seines Lehnsherren.[PARAGRAPH:2]Auch ein F&#252;rst konnte Vasall sein und sich der Oberherrschaft eines anderen F&#252;rsten unterwerfen. Ein gutes Beispiel hierf&#252;r ist die Beziehung des englischen zum franz&#246;sischen K&#246;nig im 12. Jahrhundert. Der englische K&#246;nig hatte zahlreiche Besitzungen in Frankreich, doch diese waren alle Lehnschaften des franz&#246;sischen K&#246;nigs. Der K&#246;nig von England war also dem K&#246;nig von Frankreich als dessen Lehnsmann untertan. Als Herzog der Normandie und von Guyenne, sowie Graf von Anjou, Maine, Berry, Bretagne, Touraine und Poitou war er zwar der m&#228;chtigste Vasall in Frankreich, aber immerhin ein Vasall, also Philipp II. zu Diensten verpflichtet, obwohl sie hierarchisch gleichgestellt waren.</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_EU_VAULTED_ARCHES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A vault is an architectural term for an arched form used to provide space with a ceiling or roof. The parts of a vault exert a thrust that require a counter resistance which is provided by the soil if built below ground but requires various means such as barreled or continuous vaults combined with buttresses to supply the extra needed resistance. Particularly in the Romanesque, Gothic and Baroque cathedrals of the European Middle ages, barrel vaults were replaced or supplemented by the introduction of more elaborate forms such as groin vaults, rib vaults, fan vaults and transverse ribbing which allowed the creation of higher, wider ceilings and open spaces that typified the greatest architectural wonders of European history.</English>
		<French>.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Da Gew&#246;lbe in der Regel erst in sich stabil werden, wenn der Schlussstein bzw. die Schlusssteine gesetzt sind (Ausnahme z. B. Santa Maria del Fiore in Florenz), m&#252;ssen sie &#252;ber Lehrger&#252;ste, die die innere Laibung von unten her festlegen, aufgemauert werden. Nach Setzen der Schlusssteine k&#246;nnen die Lehrger&#252;ste entfernt werden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Gew&#246;lbe wurden vorwiegend in Haustein, Backstein oder Bruchstein, seltener in Gussm&#246;rtel ausgef&#252;hrt. Besonders leichte Gew&#246;lbe stellte man aus Kalktuffstein oder Tuffstein oder hohlem, gebranntem, Topfstein her (Tuffgew&#246;lbe, Topfgew&#246;lbe).</German>
		<Italian>.</Italian>
		<Spanish>.</Spanish>
		<Portuguese>.</Portuguese>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
